[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most extensive maintenance check to be performed on an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-Check",
            "b) D-Check",
            "c) B-Check",
            "d) C-Check"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maintenance includes the installation or removal of a component from an aircraft or aircraft subassembly, but does not include: elementary work, servicing or any work done on an aircraft as part of the manufacturing process."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CAMP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous Air Mileage Program",
            "b) Continuous Air Maintenance Program",
            "c) Continuous Airworthiness Maintenance Program",
            "d) Continuous Airworthiness Mileage Program"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most extensive check to be performed on an aircraft is D-check, which occurs approximately every 5–6 years. A D-check basically takes the entire airplane apart for inspection and overhaul. Such a check can take up to 8 weeks to complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "The continuous inspection program for commercial aircraft in India, is approved by which of the following authorities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DGCA",
            "b) EASA",
            "c) FAA",
            "d) DCGA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CAMP refers to the Continuous Airworthiness Maintenance Program. Such a program includes both detailed and routine inspections of an aircraft. All commercial aircraft operators follow and plan such a program. "
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Aircraft Maintenance personnel are also known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aircraft Maintenance Engineer",
            "b) Aircraft Maintaining Engineer",
            "c) Air Maintenance Engineer",
            "d) Air Maintaining Engineer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Airlines and other commercial operators of large or turbine-powered aircraft follow a continuous inspection program approved by the Directorate General of Civil Aviation (DGCA) in India or by other airworthiness authorities such as Federal Aviation Agency (FAA), in the USA or the European Aviation Safety Agency (EASA), in Europe."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Who is responsible to review the airworthiness certiﬁcate, maintenance records, and other required paperwork to verify that the aircraft is airworthy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copilot",
            "b) Aircraft Maintenance Engineer",
            "c) Purser",
            "d) Pilot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aircraft maintenance personnel are also known as Aircraft Maintenance Engineer (AME), also called Licensed Aircraft Maintenance Engineer (LAME or L-AME)."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which is the most expensive maintenance check of all?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A-Check",
            "b) D-Check",
            "c) C-Check",
            "d) B-Check"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pilot in command of an aircraft is responsible to review the airworthiness certiﬁcate, maintenance records, and other required paperwork to assess and verify that the aircraft is airworthy. The pilot also conducts a preflight inspection of the aircraft to check for external damages."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Where do the heavier checks (C-check and D-check) take place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maintenance, repair and overhaul (MRO) company sites",
            "b) Airport bay",
            "c) Manufacturing sites",
            "d) Hangar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: D-check is the most expensive maintenance check to be performed on an aircraft. This is due to the large amount of manpower and equipment required to conduct a D-check."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "How many man hours does a D-check require?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 400",
            "c) 4,000",
            "d) 40,000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A D-check is also referred to as Heavy Maintenance Visit and it requires the most space of all maintenance checks. Due to the extensive amount of work done in D-checks, it requires up to 40,000 man hours. "
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "A maintenance release can also be called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Certificate of release to service (CRS)",
            "b) Maintenance release certificate",
            "c) Release certificate",
            "d) Certification of release to service"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aircraft maintenance checks are periodic checks that are performed on all aircraft after a certain amount of time/flying hours, to ensure that they are airworthy. Military aircraft may or may not follow maintenance programs similar to commercial aircraft operators. This is due to different roles performed by the aircraft and thus having different requirements."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ICAO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Commercial Aviation Organization",
            "b) International Civil Aviation Organization",
            "c) Indian Civil Aviation Organization",
            "d) Indian Commercial Aviation Organization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A maintenance release can also be called a certificate of release to service (CRS). The maintenance release is signed by a person authorized by the national airworthiness authority and it signifies that the aircraft is airworthy and can be released to service."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Which of the following issues Airworthiness Directive’s (ADs) in Australia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CASA",
            "b) Transport Canada",
            "c) New Zealand Civil Aviation Authority",
            "d) DGCA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ICAO refers to The International Civil Aviation Organization. The ICAO specifies international air navigation techniques and acts as a governing body to the aviation regulating authorities in different regions around the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "The maintenance carried out while an airplane is parked at an airport waiting for the next takeoﬀ is generally referred to as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Line maintenance",
            "b) Major maintenance",
            "c) General Maintenance",
            "d) Base Maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Civil Aviation Safety Authority (CASA) issues the ADs in Australia. ADs in India, Canada and New Zealand are issued by DGCA, Transport Canada and New Zealand Civil Aviation Authority respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "What is the full form of AMP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Maintenance Program",
            "b) Aircraft Maintaining Program",
            "c) Aircraft Maintenance Program",
            "d) Air Maintaining Program"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Continuous Airworthiness Maintenance Program (CAMP) includes both routine and detailed inspections. All commercial aircraft operators have such a program. Such programs are necessary for the aircraft’s airworthiness."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not true with respect to line maintenance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quick turnaround time",
            "b) Aircraft is refueled",
            "c) Critical instruments are checked for defects",
            "d) Performed at MRO sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In line maintenance the work is carried out on the gate, i.e. at the apron, under the skies. Line maintenance involves lesser number of technicians as compared to base maintenance. Time required for line maintenance is also much less than the time required for base maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "What is the full form of SRM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structure Repair Manual",
            "b) Structure Repairing Manual",
            "c) Structural Repair Manual",
            "d) Structural Repairing Manual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Unlike base maintenance, line maintenance does not require a large space such as MRO facility. Line maintenance offers a quick turnaround time and ensures on time departure of aircrafts."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Out of the following, which is not an important factor affecting the work of the line maintenance engineer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Weather",
            "c) Ground staff",
            "d) Fuel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The engineering team, with the assistance of the line maintenance MRO check’s the SRM – Structure Repair Manual – for allowable defects in the area in question."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Preflight inspection is conducted by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copilot",
            "b) Pilot",
            "c) Purser",
            "d) Ground staff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In line maintenance, the weather, time and the number of ground staff are very important factors affecting the work of the engineer."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "What is the full form of LRU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Line-replaced unit",
            "b) Line-repositioned unit",
            "c) Line-rested unit",
            "d) Line-replaceable unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pilots are required to follow up with their own pre ﬂight Inspection. The pre ﬂight inspection follows a checklist listing items that the pilot is to visually check for general condition as he or she walks around the airplane."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not true with respect to LRU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases system costs",
            "b) Improves quality",
            "c) Can be stocked",
            "d) Can be replaced quickly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LRU refers to Line-replaceable unit. The LRUs are aircraft components that are designed such that they can be replaced easily at a site. They are helpful in ensuring that the aircrafts do not go out of service due to a technical snag."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "How much time is required for line maintenance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 minutes",
            "b) 450 minutes",
            "c) 45 hours",
            "d) 450 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LRUs are helpful in bringing down repair and overhaul costs and help improve quality. Such units can be easily replaced in no time and help reduce flight delays by ensuring on time departure."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Line Maintenance is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heavy Maintenance",
            "b) Electrical Maintenance",
            "c) General Maintenance",
            "d) Routine Maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Line maintenance is a 45 minutes task during which the aircraft is refueled and all critical instruments are checked for defects."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "What is considered an aircraft cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Takeoff and landing",
            "b) Landing",
            "c) Takeoff",
            "d) Flying hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The occurrence of aircraft maintenance checks varies by the cycle count or the number of hours ﬂown since the last check. Aircraft cycle count refers to the takeoff and landing."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Preflight inspection is a part of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Landing",
            "b) Base Maintenance",
            "c) Takeoff",
            "d) Line Maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pilots are required to conduct their own preﬂight Inspection. The pilot also takes an external inspection of the aircraft to check its airworthiness. This inspection is a part of the line maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "How many pressurization cycles can a Boeing 747 endure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3,500",
            "b) 350",
            "c) 35,000",
            "d) 35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A Boeing 747 can endure about 35,000 pressurization cycles, post that metal fatigue sets in and the aircraft requires to undergo heavy maintenance and overhaul."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Airlines and other commercial operators of large or turbine-powered aircraft follow a continuous inspection program approved by the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) EASA",
            "b) DGCA",
            "c) CASA",
            "d) FAA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The continuous inspection program is approved by the Directorate General of Civil Aviation (DGCA) in India or by other airworthiness authorities such as Federal Aviation Agency (FAA) in the USA, Civil Aviation Safety Authority (CASA) in Australia or the European Aviation Safety Agency (EASA) in Europe."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Category B-check is performed at a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hangar",
            "b) Apron",
            "c) MRO site",
            "d) Parking bay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Category B-check needs about 150 man-hours and is usually performed within 1-3 days at an airport hangar. This check cannot be performed at the apron, like the Category-A check."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "How many checks are there in the base maintenance cycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 16",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The base maintenance cycle consists of six checks. These six checks are often referred to as C1, C2, C3, C4, C5 and C6 checks. These checks are a part of the base maintenance of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not true with respect to base maintenance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Costlier than line maintenance",
            "b) Greater man power required",
            "c) Requires smaller space",
            "d) More extensive than line maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Base maintenance usually demands greater man-hours and it can generally take up to 8 weeks to complete, depending on the aircraft and the number of technicians involved. It also requires the most space of all maintenance checks, and as such must be performed at a suitable maintenance base."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "How much time is required for C-check?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 weeks",
            "b) 2 months",
            "c) 2 days",
            "d) 2 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: C-check requires lesser space and manpower as compared to D-check. Such checks usually require up to 6000 man hours and are performed at a hangar or indoor facility."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "D-Check is also known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heavy Maintenance Visit",
            "b) Light Maintenance Visit",
            "c) Regular Maintenance Visit",
            "d) Unscheduled Maintenance Visit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: No, D-checks are scheduled checks. These checks require a significant amount of manpower and equipment and are performed at a suitable MRO site, thus need to be planned well in advance."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Airframe of an aircraft is its __________ structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical",
            "b) Mechanical",
            "c) Thermal",
            "d) Hydraulic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The airframe of an aircraft is its mechanical structure. The airframe comprises of the fuselage, wings, and undercarriage and excludes the propulsion system."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Why does the landing gear retract into the wings and/or fuselage during ﬂight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To decrease drag",
            "b) To increase airspeed",
            "c) To decrease airspeed",
            "d) To generate more thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aircrafts have landing gear that retract into the wings and/or fuselage to decrease drag during ﬂight. Drag slows down the aircraft, thus increasing the flying time between two places."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of the airframe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuselage",
            "b) Wing",
            "c) Stabilizing tail",
            "d) Landing gear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main parts of the airframe are the fuselage, wing, stabilizing tail and undercarriage. The landing gear is not a part of the airframe."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which was the first commercial aircraft with 50% of its structure weight made of carbon-fiber composite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 777",
            "b) Boeing 787",
            "c) Boeing 747",
            "d) Airbus A380"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Boeing 787 was the first commercial aircraft with 50% of its structure weight made of carbon-fiber composites, along 20% Aluminum and 15% titanium. It first flew in 2009."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "What material is used for aircraft fuselage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminum alloys",
            "b) Titanium alloys",
            "c) Silver alloys",
            "d) Metal alloys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aircraft fuselage is made of aluminum alloys along with other materials such as Zn, Mg and Cu. However modern aircrafts have started using carbon fiber materials in order to decrease the aircraft weight and in turn increase performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Landing gears are also known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stabilizers",
            "b) Empennage",
            "c) Undercarriage",
            "d) Aileron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wings of an aircraft are responsible for producing lift. Many diﬀerent styles and arrangements of wings have been used on heavier than air aircrafts. Some lighter than air aircraft also have wings."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about an airframe made with carbon-fiber composite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases drag",
            "b) Decreases thrust",
            "c) Higher cabin pressurization",
            "d) Higher wing aspect ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The landing gears are also known as undercarriage. It is the structure that supports an aircraft when it is not ﬂying and allows it to take oﬀ, land and taxi."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following supports an aircraft on the ground?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudder",
            "b) Engines",
            "c) Aileron",
            "d) Landing gear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbon-fiber material allows for a lower-drag along with higher wing aspect ratio and higher cabin pressurization. However, these materials have no effect on thrust."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "Which was the first widely produced general aviation aircraft manufactured with all composite construction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 787",
            "b) Airbus A350",
            "c) Cirrus SR20",
            "d) Bombardier CRJ700"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Landing gear is the structure that supports an aircraft when it is not ﬂying and allows it to manoeuvre on the ground. Most commonly, wheels are used but other equipment such as floats and skids can also be used, depending on the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "What do winglets do?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase thrust",
            "b) Reduce turbulence at the tips of an airplane’s wings",
            "c) Decrease thrust",
            "d) Increase turbulence at the tips of an airplane’s wings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fuselage is an aircraft’s main body section containing the cockpit or ﬂight deck along with the passenger cabin and cargo hold. It also often contains the engine(s)."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "The earliest aircraft were constructed primarily of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steel",
            "b) Aluminum",
            "c) Steel",
            "d) Wood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first widely produced aviation aircraft with all composite construction was Cirrus SR20. It first flew in 1995 and has a cruise speed of 287km/h."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Stabilizing tail is also known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudder",
            "b) Empennage",
            "c) Aileron",
            "d) Wingtip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The purpose of winglets is to reduce turbulence at the tips of an airplane’s wings. Winglets and sharklets are similar to each other. The wingtip vortices created by a large aircraft are strong enough to flip a smaller aircraft that maybe flying closely. Winglets are responsible to break these vortices thereby reducing drag on the airplane."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a retraction system for landing gear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic retraction system",
            "b) Thermal retraction system",
            "c) Manual retraction system",
            "d) Electrical retraction system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The earliest aircraft were constructed primarily of wood. Many newly certified aircraft are built from moulded composite materials, such as carbon fiber and titanium alloys."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "An aircraft engine generates __________ power.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical",
            "b) Mechanical",
            "c) Thermal",
            "d) Hydraulic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An aircraft engine is a component of the propulsion system for an aircraft that generates mechanical power. The power generated is used to keep the aircraft flying high in the air."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "The General Electric GE90 is a family of high-bypass __________ aircraft engines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turboshaft",
            "b) Turboprop",
            "c) Turbojet",
            "d) Turbofan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The General Electric GE90 is a family of high-bypass turbofan aircraft engines. It is built for the Boeing 777 by GE aviation. The engine offers thrust ratings from 81,000 to 115,000 lb."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "The Rolls-Royce Trent 900 is one of the power plant options for which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A380",
            "b) Boeing 747",
            "c) Airbus A320",
            "d) Airbus A350"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Rolls-Royce Trent 900 is a turbofan engine and is one of the power plant options available for the Airbus A380. Another power plant option for the A380 is the Engine Alliance GP7000."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which is the largest jet engine in the world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GE90",
            "b) Trent 800",
            "c) PW4000",
            "d) GE9X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The GE9X is the largest jet engine in the world, it is as wide as the body of a Boeing 737. The engine is manufactured by General Electric for the Boeing 777X."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "A turboprop is very efficient when operated at cruise speed of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200-400 mph",
            "b) 20-40 mph",
            "c) 10-100 mph",
            "d) 600-800 mph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Turboprops are extremely efficient when operated at cruise speeds of 200 to 400 mph. This is the ideal cruise speed for such engines, thus providing such efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "The last airliner that used turbojets was the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 737",
            "b) Airbus A330",
            "c) Concorde",
            "d) Boeing 767"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, in jet engines the oxygen necessary for fuel combustion comes from the air. The jet engines take in required oxygen through the engine blades and the process of combustion takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an aircraft engine manufacturer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BMW",
            "b) General Electric",
            "c) Pratt & Whitney",
            "d) Rolls-Royce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concorde was the last airliner that used turbojet. The Mach 2 airspeed offered by Concorde proved the engine to be highly efficient. Other aircrafts could not match such airspeeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "How many types of gas turbine engines are manufactured?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In commercial aviation, the major players in the manufacturing of turbofan engines are Pratt & Whitney, General Electric, Rolls-Royce, and CFM International."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Rolls-Royce Trent 800 engine generates a maximum thrust of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9,500lb",
            "b) 95,000lb",
            "c) 950lb",
            "d) 9,50,000lb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are four types of gas turbine engines: the turbojet, the turbofan, the turboprop, and the turboshaft."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "High-bypass turbofans are usually most efficient when the aircraft is traveling at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500-550 mph",
            "b) 50-55 mph",
            "c) 20-25 mph",
            "d) 200-250 mph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The CFM56 series is a family of high-bypass turbofan aircraft engines made by CFM International. CFM International is a French-American company headquartered in Cincinnati, Ohio, United States."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "In general aviation, the dominant manufacturer of turboprop engines has been __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maserati",
            "b) Pratt & Whitney",
            "c) Boeing",
            "d) Airbus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Rolls-Royce Trent 800 engine generates a maximum thrust of 95,000lb. It was designed to be used on the Boeing 777 and was first produced in 1996."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Turboshaft engines are used primarily for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UAVs",
            "b) Commercial aircrafts",
            "c) Cars",
            "d) Helicopters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High-bypass turbofans are usually most efficient when the aircraft is traveling at 500 to 550 miles per hour (800 to 885 km/h) i.e. the cruise speed of most large airliners."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "What is the full form of TEL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tetraethyllead",
            "b) Tetraethylenelead",
            "c) Tetraethollead",
            "d) Tetraethanelead"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In general aviation, the dominant manufacturer of turboprop engines has been Pratt & Whitney. However, General Electric in 2015 its entrance into the market."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ARINC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aeronautical Radio, Incorporated",
            "b) Aircraft Radio, Incorporated",
            "c) Aviation Radio, Incorporated",
            "d) Air Radio, Incorporated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ARINC refers to Aeronautical Radio, Incorporated. It is owned by Collins Aerospace and was founded in 1929. It provides transport communication systems for various industries like aviation, defense and healthcare."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "Aircraft AC systems operate on which of the following frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4Hz",
            "b) 40Hz",
            "c) 400Hz",
            "d) 4000Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All aircraft equipment’s using AC power supply, operates at a frequency of 400Hz. Such relatively high frequency helps in reducing the core size of equipment’s used."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "The international standards for avionics equipment are prepared by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aircraft Electronic Engineering Committee",
            "b) Airlines Electronic Engineering Committee",
            "c) Aeronautical Electronic Engineering Committee",
            "d) Aerospace Electronic Engineering Committee"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Airlines Electronic Engineering Committee (AECC) is the organization responsible for stating the international standards for avionics equipment’s. The equipment also satisfies ARINC standards."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a manufacturer of aircraft avionics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thales Group",
            "b) Rockwell Collins",
            "c) GE Aviation systems",
            "d) Mercedes-Benz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mercedes-Benz is not a manufacturer of aircraft avionics. However, Thales Group, Rockwell Collins and GE Aviation systems all manufacture aircraft avionics. Some other avionic equipment manufacturers are BAE systems and Panasonic Avionics Corporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of avionic systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flight Recorder",
            "b) Weather Radars",
            "c) Communication systems",
            "d) Empennage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The empennage acts as a stabilizer and is located on the tail of the aircraft. It is not a part of the avionic systems. However, flight recorders, weather radars and communication systems are all part of the avionic system."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "How many channels are present in the Cockpit Voice Recorder (CVR)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 4 channels in a commercial type recorder. They are Pilot, Co-pilot, Crew, and Centre-Area. The CVR is helpful in probing details of an aircraft crash, in case it happens."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "What is the frequency range of VHF (Very high frequency)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 MHz to 300 MHz",
            "b) 30 Hz to 300 Hz",
            "c) 30 KHz to 300 KHz",
            "d) 30 mHz to 300 mHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The radio frequency range from 30 MHz to 300 MHz is referred as Very high frequency (VHF).  The frequencies above VHF are known as Ultra high frequency (UHF) and the frequencies below VHF are called High frequency (HF)."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Radio altimeters are used up to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2,500 feet",
            "b) 3,000 feet",
            "c) 250 feet",
            "d) 300 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radio altimeters provide data to the Flight computers, which is then displayed on the Flight displays, for the pilots. These altimeters only provide readings up to 2,500 feet, above which pressure systems are used to determine the flight altitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Autopilot was first invented by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lawrence Sperry",
            "b) William Boeing",
            "c) Nikola Tesla",
            "d) Wright Brothers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The autopilot feature was invented by Lawrence Sperry. It was introduced during the Second World War to ensue bomber planes fly steady enough to hit precision targets from thousands of feet in the sky."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "The VHF communication system works up to the maximum airband of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 106.975 kHz",
            "b) 136.975 kHz",
            "c) 106.975 MHz",
            "d) 136.975 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The onboard communications between the pilots and crew, crew and passengers and pilots and passengers are all made using aircraft intercoms and onboard communication systems installed on the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "What is the full form of WAAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wide Area Aircraft System",
            "b) Wide Area Augmentation System",
            "c) Wide Aircraft Augmentation System",
            "d) Wide Air Augmentation System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: WAAS refers to Wide Area Augmentation System. It is an air navigation system developed by the FAA, designed to improve the precision of GPS."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about LORAN?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Expensive",
            "b) Stands for Long Range Navigation",
            "c) Operated at higher frequencies",
            "d) Range up to 1,500 miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: LORAN refers to Long Range Navigation. It was a system developed during the Second World War in the USA. It was operated at lower frequencies and offered a range up to 1,500 miles."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Which of the following organizations regulates the safety and reliability standards of avionic and other aircraft equipment, in the USA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DGCA",
            "b) FBI",
            "c) NASA",
            "d) FAA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Federal Aviation Administration regulates the safety and reliability standards of avionic and other aircraft equipment, in the USA. The regulating authorities are different for other countries in the world. For example, DGCA regulates the safety and reliability standards of avionic and other aircraft equipment in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "ARINC 708 is a type of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weather radar",
            "b) Satellite",
            "c) Sensor",
            "d) Altimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ARINC 708 is a weather radar used in commercial aircrafts. It is not the sole radar used to determine weather conditions around the aircraft, it is supplemented by various other ground sensing and proximity radars."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a data transfer standard for aircraft avionics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) IEEE 1394b",
            "b) ARINC 664",
            "c) MIL-STD-1760",
            "d) ARINC 429"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ARINC 429 is a data transfer standard for aircraft avionics. It is an alternative to MIL-STD-1553. It has a self-synchronizing and self-clocking data bus protocol. It has a 32 bit data word."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "FMS refers to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel management systems",
            "b) Fare management systems",
            "c) Flight management systems",
            "d) Flight managing systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FMS is an abbreviation for flight management systems. Most commercial aircrafts with autopilot use FMS, so that the aircraft can keep flying without the pilot’s intervention in some certain phases of the flight."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to help pilots fly at low altitudes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward looking infrared",
            "b) Terrain-following radar",
            "c) Head-up display",
            "d) ARINC 629"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sonobuoys are used to determine the location of enemy submarines. They are relatively small buoys, which are dropped from aircrafts deployed on underwater research and warfare."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Ground-proximity warning systems use ___________ altimeters.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radio",
            "b) Sound",
            "c) Radar",
            "d) Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Terrain-following radar (TFR) help aircrafts fly at low altitudes. These are fitted into aircrafts which fly relatively close to the ground at a constant flight level. Such flights are sometimes referred to as terrain hugging flights."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "What is the full form of TAWS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Terrain awareness warning system",
            "b) Traffic awareness warning system",
            "c) Terrain awareness waking system",
            "d) Traffic awareness waking system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ground-proximity warning systems use radar altimeters. The GPWS is used to avoid the aircraft being unintentionally flown into the ground or an obstacle. It improves flight safety."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Which was the first U.S. jet fighter with twin tails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lockheed Martin F-35 Lightning II",
            "b) Sukhoi SU-57",
            "c) Sukhoi SU-30",
            "d) Grumman F-14 Tomcat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: TAWS refers to the Terrain awareness warning system, it may also be called a controlled flight into terrain. The system is used for avoiding unintended impacts with the ground during the flying phases."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "The three critical flight dynamics parameters are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roll, pitch and yaw",
            "b) Roll, pitch and jaw",
            "c) Roll, play and yaw",
            "d) Roll, play and jaw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The three critical flight dynamics parameters are roll, pitch and yaw. They may also be referred to as the angles of rotation w.r.t. the aircraft’s three principal axes about its center of gravity."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What happens if an aircraft yaws about its center of gravity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A sideslip angle arises",
            "b) Aircraft will crash",
            "c) Aircraft will start descending",
            "d) Angle of attack increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When an aircraft yaws about its center of gravity, it creates a sideslip angle. It is the angle between the wheels of an aircraft and the direction in which the aircraft is travelling."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives the viscosity of flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach Number",
            "b) Knudsen Number",
            "c) Specific heat ratio",
            "d) Reynolds Number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Viscosity of the flow is given by Reynolds Number. It is represented by Re. Mach number indicates the compressibility of flow and Knudsen number indicates rarefaction of the flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an aerodynamic coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure coefficient",
            "b) Absolute temperature",
            "c) Lift coefficient",
            "d) Drag coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Absolute temperature is not an aerodynamic coefficient. However, pressure coefficient, lift coefficient and drag coefficient are all aerodynamic coefficients. A few other aerodynamic coefficients are lateral force coefficient and friction coefficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about yaw?",
        "Options": [
            "a) About the vertical body axis",
            "b) Positive with the nose to starboard",
            "c) Measured in Hertz",
            "d) Type of rotation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Yaw rotation is the rotation of a body, which changes the direction in which it is pointing. It is an essential flight dynamic and is usually measured in degrees per second or radians per second."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "The equilibrium roll angle is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roll angle",
            "b) Angle of incidence",
            "c) Zero bank angle",
            "d) Angle of attack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flight dynamics studies the stability and control of vehicles travelling through air. It does not study the efficiency of these vehicles; however, flight dynamics parameters are designed so as to improve the efficiency of these vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which is the most dominant force in spacecraft flight dynamics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravitational force",
            "b) Nuclear force",
            "c) Air resistance force",
            "d) Lift and drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The equilibrium roll angle is known as zero bank angle; it may also be called wings level. The three critical flight dynamics refer to rotations about the respective axes starting from a defined equilibrium state."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Control systems adjust the orientation of a vehicle about its __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch",
            "b) Wheels",
            "c) Centre of mass",
            "d) Centre of gravity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most dominant force in spacecraft flight dynamics, is the gravitational force. This is because aerodynamic forces affecting the spacecraft in air, are very small, thereby making gravitational force dominant."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Spacecraft flight dynamics does not involve which of the following forces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propulsive force",
            "b) Gravitational force",
            "c) Electromagnetic force",
            "d) Lift and drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The control systems adjust the orientation of a vehicle about its centre of gravity. The control systems help rotate the aircraft in pitch, roll and yaw. It may be used to pitch the aircraft up or down."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "What are the major sources of change in the aerodynamic forces and moments applied to an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle of attack of the wing and the angle of attack",
            "b) Angle of attack of the wing and the angle of attack of the vertical tail",
            "c) Angle of attack of the wing and the angle of incidence",
            "d) Angle of incidence and the angle of attack of the vertical tail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aircrafts increase or decrease the lift generated by the wings, by increasing or decreasing the angle of attack. Angle of attack is adjusted by changing the position of the nose of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Aircrafts are streamlined from nose to tail to reduce __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbulence",
            "b) Thrust",
            "c) Gravitational force",
            "d) Drag"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Spacecraft flight dynamics does not include electromagnetic force. However, propulsive force, lift and drag and gravitational force are all part of spacecraft flight dynamics. Propulsive forces are most dominant in rockets."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Angle of attack of the vertical tail is also known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sideslip angle",
            "b) Critical angle",
            "c) Zero bank angle",
            "d) Angle of incidence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two major sources of change in the aerodynamic forces and moments applied to an aircraft are the angle of attack of the wing and the angle of attack of the vertical tail. The two angles are important to maintain the center of gravity of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft systems includes an actuator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydraulic systems",
            "b) Electronic systems",
            "c) Communication systems",
            "d) Control systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The aircrafts are streamlined from nose to tail to reduce drag on the aircraft. Increased drag reduces the airspeed of an aircraft and hence increases flying time."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Drag is increased so as to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slow the aircraft to a safe speed for landing",
            "b) Decrease turbulence",
            "c) Accelerate the aircraft to a safe speed for landing",
            "d) Increase thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Drag is increased so as to slow the aircraft to a safe speed for landing. Drag offers negative impact to the airspeed thus slowing down the aircraft, thereby offering a safe landing."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Which of the following controls the pitch of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flaps",
            "b) Rudder",
            "c) Spoiler",
            "d) Elevator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The elevator is a flight control surface controlling the pitch of an aircraft. It is also responsible for adjusting the angle of attack, and hence the lift of an aircraft. It is usually located at the ear of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "The combination of ailerons and elevators is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alevon",
            "b) Spoiler",
            "c) Elevon",
            "d) Rudder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The combination of ailerons and elevators is called elevon. Their respective control inputs are also combined and it reduces the pilot’s workload. They are mostly used on tailless aircrafts."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a part of the wing assembly of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stabilizer",
            "b) Edge flaps",
            "c) Rudder",
            "d) Elevator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The edge flaps are a part of the wing assembly of an aircraft. They are used to increase the lift of an aircraft. Stabilizer, rudder and elevator are all situated at the rear of an aircraft and are a part of the tail assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "The primary control of yaw is with the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aileron",
            "b) Elevator",
            "c) Rudder",
            "d) Elevon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The primary control of yaw is with the rudder. Yaw changes the direction in which the aircraft’s nose is pointing. In addition to the rudder, ailerons also have an effect on the yaw."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "The term canard is used to describe the __________ configuration of an aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seating",
            "b) Wing",
            "c) Flap",
            "d) Engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, ailerons are used to steer the aircraft either left or right. They are mounted on the edge of each wing and work in opposite directions. Raising the aileron, reduces the lift on the wing and lowering the aileron, increases the lift."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "What is the full form of UAVs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unmanned air vehicles",
            "b) Uncharted aerial vehicles",
            "c) Uncharted air vehicles",
            "d) Unmanned aerial vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Canard refers to a wing arrangement in aircrafts. In canard configuration, a small forewing is placed ahead of the main wing. The Wright Flyer of 1903 had a canard arrangement."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a secondary control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slats",
            "b) Ailerons",
            "c) Spoilers",
            "d) Air brakes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: UAVs refers to unmanned aerial vehicles. These are vehicles without a human pilot on board. Examples of UAVs are spaceships and drones. They are controlled using a ground based controller and a communication system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "For an aircraft whose left wing is pointing straight down, its transverse axis is __________ to the ground.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Opposite",
            "b) Parallel",
            "c) Perpendicular",
            "d) Adjacent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. Spoilers are used to reduce lift on an aircraft by hampering the flow of wind over its wings. They are used for reducing lift while landing an aircraft. They allow aircraft to lose altitude without gaining significant airspeed."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "What is the rotation about longitudinal axis called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roll",
            "b) Pitch",
            "c) Yaw",
            "d) Jaw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An aircraft whose left wing is pointing straight down, will have its transverse axis perpendicular to the ground. Further, its vertical axis will be parallel w.r.t. the ground. These axes are relative to the earth and will change with the change in position of the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "The rudder is a part of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undercarriage",
            "b) Empennage",
            "c) APU",
            "d) Engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The axis passing through the aircraft from nose to tail is called as longitudinal axis. Rotation about the longitudinal axis is called roll. Further, the angular displacement about it is called bank."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of flight control systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ailerons",
            "b) Elevators",
            "c) Radars",
            "d) Flaps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rudder is a part of the empennage. More specifically, it is mounted on the vertical stabilizer, at the rear end of the aircraft. If the pilot pushes the left pedal, rudder is deflected left and similarly when the pilot pushes the right pedal, rudder is deflected right."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "What is the full form of FBW?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fare-by-wire",
            "b) Fuel-by-wire",
            "c) Force-by-wire",
            "d) Fly-by-wire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Radars are not a part of flight control systems. However, ailerons, elevators and flaps are all part of the flight control systems. Some other flight control systems are elevens and flaperons."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Why are flaps deflected downwards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To decrease lift",
            "b) To increase lift",
            "c) To decrease the effective curvature of the wing",
            "d) To increase the effective curvature of the wing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: FBW refers to fly-by-wire. Fly-by-wire is a control system that replaces manual flight controls of an aircraft with an electronic interface. Flight controls are controlled through electronic signals, which are transmitted using wires."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Which of the following axes passes from wingtip to wingtip through an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical axis",
            "b) Horizontal axis",
            "c) Transverse axis",
            "d) Longitudinal axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flaps are deflected downwards to increase the effective curvature of the wing. Flaps are used during descent or take off. They are used to reduce stalling speed of an aircraft and are mostly used during low speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Airbrakes are used to increase __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lift",
            "b) Drag",
            "c) Pitch",
            "d) Thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The transverse axis passes from wingtip to wingtip through an aircraft. It may also be called the lateral axis. Rotation along this axis is called pitch, which is controlled by elevators."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "The airbus A320 family does not include which of the following aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A318",
            "b) A321",
            "c) A350",
            "d) A319"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The A350 is not a part of the A320 family of aircraft. However, A318, A319 and A321 are all part of the A320 family. The family also includes A320neo."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the launch customer of the A320 family?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air France",
            "b) Air India",
            "c) Lufthansa",
            "d) British Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Air France was the launch customer of the A320 family. It was launched in March, 1984 and first flew on 22nd February 1987."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "When was the A318 introduced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1993",
            "b) 1990",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 2003"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The A318 is an extended part of the A320 family. It was introduced in 2003. Other extended members of the A320 family are A319 and A321."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft competes with the A320 family?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Douglas DC-3",
            "b) Boeing 737",
            "c) Boeing 777",
            "d) Bombardier Dash 8-Q400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The airbus A320 family competes with the Boeing 737. Both aircraft offer short to medium range flights. The family has also competed with the 717and 757."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Where is the final assembly line for A320s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frankfurt, Germany",
            "b) Texas, USA",
            "c) Hamburg, Germany",
            "d) Toulouse, France"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The final assembly line for A320s is located in Toulouse, France. However, the A318s, A319s and A321s final assembly line is in Hamburg, Germany. An airbus factory in Tianjin, china also manufactures A319s, A320s and A321s."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "What is the full form of NEO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neat engine option",
            "b) New emission option",
            "c) New engine option",
            "d) Neat emission option"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ACJ business jet is a part of the A320 family of aircrafts. These are corporate aircrafts, manufactured in Toulouse, France. It is a narrow body aircraft and comes in four different configurations."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as the stretched A320?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A321",
            "b) A319",
            "c) Boeing 737",
            "d) MD-80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: NEO refers too new engine option. The A320neo was introduced in December 2010 and first flew with Lufthansa on 25 January 2016. Two new engines, with large sharklets were introduced to improve fuel efficiency. "
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a supplier of engines for the A320 family?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Aero Engines",
            "b) CFM International",
            "c) Pratt & Whitney",
            "d) General Electric"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The A321 is referred to as the stretched A320. It was the first derivative of the A320 and was launched in November 1988. It first flew on 11 March 1993."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the world’s first airliner with digital fly-by-wire flight control systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A330",
            "b) A350",
            "c) A320",
            "d) A380"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: General Electric does not supply engines for the A320 family of aircrafts. However, Cfm International, Pratt & Whitney and International Aero Engines all supply engines for the A320 family."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Which of the following airline is the world’s largest operator of the A320 family of aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EasyJet",
            "b) American Airlines",
            "c) Indigo",
            "d) Spicejet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False. Swissair was the first airline to take delivery of the A319. The aircraft was delivered to Swissair on 25 April 1996. A319 has been a popular aircraft with low cost airlines, such as EasyJet."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "The maiden flight of the Airbus A321 flew with which of the following engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trent 800",
            "b) CFM56-5B",
            "c) Trent 900",
            "d) IAE V2500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The A320 is the world’s first airliner with digital fly-by-wire flight control systems. It is a system that replaces manual flight controls in an aircraft with electronic interface systems. The signals are transmitted through wires."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "How long is the A320 wing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 33.91 m",
            "b) 3.91 m",
            "c) 63.91 m",
            "d) 13.91 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: American airlines is the world’s largest operator of the A320 family of aircraft. As of September 30 2017, it has 392 aircraft in service."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which was the second airline to receive the A321, after Lufthansa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ryanair",
            "b) Air Mauritius",
            "c) Alitalia",
            "d) Qatar Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maiden flight of the Airbus A321 flew with the IAE V2500 engine. It is a turbofan engine, manufactured by International Aero Engines. The engine was certified by the FAA in 1988."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CEO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Current emission option",
            "b) Current engine option",
            "c) Compact engine option",
            "d) Compact emission option"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ceo refers to current engine option. For example, the A330 referred to as A330ceo has been replaced by the newer A330neo, which includes a new engine and other upgrades."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which of the following nations, have not placed an order for the A330 MRTT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Australia",
            "b) France",
            "c) Sri Lanka",
            "d) Germany"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sri Lanka has not placed any orders for the A330 MRTT. However, Australia, France and Germany have all placed orders for the aircraft. The aircrafts will be inducted into the respective Air Forces of each county."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft was based on the A330 MRTT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) KC-45",
            "b) A340",
            "c) KC-135",
            "d) MD-80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The KC-45 aircraft was based on the A330 MRTT. The KC-45 was a proposed mid-air refueling tanker aircraft, which aimed to replace the ageing KC-135 tankers, in the U.S. Airforce."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "When was the A330 neo launched?",
        "Options": [
            "a) December 2016",
            "b) December 2014",
            "c) July 2016",
            "d) July 2014"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The A330 neo was launched in July 2014, at the Farnborough Airshow. The aircraft offered 14% better fuel economy per seat and was powered by the newer Trent 7000 engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft was expected to replace the A330-300?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A350-700",
            "b) A350-900",
            "c) A330neo",
            "d) A380-800"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The A350-900 was expected to replace the A330-300. However, Airbus expected the A330-300 to continue selling up to 2020. The A350-900 offered long range flights with increased efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "The A330 wing is swept back at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 degrees",
            "b) 60 degrees",
            "c) 30 degrees",
            "d) 13 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the A330 was the first airbus aircraft to have Rolls-Royce Engines. The aircraft was powered by the Trent 700. An engine, solely developed for the A330, providing 311kN of thrust."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an engine choice on the A330?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pratt & Whitney PW4000",
            "b) Rolls-Royce Trent 700",
            "c) General Electric CF6",
            "d) Rolls-Royce Trent 800."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The A330 wing is swept back by 30 degrees and it allows a maximum operating Mach number of 0.86. The wings also have winglets on either sides."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "The A330-200F is a __________ aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Military",
            "b) Cargo",
            "c) Tanker",
            "d) Commercial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Rolls-Royce Trent 800 is not an engine choice for the A330. The Trent 800 was designed for the 777 family of aircrafts. Pratt & Whitney PW4000, Rolls-Royce Trent 700 and General Electric CF6 were the three engine options for A330."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Rolls-Royce Trent 800 engine generates a maximum thrust of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7,100 lbf",
            "b) 71,100 lbf",
            "c) 710 lbf",
            "d) 7,11,000 lbf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The A330-200F is a cargo aircraft. It is based on the A330-200 and is capable of carrying 70 tons of cargo up to 5,900km. As of February 2019, Airbus had delivered 38 of these aircrafts with four unfulfilled orders."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "General Electric CF6 is a family of __________ engines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbofan",
            "b) Turbojet",
            "c) Turboprop",
            "d) Turboshaft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Beluga XL is based on the Airbus A330. It offers 30% more space than its predecessor, the Airbus Beluga and first flew on 19 July 2018."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the launch operator of the A330-300?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air New Zealand",
            "b) Air Inter",
            "c) Air India",
            "d) Air Mauritius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Rolls-Royce Trent 700 engine generates a maximum thrust of 71,100 lbf. It was designed to be used on the Airbus A330 and was certified in January 1994."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "What is the typical seating arrangement in an A330 business class?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-1-2",
            "b) 1-2-1",
            "c) 1-1-1",
            "d) 2-2-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The General Electric CF6 is a family of high bypass turbofan engines. The engines were replaced by the newer GEnx engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an A330 variant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A330-200",
            "b) A330 MRTT",
            "c) A330-100",
            "d) A330-200F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Air Inter was the launch operator of the A330-300. The aircraft came into service on 17 January 1994. Air Inter was a semi-public French airline."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "The A350XWB is a __________ range aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Short",
            "d) Regional"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The A350XWB is a long range aircraft, developed by Airbus. It was introduced to compete with the Boeing 787 and the 777."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the launch operator of the A350-900?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Canada",
            "b) Air Asia",
            "c) Qatar Airways",
            "d) Etihad Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Qatar Airways was the launch operator of the A350-900. The aircraft first entered service on 15 January 2015."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "What is the full form of XWB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xtra-Wide-Body",
            "b) Xtra-Width-Body",
            "c) Xtra-Wind-Body",
            "d) Xtra-Widened-Body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: XWB refers to Xtra-Wide-Body. The abbreviation is used to refer to the A350 aircraft as A350 XWB. It is a twin engine aircraft, introduced to succeed the A340."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Engine thrust reversers for the A350 are supplied by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microsoft",
            "b) Tesla",
            "c) Suzuki",
            "d) UTC Aerospace Systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The engine thrust reversers for the A350 are supplied by UTC Aerospace Systems. The company also supplies nacelles for the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operator of the A350?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indigo",
            "b) Finnair",
            "c) Iberia",
            "d) Air China"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Indigo is not an operator of the A350. However, Finnair, Iberia and Air China all have A350 aircrafts in their respective fleets."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The world’s longest flight between Singapore Changi and Newark International Airport is operated by which of the following airlines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lufthansa",
            "b) Etihad Airways",
            "c) Singapore Airlines",
            "d) American Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the ACJ350 is derived from the A350-900ULR. It is a corporate jet, developed by Airbus. The aircraft offers a range of up to 20,000km."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "What is the wing sweep angle of the A350, at a Mach 0.85 cruise speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.319 degrees",
            "b) 319 degrees",
            "c) 31.9 degrees",
            "d) 3.19 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The world’s longest flight between Singapore Changi and Newark International Airport is operated by Singapore Airlines. The inaugural flight took 17h 52m to travel between the two cities."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Which of the following supplies the auxiliary power unit for the A350?",
        "Options": [
            "a) General Electric",
            "b) Honeywell",
            "c) BMW",
            "d) Tesla"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wing sweep angle of the A350, at a Mach 0.85 cruise speed is 31.9 degrees. The wings are 64.75 m in length."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Rolls-Royce Trent XWB engine generates a maximum thrust of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9,700 lbf",
            "b) 97,000 lbf",
            "c) 970 lbf",
            "d) 9,70,000 lbf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The auxiliary power unit for the A350 is supplied by Honeywell. The company also supplies other avionic equipment for the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "What is the maximum operating speed of the A350?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.89",
            "b) Mach 0.089",
            "c) Mach 8.9",
            "d) Mach 89"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The aircraft was planned to enter into service in 2013, however its entry into service was delayed up to mid-2017. The aircraft was launched in 2006."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the launch customer of the A350-900ULR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qatar Airways",
            "b) Singapore Airlines",
            "c) Vistara",
            "d) Emirates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Rolls-Royce Trent XWB engine generates a maximum thrust of 97,000lb. It was exclusively designed to be used on the Airbus A350 XWB and was developed from the Rolls-Royce Trent 1000."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ULR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultra-Light Reach",
            "b) Ultra-Long Reach",
            "c) Ultra-Light Range",
            "d) Ultra-Long Range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum operating speed of the A350 XWB is Mach 0.89. The A350-1000 is heavier in comparison to the A350-900."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "What is the maximum takeoff weight of the A350?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 275 tonnes",
            "b) 2750 tonnes",
            "c) 3000 tonnes",
            "d) 300 tonnes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Singapore Airlines is the launch customer of the A350-900ULR. The airline is operating the aircraft in two class configuration featuring Business and Premium Economy."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "When was the A380 program launched?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 19 January 2010",
            "b) 19 December 2010",
            "c) 19 January 2000",
            "d) 19 December 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The A380 program was launched on 19 December 2000. It was introduced by Airbus to challenge the Boeing 747, in the long haul market."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the last airline to place an order for the A380?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Canada",
            "b) Air Asia",
            "c) Emirates",
            "d) Etihad Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Emirates was the last airline to place an order for the A380, it reduced its A380 orders in favor of the A350 and the A330neo. Subsequently, Airbus announced that A380 production would end by 2021."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft has 2 flight decks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A380",
            "b) A350",
            "c) 777",
            "d) 787"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Airbus A380 has two flight decks and is a full length double decker aircraft. A350, 777 and 787 all have a single flight deck."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the longest A380 route?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dubai-Muscat",
            "b) Singapore-New York",
            "c) Dubai-Auckland",
            "d) Delhi-Frankfurt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The longest A380 route is from Dubai to Auckland. The flight is operated by Emirates and it covers a distance of 14,203 kilometers."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operator of the A380?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thai Airways",
            "b) Air India",
            "c) British Airways",
            "d) Malaysia Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Air India is not an operator of the A380. However, Thai Airways, British Airways and Malaysia Airlines all have A380 aircrafts in their respective fleets."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "What is the typical economy class layout in an A380?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-2-3",
            "b) 3-3-3",
            "c) 3-4-3",
            "d) 2-4-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the A380 plus was proposed by Airbus at the June 2017 Paris Air Show. However, the aircraft has not been produced till date and stands as an undeveloped variant."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Which of the following airlines introduced shower spas in first class on its A380s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Singapore Airlines",
            "b) Emirates",
            "c) Qatar Airways",
            "d) Lufthansa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. There are 8 liquid crystal displays in the cockpit of an A380. The displays are 15cm by 20cm in size, all physically identical and interchangeable."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "The Airbus A380 is certified for up to __________ passengers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 753",
            "b) 653",
            "c) 553",
            "d) 853"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The typical economy class layout in an A380 is 3-4-3. The typical business class and first class layout are 2-2-2 and 1-2-1 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "What is the maximum design speed of the A380?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.96",
            "b) Mach 0.096",
            "c) Mach 9.6",
            "d) Mach 96"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Emirates introduced shower spas in first class on its A380s. It allowed each first class passenger five minutes of hot water."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "Airbus delivered the 100th A380 to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Canada",
            "b) Malaysia Airlines",
            "c) Vistara",
            "d) Emirates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False. The Airbus A380 offers a range of 8000nmi, which is approximately 14,800kms. The aircraft is mostly used on long haul routes."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "The first A380 was revealed on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18 December 2010",
            "b) 18 December 2005",
            "c) 18 January 2010",
            "d) 18 January 2005"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Airbus A380 is certified for up to 853 passengers. Although, it offers a typical seating capacity of 525 passengers. It can be configured into different class configurations."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "What is the maximum takeoff weight of the A380?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600 tonnes",
            "b) 6000 tonnes",
            "c) 60 tonnes",
            "d) 60,000 tonnes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum design speed of the A380 was Mach 0.96. It was successful in attaining this speed on 1 December 2005."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the world’s largest twinjet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 777",
            "b) Boeing 747",
            "c) Boeing 737",
            "d) Boeing 787"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Boeing 777 is the world’s largest twinjet. The aircraft is commonly referred to as Triple Seven and is powered by 2 jet engines, thus the name twinjet."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "When is the 777X scheduled to enter service?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2025",
            "b) 2030",
            "c) 2020",
            "d) 2022"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 777X is scheduled to enter service by 2020. Boeing announced the development of the third-generation of the 777, in November 2013."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an engine choice for the 777?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolls-Royce Trent 800",
            "b) General Electric GE90",
            "c) Pratt & Whitney PW4000",
            "d) Rolls-Royce Trent 700"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Rolls-Royce Trent 700 is not an engine choice for the 777. However, Rolls-Royce Trent 800, General Electric GE90 and Pratt & Whitney PW4000 are all engine choices for the 777."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the launch customer of the 777?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EasyJet",
            "b) United Airlines",
            "c) Qatar Airways",
            "d) Virgin Atlantic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: United Airlines was the launch customer of the 777. The aircraft entered into commercial service on 7 June 1995."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the only customer to have operated all 777 variants produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thai Airways",
            "b) Air India",
            "c) British Airways",
            "d) Emirates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Emirates is the only customer to have operated all 777 variants produced. The variants are -200, -200ER, -200LR, -300, -300ER, and 777F."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "What is the typical economy class layout in a Boeing 777?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-2-3",
            "b) 3-3-3",
            "c) 3-4-3",
            "d) 2-4-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the 777 is Boeing’s first fly-by-wire airliner. It has computer mediated controls and control signals are transmitted through wires."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "The wings of a 777 are swept back at __________ degrees for a cruise speed of Mach 0.83.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 316 degrees",
            "b) 31.6 degrees",
            "c) 0.316 degrees",
            "d) 3.16 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The wings of the 777 also serve as fuel storage, longer range models can carry up to 47,890 US gallons of fuel."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft holds the record for the longest non-stop flight of a passenger airliner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 777-200LR",
            "b) Boeing 777-200ER",
            "c) Boeing 777F",
            "d) Boeing 777X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The typical economy class layout in a Boeing 777 is 3-4-3. The typical business class and first class layout are 2-3-2 and 1-2-1 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "What is the maximum speed of the 777?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.87",
            "b) Mach 0.087",
            "c) Mach 8.7",
            "d) Mach 87"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wings of a 777 are swept back at 31.6 degrees, for a cruise speed of Mach 0.83. The cruise speed was revised up to Mach 0.84 after flight tests."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Boeing delivered the 100th 777 to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Canada",
            "b) Malaysia Airlines",
            "c) Vistara",
            "d) Emirates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False. The Boeing 777 offers a range up to 8,555nmi, which is approximately 15,844kms. The aircraft is mostly used on long haul routes."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "The 777F first flew on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) July 14, 2019",
            "b) July 14, 2000",
            "c) July 14, 2008",
            "d) July 14, 2010"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Boeing 777-200LR holds the record for the longest non-stop flight of a passenger airliner. It flew 11,664nmifrom Hong Kong to London in 22 hours and 42 minutes and was logged in the Guinness World Records."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "What is the ICAO designation for the Boeing 777-300?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B773",
            "b) B772",
            "c) B777",
            "d) B300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum speed of the 777 was Mach 0.87. Cruise speed for the aircraft is Mach 0.84. Take-off speed is between 165 to 215mph."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "The 787 was intended to replace __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 737",
            "b) Boeing 747",
            "c) Boeing 777",
            "d) Boeing 767"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 787 was intended to replace Boeing 767. The 787 was designed to be 20% more fuel-efficient in comparison to the 767."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Where was the first 787 rolled out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Farnborough, UK",
            "b) Hamburg, Germany",
            "c) Everett, Washington",
            "d) Frankfurt, Germany"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first 787 was unveiled at Boeing’s Everett factory in Everett, Washington, on 8 July 2007. Final assembly of the aircraft takes place here."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "The 787 was initially designated __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7E7",
            "b) 7C7",
            "c) 7D7",
            "d) 7A7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 787 was initially designated 7E7. The aircraft was later renamed as 787 in January 2005."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "The longest range 787 variant has a cruise speed of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.70",
            "b) Mach 0.85",
            "c) Mach 0.80",
            "d) Mach 0.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The longest range 787 variant has a cruise speed of Mach 0.85, which is approximately equivalent to 561 mph. The aircraft offers a design life of 44,000 flight cycles."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the launch customer of 787-8?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thai Airways",
            "b) All Nippon Airways",
            "c) British Airways",
            "d) Malaysia Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  All Nippon Airways was the launch customer of 787-8. The aircraft entered commercial service on 26 October 2011."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "What is the typical business class layout in 787?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-2-3",
            "b) 3-3-3",
            "c) 2-2-2",
            "d) 2-4-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the aircraft’s maiden flight took place on December 15, 2009. Flight testing of the aircraft was completed by mid-2011."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "The 787 is __________ composite by volume.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5%",
            "b) 80%",
            "c) 8%",
            "d) 50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False. A Qantas 787-9 aircraft completed the first scheduled non-stop flight between Australia and the UK. It flew seventeen hours from Perth to London Heathrow."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "The 787-8 has a typical capacity of __________ passengers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 164",
            "b) 650",
            "c) 350",
            "d) 242"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The typical business class layout in a 777 is 2-2-2. The typical economy class layout is 3-3-3. Some airlines may also have a 3-4-3 economy layout."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "What of the following is not a 787 variant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 787-3",
            "b) 787-8",
            "c) 787-9",
            "d) 787-10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Boeing 787 is 80% composite by volume. Other materials used in the aircraft are aluminium and titanium."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following airlines was the launch customer of the 787-10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Canada",
            "b) Singapore Airlines",
            "c) Vistara",
            "d) Emirates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The Boeing 787 shares a common type rating with the relatively larger Boeing 777. It allows qualified pilots to operate both aircraft models."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "The 787 offers a range of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3,355 nautical miles",
            "b) 70,355 nautical miles",
            "c) 755 nautical miles",
            "d) 7,355 nautical miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Boeing 787-8 has a typical capacity of 242 passengers. The aircraft was targeted to replace the Boeing 767-200ER and -300ER."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "What is the maximum takeoff weight of the 787-9?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  54,500 pounds",
            "b)  5, 45,000 pounds",
            "c)  545 pounds",
            "d)  5,450 pounds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 787-3 is not a 787 variant. The short-range 787-3 was cancelled in 2010.However, 787-8, 787-9 and 787-10 are all 787 variants and are in commercial service."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "What is the range of the 737 MAX 7?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6,000 nmi",
            "b) 3,000 nmi",
            "c) 6,850 nmi",
            "d) 3,850 nmi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 737 MAX 7 offers a range of 3,850 nmi, which is approximately 7,130km. The aircraft offers a maximum range in comparison to other 737 MAX variants."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "When was the 737-100 rolled out?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17 December 1997",
            "b) 17 December 1967",
            "c) 17 January 1967",
            "d) 17 January 1997"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 737-100 was rolled out on 17 January 1967. The aircraft first flew on 9 April 1967. It entered service with Lufthansa in February 1968."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the launch operator of the 737 MAX 9?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lufthansa",
            "b) Emirates",
            "c) Air India",
            "d) Lion Air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lion Air was the launch operator of the 737 MAX 9. The aircraft first flew on 13 April 2017. The aircraft was presented at the 2017 Paris Show."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "What is the full form of MCAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maneuvering Characteristics Augmenting System",
            "b) Maneuvering Characteristics Augmentation System",
            "c) Maneuvering Characteristics and Augmentation System",
            "d) Maneuver Characteristics Augmentation System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: MCAS refers to Maneuvering Characteristics Augmentation System. It is a flight control software system developed for the Boeing 737 MAX."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "The first MAX 8 was delivered to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thai Airways",
            "b) Air India",
            "c) British Airways",
            "d) Malindo Air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The first MAX 8 was delivered to Malindo Air. The aircraft was delivered on 16 May 2017. The 737 MAX 8 was the first variant developed in the 737 MAX series."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "What is the typical economy class layout in a Boeing 737?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-3",
            "b) 4-4",
            "c) 2-2",
            "d) 1-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, The BBJ MAX 9 is a proposed business jet variants of the Boeing 737 MAX 9. Similarly, the BBJ MAX 8 is a proposed business jet variants of the Boeing 737 MAX 8."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "How long is the wing span of a 737 MAX?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 107 ft 10 in",
            "b) 97 ft 10 in",
            "c) 117 ft 10 in",
            "d) 97 ft 5 in"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The MAX 8 aircraft has been grounded, until further notice, by regulatory authorities around the world, due to two fatal crashes of MAX 8 aircraft in October 2018 and March 2019."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The CFM International LEAP-1B engines have a fan diameter of __________ inches.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 68 inches",
            "b) 50 inches",
            "c) 48 inches",
            "d) 100 inches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The typical economy class layout in a Boeing 737 is 3-3. The typical first class layout is 2-2. The Boeing 737 is a narrow body aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "What is the cruise speed of the 737-200?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.745",
            "b) Mach 0.0745",
            "c) Mach 7.45",
            "d) Mach 74.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wing span of a 737 MAX is 117 ft 10 in, which is approximately 35.92m. Wing span of a 737-100/-200 is 93 ft, approximately 28m."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Boeing delivered the 5000th 737 to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Canada",
            "b) Malaysia Airlines",
            "c) Vistara",
            "d) Southwest Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False. The Boeing 737 are not equipped with fuel dump systems. The classic aircraft were too small to require such systems, and adding a fuel dump system to the larger variants was not feasible."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "The first Boeing 737 MAX was named __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Spirit of Everett",
            "b) The Spirit of Renton",
            "c) The Spirit of Vegas",
            "d) The Spirit of Boeing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The CFM International LEAP-1B engines have a fan diameter of 68 inches, which is approximately 1.73 m. The engines are used for the 737 MAX family."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines was used on the 737 MAX?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CFM International LEAP-1B",
            "b) Rolls-Royce Trent 800",
            "c) Rolls-Royce Trent 700",
            "d) CFM56 turbofan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cruise speed of the 737-200 was Mach 0.745. Maximum speed for the 737-200 was Mach 0.82. The 737-100/-300/-400/-500 have a similar speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "The 747 is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twinjet",
            "b) Monojet",
            "c) Quadjet",
            "d) Trijet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 747 is a quadjet, which means the aircraft is powered by 4 jet engines, thus the name quadjet. The aircraft is available in passenger, freighter, and other versions."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "When was the maiden flight of the 747?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9 February 1969",
            "b) 9 February 1999",
            "c) 9 February 1960",
            "d) 9 February 1989"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 747 first flew on 9 February 1969. The aircraft was the first wide body airline produced and was referred as Jumbo Jet."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the newest version of the 747?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 747-8",
            "b) 747-400",
            "c) 747-200",
            "d) 747SP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 747-8 is the newest version of the 747. The aircraft was announced on 14 November 2005 and was referred as 747 advanced prior to its launch."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "The 747-400 has a cruise speed of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.755",
            "b) Mach 0.855",
            "c) Mach 0.655",
            "d) Mach 0.955"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 747 has a cruise speed of up to Mach 0.855, on different versions of the 747-400. The 747-400 was offered in various configurations like passenger, freighter, combi, domestic, extended range passenger and extended range freighter versions."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the launch customer of 747?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pan Am",
            "b) All Nippon Airways",
            "c) British Airways",
            "d) Malaysia Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Pan American World Airways, referred to as Pan Am was the launch customer of 747. The aircraft entered commercial service on 22 January 1970."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "What is the typical economy class layout on the main deck of a 747?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-2-3",
            "b) 3-4-3",
            "c) 2-2-2",
            "d) 2-4-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the 747-400 can carry 660 passengers in a high–density one-class configuration. In a two class configuration, it can carry 524 passengers."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ASB?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Advanced Streamlined Body",
            "b) Advanced Short Body",
            "c) Advanced Shape Body",
            "d) Advanced Sleek Body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the first 747 prototype was rolled out of the Boeing Everett assembly line before the press and the 26 airlines that had ordered the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "The 747-8I is designed to carry __________ passengers in a typical three class configuration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 164",
            "b) 650",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 467"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The typical economy class layout on the main deck of a 747 is 3-4-3.  The upper deck of a 747 has a 3–3 layout in economy class and a 2–2 layout in first class."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a 747 variant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 747-100",
            "b) 747-200",
            "c) 747-700",
            "d) 747-400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ASB refers to Advanced Short Body. The term is used to describe the aircraft 747 ASB. It was an undeveloped variant of the 747, developed as a response to the A340 and MD-80. The project was cancelled in favor of the 777."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of the following airlines placed the first order for the 747-300?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air Canada",
            "b) Singapore Airlines",
            "c) Swiss Air",
            "d) Emirates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The 747-500 is an undeveloped variant of the 747, which did not go beyond the concept stage. It was aimed to be an ultra long haul version that would allow airlines to fly nonstop between London and Sydney."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "The 747-100 offers a range of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5,300 nautical miles",
            "b) 50,300 nautical miles",
            "c) 530 nautical miles",
            "d) 8,000 nautical miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Boeing 747-8I is designed to carry 467 passengers in a typical three class configuration. The aircraft ca fly more than 8,000nmi at Mach 0.855."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "What is the maximum takeoff weight of the 747-8?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 97,00,000lb",
            "b) 9,700lb",
            "c) 97,000lb",
            "d) 970,000lb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 747-700 is not a 747 variant. However, 747-100, 747-200 and 747-400 are all 747 variants and have been part of commercial service."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which of the following was Boeing’s first wide-body twinjet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 767",
            "b) Boeing 747",
            "c) Boeing 737",
            "d) Boeing 787"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Boeing 767 was Boeing’s first wide-body twinjet. It was also the company’s first aircraft with a two-crew glass cockpit."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the longest range version of the 767?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 767-400ER",
            "b) 767-100",
            "c) 767-200ER",
            "d) 767-300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 767-200ER is the longest range version of the 767. The aircraft first entered service in 1984 and offered an increased range due to an additional center fuel tank."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Which of the following provides power to the 767-400ER?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolls-Royce Trent 800",
            "b) General Electric GE90",
            "c) General Electric CF6 engines",
            "d) Rolls-Royce Trent 700"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The General Electric CF6 engines provides power to the 767-400ER. The aircraft entered service with Continental Airlines in 2000, and features an updated cockpit along with 777 style signature interior."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following airlines placed the first order for the 767-300?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EasyJet",
            "b) Japan Airlines",
            "c) Qatar Airways",
            "d) Virgin Atlantic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Japan Airlines was the first airline to place an order for the 767-300. The 747-300 entered service with Japan Airlines on 20 October 1986."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the ICAO code for the Boeing 767-200?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B763",
            "b) B760",
            "c) B767",
            "d) B762"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: B762 is the ICAO code for the Boeing 767-200. Similarly, B763 and B764 are the ICAO codes for the Boeing 767-300 and Boeing 767-400ER respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "What is the typical economy class layout in a Boeing 767?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-2-3",
            "b) 3-3-3",
            "c) 2-3-2",
            "d) 2-4-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, the Boeing 767 is produced in three fuselage lengths. It is a mid to long range aircraft, built by Boeing Commercial Airplanes."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "The wings of a 767 are swept back at __________ degrees for a cruise speed of Mach 0.8.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 315 degrees",
            "b) 31.5 degrees",
            "c) 0.315 degrees",
            "d) 3.15 degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The 767 and 757 have a common type rating, as development of the 767 occurred in tandem with 757. The aircrafts have shared design features which allow pilots to obtain a common type rating to operate both aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operator of the 767?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vistara",
            "b) UPS Airlines",
            "c) United Airlines",
            "d) Japan Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The typical economy class layout in a Boeing 767 is 2-3-2. The typical business class layout is 1-2-1. The aircraft featured a two aisle cabin having a typical seating configuration of seven abreast in economy class."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "What is the maximum speed of the 767, at 39,000 feet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 486kn",
            "b) 48kn",
            "c) 686kn",
            "d) 68kn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wings of a 767 are swept back at 31.5 degrees, for a cruise speed of Mach 0.8. The aircraft is a low-wing cantilever monoplane."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the 767 passenger variant’s successor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 737NG",
            "b) 737 MAX",
            "c) 777X",
            "d) 787"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The 767 was the first aircraft to receive CAT IIIb certification, from the FAA, in 1984. It allows the aircraft for landings with 980 feet minimum visibility."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "The 767 was code named __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7A7",
            "b) 7XX7",
            "c) 7X7",
            "d) 7B7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vistara is not an operator of the 767. However, UPS Airlines, United Airlines and Japan Airlines are all major operators of the 767."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Which of the following airlines took delivery of the first 767?",
        "Options": [
            "a) United Airlines",
            "b) Lufthansa",
            "c) Air Asia",
            "d) Etihad Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum speed of the 767, at 39,000 feet is 486kn, which is approximately 900 km/h. The aircraft has a cruise speed of 459kn, along with a ceiling height of 43,100 feet."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "What is the full form of VFR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Visual flight rules",
            "b) Visual flying rules",
            "c) Virtual flight rules",
            "d) Virtual flying rules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: VFR refers to Visual flight rules. These are a set of rules that a pilot operates under so as to fly the aircraft in generally clear weather conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "By correcting the indicated airspeed for nonstandard temperature and pressure, we obtain ___________ airspeed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Actual",
            "b) Virtual",
            "c) True",
            "d) Relative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: By correcting the indicated airspeed for nonstandard temperature and pressure, we obtain true airspeed. True airspeed may also be referred to as TAS."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "The VSI is also called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vinometer",
            "b) Radiometer",
            "c) Barometer",
            "d) Variometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The VSI is also referred to as Variometer. The variometer is a device that detects variations in air pressure and then accordingly displays the appropriate information on the PFD as a rate of climb/descent."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "What is the frequency at which aircraft equipment’s operate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 350Hz",
            "b) 450Hz",
            "c) 400Hz",
            "d) 40Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aircraft equipment’s operate at 400Hz. They operate at high frequency in order to reduce the core size of equipment’s used."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "What is the full form of IAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Implied airspeed",
            "b) Indicated airspeed",
            "c) Incident airspeed",
            "d) Immediate airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IAS refers to Indicated airspeed. It is the airspeed that is read directly from the airspeed indicator on an aircraft. The indicator is located on the instrument panel."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "What does the attitude indicator display?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aircraft’s relation to the horizon",
            "b) Aircraft’s relation to the ground",
            "c) Aircraft’s relation to the wind flow",
            "d) Aircraft’s relation to the atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attitude indicator displays the aircraft’s relation to the horizon. It is a primary aircraft instrument and is also useful in conditions of poor visibility."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following can replace a heading indicator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal situation indicator",
            "b) Vertical situation indicator",
            "c) Horizontal path indicator",
            "d) Vertical path indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A horizontal situation indicator can replace a heading indicator, which is also referred to as HSI. The instrument provides the same heading information but also assists with navigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "The turn indicator indicates rotation about the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal axis",
            "b) Vertical axis",
            "c) Longitudinal axis",
            "d) Diagonal axis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The turn indicator indicates rotation about the longitudinal axis. The turn indicator includes Turn-and-Slip Indicator and the Turn Coordinator. Additional marks on the instrument indicate a standard rate turn."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "TAS shows airspeed in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Miles per hour",
            "b) Knots",
            "c) Nautical miles",
            "d) Kilometer per hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TAS shows airspeed in knots. The airspeed is usually in the range from 200 knots and higher, and is the actual air speed of an aircraft, in accordance with external conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "The compass instrument shows the aircraft’s heading relative to magnetic ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) West",
            "b) North",
            "c) South",
            "d) East"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, Instrument flight rules are one of two sets of regulations that govern all aspects of civil aviation aircraft operations. The other set of rules is Visual flight rules."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "What is the full form of FDAI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flight Directing Altitude Indicators",
            "b) Flight Director Altitude Indicators",
            "c) Flight Directing Attitude Indicators",
            "d) Flight Director Attitude Indicators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: FDAI refers to Flight Director Attitude Indicators. The attitude indicators used on manned spacecraft and are called Flight Director Attitude Indicators. The FDAI can be programed to use known positions relative to Earth."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to account for the pilot’s line of vision, w.r.t an attitude indicator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Precision knob",
            "b) Adjustment knob",
            "c) Pressure knob",
            "d) Calibrating knob"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the attitude indicator is a primary instrument for flight, in particular for flights operating in instrument meteorological conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "The bank index placed at the top of the attitude indicator displays the aircraft angle of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch",
            "b) Incidence",
            "c) Bank",
            "d) Attack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The precision knob is used to account for the pilot’s line of vision, w.r.t an attitude indicator. It moves the aircraft up and down to align it against the horizon bar."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "The top half of the attitude indicator is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green",
            "b) Blue",
            "c) Brown",
            "d) Yellow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bank index placed at the top of the attitude indicator displays the aircraft angle of bank. The degree of pitch, either up or down, is indicated by the reference lines which are placed in the middle of the instrument."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Attitude indicator is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Artificial horizon",
            "b) Real horizon",
            "c) Virtual horizon",
            "d) True horizon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The top half of the attitude indicator is blue, representing the sky, while the bottom half is brown, representing the ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Why does the attitude indicator include a symbolic miniature aircraft mounted on it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) So that it appears to be flying relative to the horizon",
            "b) So that it appears to be flying relative to the ground",
            "c) So that it appears to be flying relative to another aircraft",
            "d) So that it appears to be flying relative to the clouds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attitude indicator is also known as artificial horizon. It may also be called as gyro horizon, due to the use of gyroscope within the instrument."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The heart of the Attitude Indicator is a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gyroscope",
            "b) Pressure gauge",
            "c) Altimeter",
            "d) Radar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The attitude indicator includes a symbolic miniature aircraft mounted on it, so that it appears to be flying relative to the horizon. This is an essential component of the attitude indicator."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "The underwater locator beacon are able to operate to a depth of up to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60,000 meters",
            "b) 60 meters",
            "c) 600 meters",
            "d) 6,000 meters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The underwater locator beacon are able to operate to a depth of up to 6,000 meters, which is approximately 20,000 feet. These beacons are able to operate for up to 30 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "What is the FAA requirement for the recording duration of a CVR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum 2 hours",
            "b) Minimum 2 hours",
            "c) Maximum 6 hours",
            "d) Minimum 6 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The FAA requirement for the recording duration of a CVR, is minimum of 2 hours, as of 2008. The recording is done for a set of 4 channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "The CVRs using analog wire based recording were replaced by analog ___________ recorders.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optical tape",
            "b) Fiber tape",
            "c) Carbon tape",
            "d) Magnetic tape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The CVRs using analog wire based recording were replaced by analog magnetic tape recorders. In such comparatively modern CVRs, the tape used to automatically reverse at each end and a few units also made use of two reels."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about solid state recorders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improve safety",
            "b) Lower maintenance cost than current recorders",
            "c) Require scheduled maintenance",
            "d) Replaces moving components with non-moving components"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, the CVR is typically mounted in the rear of the airplane to maximize the chances of its survival in a crash. This is in similarity to the mounting of FDR."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "A flight data recorder must be able to withstand an acceleration of 3400g for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.5 milliseconds",
            "b) 6.5 seconds",
            "c) 65 seconds",
            "d) 65 milliseconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Solid state recorders have the advantage of not requiring scheduled maintenance and thus make the data easier to retrieve. They provide enhanced safety to the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a parameter required for CVRs and FDRs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetration resistance",
            "b) Static crush",
            "c) Airspeed",
            "d) Fluid immersion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A flight data recorder must be able to withstand an acceleration of 3400g for 6.5 milliseconds. This requirement is based on the EUROCAE documents."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Which of the following defines the minimum specification to be met for all aircraft requiring flight recorders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EURO ED-112",
            "b) EUROCAE ED-112",
            "c) FAA ED-112",
            "d) EUROCARE ED-112"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Airspeed is not a parameter required for CVRs and FDRs. However, penetration resistance, static crush and fluid immersion are all parameters required for CVRs and FDRs."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "The CVRs and FDRs must be able to withstand a crushing distance of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45km",
            "b) 45mm",
            "c) 45m",
            "d) 45cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: EUROCAE ED-112 defines the minimum specification to be met for all aircraft requiring flight recorders. It may be referred to as Minimum Operational Performance Specification for Crash Protected Airborne Recorder Systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CVR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crew voice recorder",
            "b) Cockpit voice recorder",
            "c) Cabin voice recorder",
            "d) Central voice recorder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CVR refers to cockpit voice recorder. It is an instrument that preserves the recent history of sounds in the cockpit, including any conversation between the pilots."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Flight recorders are typically designed to withstand an impact of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3400g",
            "b) 340g",
            "c) 34,000g",
            "d) 34g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flight recorders are typically designed to withstand an impact of 3400g. This is so that the instrument is capable of surviving the conditions likely to be encountered in a severe aircraft accident."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Flight Data Recorder (FDR) is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orange Box",
            "b) Black Box",
            "c) Red Box",
            "d) Green Box"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flight data recorder; commercial aircraft cockpit data recorders are also commonly known as a “black box”, they store ﬂight information and audio from the cockpit. They’re often recovered from a plane crash to determine the cause of the incident."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Since when have been flight data recorders, a mandatory requirement in commercial aircraft in the United States?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1997",
            "b) 1907",
            "c) 1967",
            "d) 2007"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since 1967, flight data recorders have been a mandatory requirement in commercial aircraft in the United States. The instruments are extremely critical for safe flying of aircrafts."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Which color paint is used to coat the exterior of the FDR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bright orange",
            "b) Bright pink",
            "c) Bright red",
            "d) Bright black"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bright orange paint is used to coat the exterior of the FDR. The paint is heat resistant and provides high visibility in case of a wreckage."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a channel used by CVRs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cargo",
            "b) Pilot",
            "c) Copilot",
            "d) Crew"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cargo is not a channel used by CVRs. In total, there are 4 channels in a commercial type recorder: Pilot, Copilot, Crew, and Centre-Area. In case of a crash or mishap, the cumulative information from these channels is essential to evaluate the cause of the tragedy."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "The FDR unit is usually mounted in the aircrafts ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuselage section",
            "b) Nose section",
            "c) Tail section",
            "d) Wing section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The FDR unit is usually mounted in the aircrafts tail section. This is because, the FDR is most likely to survive a crash, if placed in this section."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "What is the full form of FDAU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flight Data Analyzing Units",
            "b) Flight Data Acquisition Units",
            "c) Flight Drag Acquisition Units",
            "d) Flight Drag Analyzing Units"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FDAU refers to Flight Data Acquisition Units. These are units that record important flight parameters, including control and actuator positions, engine information and time of day."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "How often are FDR verification checks performed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Annually",
            "b) Weekly",
            "c) Monthly",
            "d) Bi-weekly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FDR verification checks are performed annually. These verification checks or readouts are a requirement by aviation regulation authorities around the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "The reference pressure in Canada and the United States, is noted in which of the following units?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meters of mercury",
            "b) Inches of mercury",
            "c) Hectopascals",
            "d) Pascals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the air pressure decreases with an increase of altitude. The increase is approximately 100 hectopascals per 800 meters, or roughly one inch of mercury per 1000 feet."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ISA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Stationary Atmosphere",
            "b) Internal Standard Atmosphere",
            "c) International Standard Atmosphere",
            "d) Internal Stationary Atmosphere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reference pressure in Canada and the United States, is noted in inches of mercury. Elsewhere, it is noted in hectopascals. It is displayed in the small Kollsman window, on the face of the aircraft altimeter."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "In a sensitive altimeter, the sea-level reference pressure can be adjusted with a __________ knob.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Setting",
            "b) Calibrating",
            "c) Adjusting",
            "d) Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ISA refers to International Standard Atmosphere. It is a static atmospheric model established to provide a common reference for temperature and pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Radio altimeters are used up to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2500 feet",
            "b) 3000 feet",
            "c) 250 feet",
            "d) 300 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sea-level reference pressure can be adjusted with a setting knob. The knob is located on the altimeter. Modern aircraft use sensitive altimeters."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the value of the atmospheric pressure, used to adjust the sub-scale of a pressure altimeter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barometric setting",
            "b) Atmospheric setting",
            "c) Altimeter setting",
            "d) Altitude setting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radio altimeters give data to the auto throttle which is a part of the Flight Computer. Radio altimeters only give readings up to 2,500 feet above ground level. Above 2,500 feet, other systems are used to determine the fight altitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "What is a barometer supplied with a nonlinear calibration, so as to indicate altitude called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radio Altimeter",
            "b) Radar altimeter",
            "c) Weather altimeter",
            "d) Pressure altimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Altimeter setting is the value of the atmospheric pressure, used to adjust the sub-scale of a pressure altimeter. It is done so that it indicates the height of an aircraft above a known reference surface, such as mean sea level."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The altimeter is used to shows the aircraft’s __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altitude",
            "b) Airspeed",
            "c) True speed",
            "d) Mach speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pressure altimeter may also be referred to as barometer’s which are equipped with a nonlinear calibration. Such calibration is done so as to indicate altitude. Further, these instruments may also be called as barometric altimeter."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Where is the static port mounted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) On the fuselage of an aircraft",
            "b) On the nose of an aircraft",
            "c) On the engine of an aircraft",
            "d) On the tail of an aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The static port is mounted on the fuselage of an aircraft. The port is located at such a position where it can access the air flow in a relatively undisturbed area."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Where is the alternative static port located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inside the wings of the aircraft",
            "b) Inside the rudder of the aircraft",
            "c) Inside the engine of the aircraft",
            "d) Inside the cabin of the aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An alternative static port is located inside the cabin of the aircraft. The alternate port acts as a backup, in case the external static port(s) are blocked."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not determined using the pitot-static system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altitude",
            "b) Mach Number",
            "c) Thrust",
            "d) Airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thrust is not determined using the pitot-static system. However, the other three parameters altitude, Mach number and airspeed are determined using the pitot-static system."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "What is the difference between the pitot pressure and the static pressure called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atmospheric Pressure",
            "b) Dynamic Pressure",
            "c) Air Pressure",
            "d) Cabin Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Pitot tube is most commonly located on the wing assembly of an aircraft. The tube is placed in such a way that its opening is exposed to the relative wind so that maximum air contact takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "The two additional radial markings on the airspeed indicator, one red and one blue, are associated with potential __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engine Failure",
            "b) Landing Gear Failure",
            "c) Radar Failure",
            "d) Altimeter Failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The difference between the pitot pressure and the static pressure is called dynamic pressure. The greater the dynamic pressure, the higher is the airspeed."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which of the following refers to the speed for best rate of climb with the critical engine inoperative?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VFE",
            "b) VNE",
            "c) Vmc",
            "d) VYSE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two additional radial markings on the airspeed indicator, one red and one blue, are associated with potential engine failure. The radial red line indicates Vmc and the radial blue line indicates VYSE."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "When the aircraft is moving forward, air entering the Pitot tube is at a __________ pressure than the static line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal",
            "b) Lower",
            "c) Greater",
            "d) Infinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: VYSE refers to the speed for best rate of climb with the critical engine inoperative. It is indicated on the airspeed indicator in multi-engine aircraft that include radial markings on the ASI."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Ram air enters the system through the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitot tube",
            "b) Static tube",
            "c) Engines",
            "d) APU Exhaust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At an instant where the aircraft is moving forward, the air entering the aircraft’s Pitot tube will be at a greater pressure than the static line. This phenomenon in turn causes the diaphragm to flex thus moving the pointer."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a unit of measurement for airspeed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kilometers per hour",
            "b) Knots",
            "c) Miles per hour",
            "d) Pascal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, TAS refers to True Airspeed, which increases as altitude increases, as air density decreases. Similarly, TAS decreases as altitude decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant airspeed",
            "b) Continuous airspeed",
            "c) Calibrated airspeed",
            "d) Comparative airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pascal is not a unit of measurement for airspeed. However, kilometers per hour, knots and miles per hour, are all used to indicate airspeed. The airspeed might be displayed in two units as well."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Static pressure is measured from the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static port",
            "b) Static scale",
            "c) Pitot scale",
            "d) Pitot tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: CAS refers to Calibrated airspeed. This airspeed is corrected for installation and instrument errors. Further, an airspeed calibration chart is available for any remaining errors."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "What will the ASI pointer read, if both the Pitot tube and the static system are blocked?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Positive Infinite",
            "c) No reading",
            "d) Negative Infinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Static pressure is measured from the static port. The pitot-static system is a system of pressure-sensitive instruments."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "If the pitot opening is blocked, but the drain hole is open, it will cause the system pressure to drop to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Critical pressure",
            "b) Low pressure",
            "c) Ambient pressure",
            "d) Atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If both the Pitot tube and the static system are blocked, the ASI pointer will read zero on its scale. However, if the static ports are blocked but the Pitot tube remains open, the ASI will continue to operate, but will give inaccurate readings."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Which of the following determines when an aircraft will stall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle of pitch",
            "b) Angle of incidence",
            "c) Angle of bank",
            "d) Angle of attack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the pitot opening is blocked, but the drain hole is open, it will cause the system pressure to drop to ambient pressure. Ambient pressure on an object refers to the pressure of the surrounding medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "The Lift Reserve Indicator provides a measure of the amount of __________ being generated, by an aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lift",
            "b) Thrust",
            "c) True speed",
            "d) Mach speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The angle of attack determines when an aircraft will stall. An aircraft can stall at any speed, so monitoring the airspeed alone will not prevent a stall."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used only to determine airspeed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static pressure",
            "b) Pitot pressure",
            "c) Cockpit pressure",
            "d) Cabin pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Lift Reserve Indicator provides a measure of the amount of lift being generated, by an aircraft. The instrument uses a pressure differential system and provides the pilot a visual representation of reserve lifts available."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Mechanical gauges have been retained for backup purposes in the event of total __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical Failure",
            "b) Mechanical Failure",
            "c) Thermal Failure",
            "d) Hydraulic Failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mechanical gauges have been retained for backup purposes in the event of total electrical failure. They have not been completely eliminated from the cockpit, despite the onset of the PFD."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Which was the first general aviation manufacturer to add a PFD to the already existing MFD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing",
            "b) Cirrus Aircraft",
            "c) Airbus",
            "d) Lockheed Martin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cirrus Aircraft was the first general aviation manufacturer to add a PFD to the already existing MFD. Further, in 2003 the manufacturer made such displays standard equipment on their SR-series aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a necessary component of the PFD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altimeter",
            "b) Turn coordinator",
            "c) Airspeed indicator",
            "d) Flaps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flaps is not a necessary component of the PFD. However, altimeter, airspeed indicator and turn coordinator are all necessary components of the PFD., as described by the FAA."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What is the full form of AMSL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altitude above mean sea level",
            "b) Altitude above mean sea level",
            "c) AOA above mean sea level",
            "d) Airspeed above mean sea level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: AMSL refers to the altitude above mean sea level. The pitot system in aircraft is used to measure the AMSL. This is because the pitot system is useful in tracking air pressure measurements, which are necessary to find AMSL."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "What does the vertical speed indicator, indicate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rate at which the pressure changes",
            "b) Rate at which the altitude changes",
            "c) Rate at which the temperature changes",
            "d) Rate at which the airspeed changes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The vertical speed indicator indicates the rate at which the altitude changes. It is usually represented with numbers in thousands of feet per minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Which of the following is shown at the bottom of the PFD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airspeed Indicator",
            "b) Heading display",
            "c) Vertical Speed Indicator",
            "d) Altitude Indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the PFD does not contain any mechanical parts. The primary flight display is responsible for merely displaying data from the underlying mechanical systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not shown on the heading display?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Current heading",
            "b) Airspeed",
            "c) Thrust",
            "d) Rate of turn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The heading display is shown at the bottom of the PFD. Airspeed indicator, vertical speed indicator and altitude indicator are displayed at different positions on the PFD."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "A measurement of “+4” on the vertical speed indicator indicates an ascent of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200 feet per minute",
            "b) 2000 feet per minute",
            "c) 400 feet per minute",
            "d) 4000 feet per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thrust is not shown on the heading display. However, the heading display shows not only the current heading, but also the current rate of turn, current heading setting on the autopilot, and other indicators."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Airbus proposed a common symbol system on the PFD and HUD with the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A380-800",
            "b) A350-800",
            "c) A350-1000",
            "d) A330neo"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A measurement of “+4” on the vertical speed indicator indicates an ascent of 4000 feet per minute. Similarly, a measurement of “-1.5” indicates a descent of 1500 feet per minute."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the official language of aviation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) English",
            "b) French",
            "c) Spanish",
            "d) Greek"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: English is the official language of aviation. All aviation communications are done using the language, irrespective of the local language of the place where aircraft is flying."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "The use of English in aviation industry is regulated by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DGCA",
            "b) FAA",
            "c) ICAO",
            "d) UNO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The use of English in aviation industry is regulated by the ICAO. ICAO refers to the International Civil Aviation Organization, which is a specialized agency of the United Nations."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which of the following communications is not included in FANS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air traffic control clearances",
            "b) Ground staff communications",
            "c) Pilot requests",
            "d) Position reporting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ground staff communications are not included in FANS. However, air traffic control clearances, pilot requests and position reporting are all part of the FANS communication system."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a communication error?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amount of information",
            "b) Unclear pronunciation",
            "c) Attenuation",
            "d) Misunderstanding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Attenuation is not a communication error. However, amount of information, unclear pronunciation and misunderstanding are all types of a communication error."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "The protocol for ACARS was designed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing",
            "b) ARINC",
            "c) FAA",
            "d) ICAO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The protocol for ACARS was designed by Aeronautical Radio, Incorporated (ARINC). It was deployed in 1978, using the telex format."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The Airbus ICAO compliant product for the A320 family of aircrafts is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) FANS-B",
            "b) FANS-A",
            "c) ICAO-D",
            "d) ICAO-C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Airbus ICAO compliant product for the A320 family of aircrafts is known as FANS-B. The term FANS refers to Future Air Navigation System. These are systems used on modern airliners to improve their navigational capabilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "The Airbus A380 and Boeing 787 have which of the following capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FANS-1/A",
            "b) FANS-1/B",
            "c) FANS-1/C",
            "d) FANS-1/D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Airbus A380 and Boeing 787 aircrafts have FANS-1/A capability. ARINC 622 standard is used to define such devices. The A380 and 787 are both modern airliners, featuring enhanced aerodynamic capabilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ACARS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airplane communications addressing and reporting system",
            "b) Aviation communications addressing and reporting system",
            "c) Aircraft communications addressing and reporting system",
            "d) Airspace communications addressing and reporting system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ACARS refers to Aircraft communications addressing and reporting system. Such systems make use of digital datalink technology and are helpful in transmitting short messages between an aircraft and the ground station."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "English was established as the international aviation language in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1951",
            "b) 1901",
            "c) 2001",
            "d) 1991"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: English was established as the international aviation language in 1951. It was done so as to improve consistency, accuracy, and effectiveness of pilot – air traffic control communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which is the only channel that retains 100 kHz channel spacing in the US?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 121.5 MHz",
            "b) 131.5 MHz",
            "c) 141.5 MHz",
            "d) 171.5 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 121.5 MHz is the only channel that retains 100 kHz channel spacing in the US. It is an emergency communication channel. No channel allocations are present between 121.4 and 121.5 or between 121.5 and 121.6."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What is the transmission range of an aircraft flying at a cruise altitude of 35,000 feet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000 mi",
            "b) 400 mi",
            "c) 200 mi",
            "d) 4000 mi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The transmission range of an aircraft flying at a cruise altitude of 35,000 feet, is roughly around 200 miles, which is approximately 322 km. The range is dependent on the prevailing weather conditions and is reduced in extreme weather conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "The VHF air band uses the frequencies between 108 and ___________ MHz.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 127",
            "b) 137",
            "c) 110",
            "d) 237"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The VHF air band uses the frequencies between 108MHz and 137MHz. In most countries a license is required to operate an air band equipment."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about VHF propagation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Can penetrate building walls",
            "b) Can travel long distances",
            "c) Transmitting antennas are huge",
            "d) Can be received indoors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: VHF band is the first band which offers transmitting antennas small enough that they can be mounted on vehicles and portable devices. The VHF signals can be received indoors and are able to travel long distances if conditions are suitable."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a common use for radio waves in the VHF band?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FM radio broadcasting",
            "b) Walkie-talkie communication",
            "c) Marine communications",
            "d) Television broadcasting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Walkie-talkie communication is not a common use for radio waves in the VHF band. However, FM radio broadcasting, Marine communications and Television broadcasting are all common uses of radio waves in the VHF band."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Frequencies lying immediately below VHF are referred to as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High frequency",
            "b) Ultra high frequency",
            "c) Low frequency",
            "d) Ultra low frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequencies lying immediately below VHF are referred to as high frequency. The high frequency band has a number of applications ranging from aviation communication, weather analysis and government usage. Further, the high frequency band succeeds the medium frequency band."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "What is the frequency range of VHF (Very high frequency)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 MHz to 300 MHz",
            "b) 30 Hz to 300 Hz",
            "c) 30 KHz to 300 KHz",
            "d) 30 mHz to 300 mHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Very high frequency (VHF) is the radio frequency range from 30 MHz to 300 MHz.  VHF is the ITU designation for the range of radio frequency EM Waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "When were the frequencies between 136.000 and 136.975 MHz added?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 January 2019",
            "b) 1 January 2010",
            "c) 1 January 1990",
            "d) 1 January 1999"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frequencies lying between the 136.000 and 136.975 MHz bandwidth were added on 1 January 1990. These frequencies helped in increasing the total number of channels to 740. The addition was necessary to decrease the load on the existing channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Radio operations used for aircraft communication make use of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amplitude modulation",
            "b) Frequency modulation",
            "c) Phase modulation",
            "d) Channel Modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radio operations used for aircraft communication make use of amplitude modulation techniques. It is a reliable modulation technique and ensures that the signal is transmitted with minimal loss."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "What is the full form of SSB modulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shaky-sideband modulation",
            "b) Separated-sideband modulation",
            "c) Sorted-sideband modulation",
            "d) Singe-sideband modulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, military aircraft also use a dedicated UHF-AM band from 225.0–399.95. It is used mainly for air-to-air and air-to-ground communications, including communications with the ATC."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "What is the maximum audio frequency at which an air band channel can operate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.166 MHz",
            "b) 4.166 mHz",
            "c) 4.166 kHz",
            "d) 4.166 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SSB modulation refers to Singe-sideband modulation (SSB), or single-sideband suppressed-carrier modulation (SSB-SC). Under SSB modulation, the transmitter bandwidth and power are used in a more efficient manner and the system is based on AM Modulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "The European Union allows a maximum of ___________ air band channels.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2,280",
            "b) 280",
            "c) 774",
            "d) 228"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum audio frequency at which an air band channel can operate is 4.166 kHz. The frequency is kept in accordance to the largest possible bandwidth of a particular air band channel, which is 8.33 kHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the emergency channel for military aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 243.0 Hz",
            "b) 243.0 MHz",
            "c) 343.0 MHz",
            "d) 343.0 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The European Union allows a maximum of 2,280 air band channels. Further, it is a common practice in the European Union to divide one air band channel into three different channels, thus increasing the total available channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "What is the full form of MUF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Most usable frequency",
            "b) Minimum usable frequency",
            "c) Maximum usable frequency",
            "d) Minimal usable frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MUF refers to Maximum usable frequency. The maximum usable frequency is dependent on the angle of incidence of the waves and thus keeps on changing."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor influencing HF propagation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wind speed",
            "b) Season",
            "c) Solar activity",
            "d) Sunspot cycle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wind speed is not a factor influencing HF propagation. However, season, solar activity and sunspot cycle along with other factors influence HF propagation."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "The High frequency band is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pentameter band",
            "b) Decameter band",
            "c) Quadmeter band",
            "d) Hexameter band"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The High frequency (HF) Band is also known as the Decameter band. This is because of the wavelengths in this band range from one to ten decameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Communication at high frequencies is often called as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longwave radio",
            "b) Ultra shortwave radio",
            "c) Shortwave radio",
            "d) Mediumwave radio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Communication at high frequencies is often called shortwave radio. This is because the HF band is a major part of the shortwave band of frequencies."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "What is the wavelength range of HF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100km to 10km",
            "b) 1000m to 100m",
            "c) 1000km to 100km",
            "d) 100m to 10m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 100m to 10m is the wavelength range of HF. These frequencies are suitable for long-distance communication across intercontinental distances."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Frequencies immediately below HF are referred to as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Medium frequency",
            "b) Ultra high frequency",
            "c) Low frequency",
            "d) Ultra low frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequencies immediately below HF are referred to as Medium frequency. The medium frequency band also comprises of the medium wave band, used specifically for broadcasting AM."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "What is the frequency range of HF (High frequency)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 MHz to 30 MHz",
            "b) 3 Hz to 30 Hz",
            "c) 3 KHz to 30 KHz",
            "d) 3 mHz to 30 mHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: High frequency refers to the radio frequency range lying between 3 MHz to 30 MHz. These waves possess wavelengths from one to ten decameters and the band is thus referred to as the decameter band."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "What is the full form of FOT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency of open transmission",
            "b) Frequency of optimum transmission",
            "c) Frequency of optical transmission",
            "d) Frequency of optional transmission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FOT refers to the Frequency of optimum transmission. It is the highest effective frequency, predicted to be useful for a specified path in the transmission of radio waves, via ionospheric reflection."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "The lowest usable frequency depends on the absorption of which of the following layers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D-layer",
            "b) E-layer",
            "c) F-layer",
            "d) G-layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lowest usable frequency depends on the absorption of the D-layer. The D-layer is the lower layer of the ionosphere and lies beneath the E-layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "On a day in full summer the __________ tend to be more usable.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultra low frequencies",
            "b) Medium frequencies",
            "c) Lower frequencies",
            "d) Higher frequencies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True. In aviation, HF communication systems are required for all trans-oceanic flights. This is because HF is suitable for long-distance communication and for mountainous terrains."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "What is the full form of RFID?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Real frequency identification",
            "b) Radar frequency identification",
            "c) Radio frequency identification",
            "d) Rate frequency identification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: On a day in full summer the higher frequencies tend to be more usable. This is because of the MUF and LUF phenomenon, which depend on the angle of incidence of the waves."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Which of the following is referred to as the upper section of HF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26.5 MHz to 30 MHz",
            "b) 26.5 Hz to 30 Hz",
            "c) 265 MHz to 300 MHz",
            "d) 265 Hz to 300 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RFID refers to radio frequency identification. The RFID tags use High Frequency (HF). These tags are commonly known as High-Frequency Identification or HFIDs."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "The MUF is lowest when the waves are directed ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straight downwards",
            "b) Straight upwards",
            "c) Diagonally",
            "d) Incidentally"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The upper section of high frequency range refers to frequencies having a magnitude between 26.5 MHz and 30 MHz. Frequencies from this section possess characteristics similar to frequencies in the lower part of VHF."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "The clear-channel stations are required to broadcast at higher powers of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mW to 50 mW",
            "b) 10 MW to 50 MW",
            "c) 10 W to 50 W",
            "d) 10 kW to 50 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The clear-channel stations, are required to broadcast at higher powers of 10 kW to 50 kW. These channels are for night time use over extended service areas via sky wave."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Radio waves at Medium Frequency wavelengths propagate via ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ground waves",
            "b) Air waves",
            "c) Sky waves",
            "d) Electric waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radio waves at Medium Frequency wavelengths propagate via ground waves. Ground waves follow the contour of the Earth and travel beyond the visual horizon."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "The Medium frequency band is also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pentameter band",
            "b) Hectometer band",
            "c) Quadmeter band",
            "d) Hexameter band"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Medium frequency (HF) Band is also known as the Hectometer band. This is because of the wavelengths in this band range from ten to one hectometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "What is the wavelength range for medium frequency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 to 100cm",
            "b) 1000 to 100miles",
            "c) 1000 to 100m",
            "d) 1000 to 100km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wavelength range for medium frequency is 1000 to 100m. MF is mostly used in trans-oceanic ATC control and maritime ship to shore communication."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which of the following frequency is used by the US Coastguard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2670 kHz",
            "b) 2670 MHz",
            "c) 2670 Hz",
            "d) 2670 mHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 2670 kHz is the frequency used by the US Coastguard. Similarly, there are a number of coast guard and other ship to shore frequencies in use between 1600 and 850 kHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Frequencies immediately below medium frequency band are referred to as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High frequency",
            "b) Ultra high frequency",
            "c) Low frequency",
            "d) Ultra low frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frequencies immediately below medium frequency band are referred to as low frequency. The low frequency band may also be referred to as the kilometer band and it succeeds the ultra-low frequency band."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "What is the frequency range of MF (Medium frequency)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 Hz to 3 MHz",
            "b) 300 kHz to 3 MHz",
            "c) 300 KHz to 3000 KHz",
            "d) 300 kHz to 300 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Medium Frequency (MF) is the radio frequency range from 300 kHz to 3 MHz. MF is the ITU designation for the range of radio frequency EM Waves between the given frequencies."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "What is the allocated frequency range for MF in North America?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 525 MHz to 1705 MHz",
            "b) 52 kHz to 170 kHz",
            "c) 525 kHz to 1705 kHz",
            "d) 525 MHz to 1705 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, in medium frequency the same frequencies are re-allocated to different broadcasting stations. Such re allocation is done due to a limited number of channels being available. However it should also be noted that such stations may be a significant distant apart from each other, generally several thousand meters."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "What is the full form of DME?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distance measuring equipment",
            "b) Distance maintaining equipment",
            "c) Data measuring equipment",
            "d) Data maintaining equipment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DME refers to distance measuring equipment. It is a radio navigation technology that measures the distance between an aircraft and a ground station."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "The propagation delay of DME radio signals in the frequency band is timed between ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 960 Hz and 1215 Hz",
            "b) 960 MHz and 1215 MHz",
            "c) 96 MHz and 121 MHz",
            "d) 96 Hz and 121 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The propagation delay of DME radio signals in the frequency band is timed between 960 MHz and 1215 MHz. Line of visibility between the aircraft and the ground station is necessary."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "Which of the following specifies the carrier frequency and the spacing between the pulses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch assignment",
            "b) Amplitude assignment",
            "c) Channel assignment",
            "d) Frequency assignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The channel assignment specifies the carrier frequency and the spacing between the pulses. These are two essential operating values of the DME."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an agency that sets standards for DME systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RTCA",
            "b) EASA",
            "c) ICAO",
            "d) Rolls-Royce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rolls-Royce is not an agency that sets standards for DME systems. However, RTCA, EASA and ICAO are all agencies that set standards for DME systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "ICAO characterizes DME transmissions as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High frequency",
            "b) Ultra high frequency",
            "c) Low frequency",
            "d) Medium frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ICAO characterizes DME transmissions as UHF or ultra high frequency. This is because of the relatively high frequency of such transmissions in comparison to other transmissions. It may also be described by the term L-band."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Where was the DME developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Australia",
            "b) Germany",
            "c) India",
            "d) Canada"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The DME instrument was developed in Australia. It was invented by James Gerrand, under the supervision of Edward George Bowen. Germany is another country having significant contributions to the aerospace industry. Airbus has a major facility at Hamburg, Germany. India and Canada also have a fair share of Aerospace Business."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "DME is functionally identical to the distance measuring component of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) TACAN",
            "b) VOR",
            "c) ILS",
            "d) RADAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The DME is functionally identical to the distance measuring component of TACAN. This is done to maintain compatibility between the two systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "What is the typical peak pulse output of a DME ground transponder for en-route or terminal navigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 kW",
            "b) 10 kW",
            "c) 1 kW",
            "d) 1000 kW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The typical peak pulse output of a DME ground transponder for en-route or terminal navigation is 1 kW, on the assigned UHF channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "How much is the typical time delay after which the aircraft interrogates with the ground transponder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 microseconds",
            "b) 50 seconds",
            "c) 50 minutes",
            "d) 50 milliseconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 50 microseconds is the typical time delay after which the aircraft interrogates with the ground transponder. The process involves a series of pulse-pairs (interrogations)."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "How much time does a radio signal take, to travel 1 nautical mile to the target and back?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12.36 nanoseconds",
            "b) 12.36 seconds",
            "c) 12.36 microseconds",
            "d) 12.36 milliseconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, The DME system comprises a UHF interrogator in the aircraft. This interrogator may also be referred to as a receiver or transmitter and is necessary to interpret the incoming UHF transmission signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "How much is the accuracy of DME ground stations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.85 m",
            "b) 185 m",
            "c) 18.5 m",
            "d) 0.185 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 12.36 microseconds is the time taken by a radio signal to travel 1 nautical mile to the target and back. The distance is approximately 1,852 meters."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "An aircraft directly above the DME station at 1 nautical mile altitude would show ___________ on the DME readout.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 nautical mile",
            "b) 10 nautical mile",
            "c) 0 nautical mile",
            "d) 1.0 nautical mile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 185 m is the accuracy of DME ground stations. It may vary by ±0.1 nautical mile. ICAO recommends an accuracy of less than the sum of 0.25 nautical miles."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "The physical distance between the aircraft antenna and the DME transponder antenna is referred to as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slant range",
            "b) Slant height",
            "c) Slant angle",
            "d) Slant length"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The physical distance between the aircraft antenna and the DME transponder antenna is referred to as slant range. It is measured using the DME."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "The typical DME ground based responder beacon has a limit of ________ interrogations per second.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2700",
            "b) 270",
            "c) 27",
            "d) 27000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, the spacing of all channels is 1 MHz. Further, it has a signal spectrum width of 100 kHz. There are 126 channels each, for interrogation and reply."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following frequencies are used by an airplane’s DME interrogator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1025 mHz to 1150 mHz",
            "b) 1025 Hz to 1150 Hz",
            "c) 1025 MHz to 1150 MHz",
            "d) 1025 KHz to 1150 KHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The typical DME ground based responder beacon has a limit of 2700 interrogations per second. It refers to pulse pairs per second, called pps."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the range of frequency for the transmitting channel of DME transponders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 962 mHz to 1213 mHz",
            "b) 962 Hz to 1213 Hz",
            "c) 962 KHz to 1213 KHz",
            "d) 962 MHz to 1213 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 1025 MHz to 1150 MHz are the frequencies are used by an airplane’s DME interrogator. DME frequencies are paired to VHF omnidirectional range frequencies."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "How much is the difference between interrogation and reply frequencies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 63 MHz",
            "b) 63 Hz",
            "c) 60 MHz",
            "d) 63 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 962 MHz to 1213 MHz is the range of frequency for the transmitting channel of DME transponders. The range frequency for the receiving channel is between 1025 and 1150 MHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "DME facilities use a ___________ Morse code in order to identify themselves.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,350 MHz",
            "b) 1,350 Hz",
            "c) 150 Hz",
            "d) 150 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The difference between a pair of interrogation and reply frequencies is of the magnitude of 63 MHz. Also the band comprises of 126 channels solely for interrogation purpose and another 126 channels for reply purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Terminal transponders generally work to a minimum height above ground of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12,000 feet",
            "b) 1200 feet",
            "c) 120 feet",
            "d) 12 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The DME use a 1,350 Hz Morse code in order to identify themselves. This code is in the form of a three letter identity, which when collated with either a VOR or ILS system, will have a similar identity code."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "What is the range of high altitude transponders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1300 nautical miles",
            "b) 13 nautical miles",
            "c) 100 nautical miles",
            "d) 130 nautical miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Terminal transponders generally work to a minimum height above ground of 12,000 feet. These transponders are usually installed in airport buildings. Such transponders often have a short range and are unable to work in extreme weather conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "How many frequencies are defined for DME interrogations and replies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 2520",
            "c) 252",
            "d) 22"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The range of high altitude transponders is 130 nautical miles. They typically provide service to a minimum height of 45,000 feet. These devices are based on wireless communication and can operate in extreme conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "The Y channels interrogation pulse pairs are spaced by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 36 milliseconds",
            "b) 36 seconds",
            "c) 36 microseconds",
            "d) 36 nanoseconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A total of 252 frequencies are defined for DME interrogations and replies. However, all of them are not used. The frequencies are the same for X and Y channels."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "What is the full form of VOR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Virtual Omni-Directional Range",
            "b) VHF Omni-Directional Range",
            "c) VHF Omni-Directing Range",
            "d) VHF Omni-Directional Radar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term VOR refers to VHF Omni-Directional Range. Further, the term VHF is an acronym for Very High Frequency. This is a system used in aircrafts for navigation purposes and requires very high frequency transmission signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "VOR is a _________ range radio navigation method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short",
            "b) Ultra long",
            "c) Long",
            "d) Medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The VOR transmission is a short range radio navigation method. These systems allow an aircraft to determine its position during flying phases and help it align with the desired flight path."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The line of position is called the ________ from the VOR.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonal",
            "b) Axial",
            "c) Radial",
            "d) Lateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The line of position is called the radial from the VOR. The position of an aircraft can be fixed using the intersection of radials from two different VOR stations."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The VOR uses frequencies in which of the following band?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LF",
            "b) MF",
            "c) VHF",
            "d) UHF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The VOR uses frequencies in the VHF band, i.e. very high frequency band. The letter V in VOR stands for VHF. The system is used by both commercial and general aviation."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "What is the full form of RDF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radial direction finding",
            "b) Radio direction finding",
            "c) Rate direction finding",
            "d) Ratio direction finding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term RDF in aviation terminology refers to radio direction finding. The system is used in order to determine the direction from which the received signal was originally transmitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Where was the VOR developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Australia",
            "b) Germany",
            "c) India",
            "d) The United States"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The VOR was developed in the United States. It was developed in the beginning of 1937 and was deployed by 1946. In 2000, there were about 3,000 VOR stations operating around the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "The extremely directional second signal sent by a VOR ground station generally rotates in a clockwise direction in space for about ________ times a second.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The extremely directional second signal sent by a VOR ground station, generally rotates in a clockwise direction in space for about 30 times a second. In order to propagate such signals, phased antenna arrays have to be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "The signals transmitted from VOR stations are competent up to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4,000 miles",
            "b) 2,000 miles",
            "c) 200 miles",
            "d) 10,000 miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The signals transmitted from VOR stations are competent up to 200 miles. The transmitted signals act as a line of sight in between the receiver and the transmitter."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "VOR and NDB approaches are being replaced by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RADAR",
            "b) RNAV",
            "c) TACAN",
            "d) CAT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Newer RNAV approach procedures are replacing the older VOR and NDB approaches. These newer systems are however expensive and involve high maintenance costs. They may also be referred to as GPS."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "How much is the predictable accuracy of VOR signals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 900 km",
            "b) 90 km",
            "c) 90 m",
            "d) 900 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, VOR signals provide much greater accuracy as compared to NDB systems. These systems also offer better reliability in comparison to NDB systems, due to a number of factors affecting the systems performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "VOR stations depend on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Line of approach",
            "b) Line of sight",
            "c) Line of descent",
            "d) Line of attack"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The predictable accuracy of VOR signals is 90 m, which is approximately 300 feet. The accuracy can also be described as 2 sigma at 2 NM from a pair of VOR beacons."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "The VORs are assigned radio channels between _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10.80 MHz and 117.95 MHz",
            "b) 10.80 Hz and 117.95 MHz",
            "c) 108.0 Hz and 117.95 Hz",
            "d) 108.0 MHz and 117.95 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The VORs are assigned radio channels between 108.0 MHz and 117.95 MHz. VOR range is limited to the horizon, or closer if mountains intervene."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "What is the spacing between VOR channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 kHz",
            "b) 50 Hz",
            "c) 50 MHz",
            "d) 5000 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the channels 108.10, 108.15, 108.30, 108.35 and so on, are reserved for ILS in the US."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following systems shares the first 4 MHz from VOR radio channels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) GPS",
            "b) RADAR",
            "c) ILS",
            "d) CAT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The spacing between VOR channels is 50 kHz. The frequencies lie in the very high frequency (VHF) range and VOR stations rely on line of sight. Further, to leave channels for ILS, in the range 108.0 to 111.95 MHz, the 100 kHz digit is always even."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "The conventional 30 Hz reference signal is frequency modulated on a __________ sub carrier.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 96 Hz",
            "b) 99,960 Hz",
            "c) 960 Hz",
            "d) 9,960 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ILS, or instrument landing system shares the first 4 MHz from VOR radio channels. The four MHz to be shared, start from the frequency 108.0 MHz."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "What is the full form of HSI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal situation indicator",
            "b) Height situation indicator",
            "c) Heading situation indicator",
            "d) Heat situation indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The conventional 30 Hz reference signal is frequency modulated on a 9,960 Hz sub carrier.  The omnidirectional signal usually contains an amplitude modulated voice channel."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "A typical light-airplane VOR indicator may also be called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bearing indicator",
            "b) Omni bearing indicator",
            "c) Omni indicator",
            "d) VHF indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HSI refers to Horizontal situation indicator. It is a flight instrument that combines VOR-ILS display, thus reducing the pilot’s workload."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "What are the upper air routes known as in the US?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jet Routes",
            "b) Air Routes",
            "c) Victor Airways",
            "d) Vector Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A typical light-airplane VOR indicator may also be called Omni bearing indicator, or OBI. It consists of a knob to rotate an Omni Bearing Selector, referred to as OBS. This OBS is used to set the desired course."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "What is a collocated VOR and TACAN beacon called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VICTOR",
            "b) VECTOR",
            "c) TACVOR",
            "d) VORTAC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the United States, the upper air routes are referred to as jet routes. Further, the routes are named as such as most countries around the world, use separate systems of airway at different levels."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "What is the predicted accuracy of the VOR system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ±1.9°",
            "b) ±1.0°",
            "c) ±1.4°",
            "d) ±2.4°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: VOR and TACAN beacons that are collocated together are referred to as VORTAC. A VOR equipment collocated solely with a DME equipment is referred to as a VOR-DME. All these are radio based navigational aids for pilots."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a parameter monitored by the VOR beacons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bearing accuracy",
            "b) Signal level",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Presence of notches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The predicted accuracy of a typical VOR system is ±1.4°. It is assumed that for approximately 99.94% outcomes, a VOR based system has less than ±0.35° error."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ILS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inclined Landing System",
            "b) Incident Landing System",
            "c) Instrument Landing System",
            "d) Immediate Landing System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ILS refers to Instrument Landing System. It is an aircraft system that enables pilots to take an instrument approach to landing if they are unable to establish visual contact with the runway."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "ILS operates as a __________ based instrument approach system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ground",
            "b) Air",
            "c) Sky",
            "d) Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: ILS operates as a ground based instrument approach system. It provides the aircraft with horizontal and vertical guidance just before and during landing."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "The localizer provides _________ guidance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diagonal",
            "b) Axial",
            "c) Lateral",
            "d) Vertical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The instrument landing system of an aircraft involves two independent sub systems. The two systems are the localizer and the glide slope. The former provides lateral guidance whereas the later provides vertical guidance."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "A localizer is generally located beyond which end of a runway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neither",
            "b) Either",
            "c) Arrival",
            "d) Departure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The localizer system is generally located beyond the departure end of a runway. The system comprises a number of pairs of directional antennas."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "What of the following is the lateral component of the ILS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glide slope",
            "b) Localizer",
            "c) Beacon",
            "d) Gyro compass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Localizer is the lateral component of the ILS. Whereas, glide slope is the vertical component. The localizer works like cooperation between the transmitting airport runway and the receiving cockpit instruments."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "The LOC signal is in the __________ range.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11 Hz",
            "b) 11 MHz",
            "c) 110 Hz",
            "d) 110 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The LOC signal is in the 110 MHz range. Similarly, G/S signal is in the 330 MHz range. Localizer and glide slop carrier frequencies are paired with each other."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "What is the frequency range for LOC carrier frequencies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 108.10 MHz to 111.95 MHz",
            "b) 108.10 Hz to 111.95 Hz",
            "c) 10.10 Hz to 11.95 MHz",
            "d) 10.10 MHz to 11.95 MHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The frequency range for LOC carrier frequencies is 108.10 MHz to 111.95 MHz. Each antenna transmits a narrow beam, for the LOC."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "ILS beams intended for use in one direction only are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single beam",
            "b) Forward beam",
            "c) Back beam",
            "d) Double beam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ILS beams intended for use in one direction only are called back beams. These beams are of help during the approach, but the use of back beam localizer reduces precision compared to normal use."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "The center of the glide slope signal is arranged so as to define a glide path of roughly __________ degrees above the horizontal reference.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The center of the glide slope signal is arranged so as to define a glide path of roughly 3 degrees above the horizontal reference. A carrier signal is used to transmit the glide slope signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "What are the maximum number of channels in an instrument landing system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 900",
            "b) 90",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There can be a maximum of 40 channels in an Instrument Landing System. The channels are alternatively modulated at 90 Hz and 150 Hz. Signals from these channels are transmitted by means of co-located antennas."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "What is the full form of IGS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Instrument guiding system",
            "b) Instrument guidance system",
            "c) Instrument gauge system",
            "d) Instrument gate system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IGS refers to Instrument guidance system. It is a modified ILS used to accommodate a non-straight approach. A famous example for the IGS is approach to runway 13 at Hong Kong Kai Tak Airport."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Marker beacons operate at a carrier frequency of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75 MHz",
            "b) 75 Hz",
            "c) 750 MHz",
            "d) 75 Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The marker beacons operate at a carrier frequency of 75 MHz. The beacons transmit signals which in turn activate an indicator on the flight deck instrument panel. This further enables the pilot to hear the tone of the beacon."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Which of the following instrument is used in CATII and CATIII approaches to determine decision height?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barometer",
            "b) Altimeter",
            "c) Radar altimeter",
            "d) Radio altimeter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The radar altimeter instrument is used in CATII and CATIII approaches to determine the decision height of an aircraft. In contrary, the CATI approach relies solely on altimeter indications."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "CATIII localizers must cut off within __________ seconds of detecting an error.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CATIII localizers must cut off within 2 seconds of detecting an error. On the other hand, CATI localizers may cut off within 10 seconds of detecting an error. Higher CAT categories involve shorter cut off times."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Generally, an aircraft is established by at least __________ prior to the final approach.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 nautical miles",
            "b) 10 nautical miles",
            "c) 8 nautical miles",
            "d) 200 nautical miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally, an aircraft is established by at least 2 nautical miles prior to the final approach. At a controlled airport, ATC will direct the aircraft to the localizer course via certain assigned headings."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "When was the first landing of a scheduled passenger airliner using ILS, in the U.S?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26 January 1958",
            "b) 26 January 1938",
            "c) 26 January 1998",
            "d) 26 January 2008"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, ALS is a mandatory requirement to perform CATIII landing operations. Further, the systems should also have sufficient capability and reliability in order to control the aircraft for a safe landing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "The Wide Area Augmentation System provides precision guidance to __________ standards.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Category IIIIB",
            "b) Category IIIA",
            "c) Category II",
            "d) Category I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It was on 26 January 1938, that a scheduled passenger airliner landed using the instrument landing system for the first time ever, in the United States of America. The flight was operated by the Pennsylvania Central Airlines."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "What is the full form of RADAR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Risk Detection and Ranging",
            "b) Rate Detection and Ranging",
            "c) Real Detection and Ranging",
            "d) Radio Detection and Ranging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RADAR refers to Radio Detection and Ranging.  It can be used to detect many objects such as aircrafts, ships, spacecraft along with information about weather formations, and terrain."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Radar uses ________ waves.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radio",
            "b) Ultrasonic",
            "c) Nuclear",
            "d) Electronic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radar systems use radio waves. It is a system used to determine parameters like the range, angle, or velocity of different objects."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Which of the following systems is similar to RADAR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VOR",
            "b) ILS",
            "c) LIDAR",
            "d) VHF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: LIDAR is a system similar to radar. It is a system that predominantly uses infrared light from lasers rather than radio waves. It makes use of the other parts of the electromagnetic spectrum."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "When did the term RADAR come into existence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1900",
            "b) 1940",
            "c) 2000",
            "d) 1990"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term RADAR is used as an acronym for Radio Detection and Ranging. The term was introduced in 1940 and was first used by the US Navy."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Where was the cavity magnetron developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Australia",
            "b) Germany",
            "c) United Kingdom",
            "d) The United States"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, radio waves are invisible to the human eye. Moreover, these waves are also invisible to optical cameras."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an effect that creates Earth’s blue sky and red sunsets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rayleigh scattering",
            "b) Gauss Law",
            "c) Faradays Law",
            "d) Maxwell effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cavity magnetron was developed in the United Kingdom, its development brought new advancements in various sub systems and improved the efficiency of relatively smaller sub systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "A motion that brings about change in the number of wavelengths between the reflector and the radar, in turn causes _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time shift",
            "b) Phase shift",
            "c) Frequency shift",
            "d) Velocity shift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rayleigh scattering is the effect that creates Earth’s blue sky and red sunsets. It is named after the British physicist Lord Rayleigh."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "What is the full form of MTI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Major Target Indication",
            "b) Moving Target Indication",
            "c) Main Target Indication",
            "d) Missile Target Indication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A motion that brings about change in the number of wavelengths between the reflector and the radar, in turn causes a frequency shift in the system. Such a shift may either enhance or degrade the performance of a system."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of polarization used by RADARS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal",
            "b) Vertical",
            "c) Diagonal",
            "d) Linear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: RADARS do not use diagonal polarization. They only use horizontal, vertical, linear, and circular polarization. It is used in order to detect different types of reflections."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Circular polarization technique is used to nullify the interference caused due to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat",
            "b) Rain",
            "c) Wind",
            "d) Mountains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Circular polarization technique is used to nullify the interference caused due to rain. Random polarization technique is used for hard surfaces such as rocks, fractal surfaces or soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "A radar beam usually follows a _________ path in vacuum.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Closed",
            "b) Vertical",
            "c) Circular",
            "d) Linear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, the linear polarization returns usually indicate metal surfaces. The orientation of a linearly polarized EM wave is defined by the direction of the electric field vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Reflected signals ______ rapidly as distance increases.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decline",
            "c) Attenuate",
            "d) Travel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A radar beam usually follows a linear path in vacuum. Although the beam follows a slightly curved path in the atmosphere, this change is due to the variation of the RI of air."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "What is the full form of SNR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shot to noise ratio",
            "b) Signal to noise ratio",
            "c) Sign to noise ratio",
            "d) Side to noise ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amount of reflected signals decline rapidly with an increase in the distance travelled by the signal. Further, the noise component brings in a radar range limitation, affecting the performance of the device."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a measure of the noise produced by a receiver compared to an ideal receiver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Noise to signal ratio",
            "b) Signal to noise ratio",
            "c) Noise figure",
            "d) Noise number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SNR refers to signal to noise ratio. It can be defined as the ratio of the signal power to the noise power within the desired signal. Higher the SNR, better is the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The Doppler device separates any clutter from an aircraft by means of a ________ spectrum.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency",
            "b) Amplitude",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) Phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Noise figure is a measure of the noise produced by a receiver compared to an ideal receiver. It is a figure that needs to be minimized to improve performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following describes the time taken by a radar pulse to travel one nautical mile, reflect off a target, and then return to the radar antenna?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radar distance",
            "b) Unit radar",
            "c) Radar mile",
            "d) Radar return"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Doppler device separates any clutter from an aircraft by means of a frequency spectrum. The separation is done in such a manner that each individual signal can be separated by using various velocity differences."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "In an aircraft, the cockpit is usually referred to as the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aircraft deck",
            "b) Flight deck",
            "c) Control deck",
            "d) Operating deck"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In an aircraft, the cockpit is usually referred to as the flight deck. It is usually near the front of an aircraft, from where a pilot controls the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "When was the word cockpit first used in context to airplanes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1994",
            "b) 2004",
            "c) 1914",
            "d) 1814"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The word cockpit was first used in context to airplanes in 1914. Further, from about 1935, the term cockpit was used informally to refer to the driver’s cabin, especially in high performance cars."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "What is the full form for HOTAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hands on Throttle and Stick",
            "b) Hands on Throttle and Stand",
            "c) Hands on Thrust and Stand",
            "d) Hands on Throttle and Slats"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HOTAS is an acronym for Hands on Throttle and Stick. It is the concept of placing buttons and switches on the throttle lever and flight control stick in an aircraft cockpit."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a function provided by HOTAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radio communications",
            "b) Nose wheel steering",
            "c) Speed brake controls",
            "d) Landing gear controls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Landing gear controls is not a function provided by HOTAS. However, radio communications, nose wheel steering and speed brake controls are all functions incorporated into HOTAS."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first airplane with a completely enclosed cabin for pilots?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Avro Type F",
            "b) MD-80",
            "c) Blériot VIII",
            "d) Bell X-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Avro Type F was the first airplane with a completely enclosed cabin for pilots. It was an early single seat British aircraft, which was introduced in 1912."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "What is the full form of FCU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flight control usage",
            "b) Flight center unit",
            "c) Flight control unit",
            "d) Flight center usage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the right seat in an aircraft cockpit is the seat used by the co-pilot. The pilot sits in the left seat, so that they can operate the throttle and other instruments with his right hand."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Which of the following shows some form of heading indicator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PFD",
            "b) FCU",
            "c) ND",
            "d) ECAM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FCU refers to Flight control unit. It is a unit that allows for the selection and parameter setting of the different auto flight functions."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "What is the full form of DVI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Digital voice input",
            "b) Direct voice input",
            "c) Discrete voice input",
            "d) Damp voice input"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The PFD, or primary flight display shows some form of heading indicator and ILS/VOR deviation indicators. The PFD is usually located in a prominent position, either centrally or on either side of the cockpit."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a cockpit design discipline?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neuroscience",
            "b) Bioscience",
            "c) Human Factors Engineering",
            "d) Cognitive science"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: DVI refers to direct voice input. It is a kind of human-machine interaction and is used in the design of the cockpits of several modern military aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "The MFD is usually referred to as the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glare shield panel",
            "b) Glare panel",
            "c) Shield panel",
            "d) Display panel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the controls are incorporated onto the stick and throttle to enable the pilot to maintain a head-up position. It also helps to maintain an eyes out position, or HOTAS concept."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a standard that defines the interface between an independent cockpit display system and the avionics equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARINC",
            "b) ARINC 661",
            "c) EICAS",
            "d) ECAM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bioscience is not a cockpit design discipline. However, neuroscience, Human Factors Engineering and Cognitive science are all cockpit design disciplines."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not shown by backup instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed",
            "b) Altitude",
            "c) Heading",
            "d) Passengers onboard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The MFD is usually referred to as the glare shield panel. MFD refers to multi-function display and is usually a long narrow panel located centrally in front of the pilot."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "A traditional cockpit may also be referred as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steam cockpit",
            "b) Electric cockpit",
            "c) Gasoline cockpit",
            "d) Thermal cockpit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A traditional cockpit may also be referred as a steam cockpit. Such cockpits rely on numerous mechanical gauges to display information."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Attitude and heading reference systems and air data computers have replaced __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nautical flight instruments",
            "b) Hydraulic flight instruments",
            "c) Thermal flight instruments",
            "d) Gyroscopic flight instruments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Attitude and heading reference systems and air data computers have replaced the traditional gyroscopic flight instruments.  These systems improve reliability and maintenance cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ISIS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrated station instrument system",
            "b) Independent standby instrument system",
            "c) Integrated standby instrument system",
            "d) Integrated static instrument system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term ISIS in aviation terminology refers to integrated standby instrument system. The system acts as a backup instrument, in case there is a failure in the glass cockpit instrument system."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "The Airbus A380 is fitted with glass cockpits consisting of _________ units.",
        "Options": [
            "a) LED",
            "b) LCD",
            "c) CRT",
            "d) UHD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Boeing 2707 was one of the earliest commercial aircraft to be designed with a glass cockpit. However, the 2707 aircraft was cancelled in 1971 after a large number of technical difficulties."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first orbiter to be retrofitted with a glass cockpit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atlantis",
            "b) Columbia",
            "c) Discovery",
            "d) Endeavour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Airbus A380 is fitted with glass cockpits consisting of LCD units. The A350, 777, and 787 aircrafts also feature similar units."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "What is the full form of EVS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronic Vision systems",
            "b) End Vision systems",
            "c) Enlarged Vision systems",
            "d) Enhanced Vision systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Atlantis orbiter was the first to feature a glass cockpit. The glass cockpits were retrofitted on the orbiter and were not present initially. The process was done in the year 2000."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Which of the following systems display a realistic 3D depiction of the outside world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Virtual Vision systems",
            "b) Enhanced Vision systems",
            "c) Synthetic Vision systems",
            "d) Actual Vision systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: EVS refers to Enhanced Vision systems. These systems add real time information from external sensors, such as an infrared camera."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used as a pilot-input device in a computer-style environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure sensors",
            "b) Trackball",
            "c) Thumb pad",
            "d) Joystick"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Synthetic Vision systems, referred to as SVS display a realistic 3D depiction of the outside world. The representation is based on a database of terrain and geophysical features."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an aircraft equipped with glass cockpit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diamond DA42",
            "b) Cessna 172",
            "c) Boeing 777",
            "d) Wright Flyer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pressure sensors are not used as a pilot input device in a computer-style environment. However, a trackball, thumb pad or joystick is used as a pilot input device."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Glass cockpits eliminate the need for a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pilot",
            "b) Flight engineer",
            "c) Co pilot",
            "d) Purser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the ISIS is electronically separate from the main instruments. It can run for several hours on a backup battery and includes an artificial horizon, altimeter and airspeed indicator."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first light aircraft to feature glass cockpits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A380",
            "b) Boeing 737",
            "c) Cessna 172",
            "d) Cirrus SR22"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Wright Flyer is not an aircraft equipped with glass cockpit. However, Diamond DA42, Cessna 172 and the Boeing 777 are all equipped with glass cockpits."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "The F-35’s features a glass cockpit touchscreen dubbed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Panoramic cockpit display",
            "b) Infinite cockpit display",
            "c) Advanced cockpit display",
            "d) Clean cockpit display"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The glass cockpits eliminate the need for a flight engineer. They are thus popular with airline companies as they usually bring down costs."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Head up display is a ________ display.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Translucent",
            "b) Transparent",
            "c) Reflective",
            "d) Opaque"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Head up displays are transparent displays that are primarily used in aircrafts to ease the pilot’s workload. These displays help the pilots to read data which otherwise may not be visible to them in a certain position."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Head up displays were primarily developed for ________ aviation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Combat",
            "b) Charter",
            "c) Commercial",
            "d) Military"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These displays were primarily developed for military aviation. Although, they are being used in commercial aircrafts as well as in automobiles and other professional applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first modern military fighter to not have a fixed HUD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F-16",
            "b) F/A-18",
            "c) F-35 Lightning II",
            "d) Eurofighter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The F-35 Lightning II is the first modern military fighter to not have a fixed HUD. However, the F/A-18, F-16, and Eurofighter, use both a HUD and HMD concurrently."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Which of the following HUDs use a CRT to generate an image?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Second generation HUDs",
            "b) First generation HUDs",
            "c) Third generation HUDs",
            "d) Fourth generation HUDs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, a typical HUD contains three primary components. The three components are: a projector unit, a combiner, and a video generation computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Which of the following HUDs generate image on a phosphor screen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) First generation HUDs",
            "b) Second generation HUDs",
            "c) Third generation HUDs",
            "d) Fourth generation HUDs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Head up display devices are broadly classified into four generations. The first generation displays make use of a CRT to generate the image. These are the most common type of displays being used in aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The fourth generation HUDs use a ________ to display images and video imagery on a clear transparent medium.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiating antenna",
            "b) Scanning antenna",
            "c) Radiating laser",
            "d) Scanning laser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first generation head up displays use a phosphor screen to generate the image. Such screens have a shorter shelf life as the screen coating may degrade with time, making the equipment unusable."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft has HUDs as standard equipment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A320",
            "b) Boeing 737MAX",
            "c) Boeing 787",
            "d) Airbus A380"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fourth generation HUDs use a scanning laser to display images and video imagery on a clear transparent medium. This is the latest generation of HUDs."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor in the design of a HUD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cabin pressure",
            "b) Field of view",
            "c) Boresight",
            "d) Compatibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boeing 787 has HUDs as standard equipment. HUDs were introduced to commercial aviation in the 1970s and the technology is becoming more common day by day."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "What is the full form of LVTO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Least Virtual Take-off",
            "b) Least Visibility Take-off",
            "c) Low Virtual Take-off",
            "d) Low Visibility Take-off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LVTO refers to Low Visibility Take-off. The HUDs act as a major help in such take offs, reducing the pilots workload and the need to look at flight instruments during take-off."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following shows where the nose of the aircraft is actually pointing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flight path vector",
            "b) Boresight",
            "c) Angle of attack indicator",
            "d) Acceleration indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Boresight is used to indicate the direction in which the nose of an aircraft is pointing. The boresight is fixed on the flight display panel such that it is clearly visible to the pilots. It may also be called as waterline symbol."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "When was the modern HUD used in IFR approaches to landing, developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1999",
            "b) 1905",
            "c) 2005",
            "d) 1975"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The modern HUD used in IFR approaches to landing was developed in 1975. HUDs have evolved from the reflector sight technology, a parallax-free optical sight technology."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Which of the following HUDs uses optical waveguides to produce images?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Second generation HUDs",
            "b) First generation HUDs",
            "c) Third generation HUDs",
            "d) Fourth generation HUDs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The third generation HUDs use optical waveguides to produce images. These images are directly produced in the combiner rather than using a projection system."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which of the following shows the wing’s angle relative to the airflow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boresight",
            "b) Velocity vector symbol",
            "c) Angle of attack indicator",
            "d) Navigation data and symbols"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the second gen head up displays use a solid state light source. Such systems are usually used in commercial aircrafts and may be slightly expensive in comparison to other similar systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "During the approach and landing, a pilot can fly the approach by keeping the FPV symbol at the desired _______ angle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attack",
            "b) Descent",
            "c) Inclination",
            "d) Pitch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The angle of attack indicator shows the wing’s angle relative to the airflow. It is often displayed as α. It is a necessary requirement for HUDs."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "What is the full form of HDDs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heading-down displays",
            "b) Heat-down displays",
            "c) Head-down displays",
            "d) Hill-down displays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the approach and landing, a pilot can fly the approach by keeping the FPV symbol at the desired descent angle. Along with this, the touchdown point on the runway should also be taken care of."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Objects that are 3 degrees below the horizon as viewed from the cockpit, appear at the _________ degree index on the HUD display.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -300",
            "b) +300",
            "c) +3",
            "d) −3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the collimated images on the HUD combiner are perceived to be existing at or near the optical infinity. It indicates that the pilot does not need to refocus his eyes to view the outside world and the HUD display."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "What is the full form of HMSD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heading-mounted sight and display",
            "b) Horizon-mounted sight and display",
            "c) Helmet-mounted sight and display",
            "d) Horizontally-mounted sight and display"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term HMSD in aviation terminology refers to helmet mounted sight and display. It is a modern technique that enables cueing of different weapons in a combat aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a pointer to direct air-to-air and air-to-ground weapons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arm Angle",
            "b) Thigh angle",
            "c) Hand angle",
            "d) Head angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The head angle acts as a pointer to direct air-to-air and air-to-ground weapons. The pilot can direct weapons to a target merely by pointing his head at the target."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "The weapons are directed at the target by actuating a switch via _________ controls.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RADAR",
            "b) HOTAS",
            "c) Mechanical",
            "d) Electronic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The weapons are directed at the target by actuating a switch via HOTAS controls. HOTAS refers to Hands on Throttle-And-Stick, it is a concept which provides all critical controls on the throttle and stick."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which of the following parameters is not displayed on the HMD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airspeed",
            "b) Altitude",
            "c) Target range",
            "d) Fuel capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, when in close combat prior to HMDs, the pilot had to align the aircraft to shoot at a target. HMDs allow pilots to simply point their head at a target, assign it to weapon and shoot."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "What is the full form of HOBS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High Off-Boresight",
            "b) Heading Off-Boresight",
            "c) High Off-Bore",
            "d) Heading Off-Bore"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fuel capacity is not displayed on the HMD. However, airspeed, altitude and target range along with weapon seeker status, g force and other parameters are displayed on the HMD."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": " Which of the following was the first air force to fly the helmet sight operationally?",
        "Options": [
            "a) German Air Force",
            "b) French Air Force",
            "c) Indian Air Force",
            "d) South African Air Force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HOBS refers to High Off-Boresight weapons. HMD systems when combined with HOBS provide the aircrew ability to attack and destroy nearly any target seen by the pilot."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "The line between the pilot’s eye and reticle on the visor is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Line of approach",
            "b) Line of attack",
            "c) Line of sight",
            "d) Line of descent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The South African Air Force was the first air force to fly the helmet sight operationally. The nation emerged as one of the pioneers in helmet mounted sight technology."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor affecting the implementation of HMDs in aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Latency",
            "b) Field of regard",
            "c) Durability",
            "d) Air temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The line between the pilot’s eye and reticle on the visor may be referred to as the line of sight, in aviation terminology. This line is said to be there between the aircraft and its intended target."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Which of the following technique requires precise magnetic mapping of the flight deck?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electromagnetic tracking",
            "b) Sonic tracking",
            "c) Optical tracking",
            "d) Hybrid tracking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electromagnetic tracking requires precise magnetic mapping of the flight deck. It is to account for the ferrous and conductive materials in the seat and flight deck to reduce angular errors in the measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not one of the basic methods used in current HMD technology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inertial",
            "b) Optical",
            "c) Thermal",
            "d) Hybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thermal is not one of the basic methods used in current HMD technology. There are five basic methods currently being used in HMD technology, they are inertial, optical, electromagnetic, sonic and hybrid."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Optical systems employ _________ emitters on the helmet to measure the pilot’s head position.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat",
            "b) Radio",
            "c) Ultrasonic",
            "d) Infrared"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The optical systems employ infrared emitters on the helmet to measure the pilot’s head position. One of the limitations is sensitivity to sunlight or other heat sources."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "What are the typical operating frequencies for sonic tracking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 MHz to 100 MHz",
            "b) 50 Hz to 100 Hz",
            "c) 50 kHz to 100 kHz",
            "d) 50 mHz to 100 mHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The typical operating frequencies for sonic tracking are in the 50 kHz to 100 kHz range. These can be made to carry audio sound information directly to the pilot’s ears by means of subcarrier modulation."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "What is the full form of IHADSS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrated Heading and Display Sighting System",
            "b) Integrated Height and Display Sighting System",
            "c) Integrated Helmet and Display Sighting System",
            "d) Integrated Helmet and Direction Sighting System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the hybrid inertial/optical trackers feature high accuracy. Although, they offer low latency and suffer from precession and drift over time."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "The scorpion helmet mounted display system was introduced by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing",
            "b) Thales",
            "c) Airbus",
            "d) BAE Systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IHADSS refers to Integrated Helmet and Display Sighting System. The IHADSS is used on the Italian Agusta A129 Mangusta and features Nap-of-the-earth night navigation."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "What is the full form of HObIT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hybrid Optical based Information Tracker",
            "b) Hydraulic Optical based Inertial Tracker",
            "c) Hybrid Optical based Inertial Tracker",
            "d) Hydraulic Optical based Information Tracker"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thales introduced the scorpion helmet mounted display system. It was introduced to the military aviation market in 2008 and was the winner of the USAF/ANG/AFRes Helmet Mounted Integrated Targeting program."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "The Honeywell M142 IHADSS comes with a ________ field of view.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300° by 100°",
            "b) 100° by 300°",
            "c) 4° by 3°",
            "d) 40° by 30°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the pilots using scorpion, can view both night vision images and the symbols on the display. The scorpion was designed to be installed on a standard issue HGU-55/P helmet."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a suitable place to perform infrared heating de-icing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Apron",
            "b) Aircraft bay",
            "c) Hangar",
            "d) MRO facility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, propylene glycol is less toxic than ethylene glycol. Both of them are de-icing fluids used by airlines for de-icing aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Which of the following compounds are not used at airports?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethylene based",
            "b) Chloride based",
            "c) Propylene based",
            "d) Copper based"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Infrared heating de-icing process take place inside a specially constructed hangar. It is a substantially faster method as compared to other deicing methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a low cost pavement de-icing mixture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon Mixture",
            "b) Aluminum mixture",
            "c) Urea mixture",
            "d) Quartz Mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Compounds primarily based on chloride are not used at airports around the world. Such compounds result in increased corroding on aircrafts and other equipment’s. Salts are an example of chloride based compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "A de-icing fluid fails when it can no longer absorb the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal",
            "b) Contaminant",
            "c) Air particles",
            "d) Rust particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Urea mixture is an economical de-icing mixture used primarily for deicing airport pavements. After application, the mixture gets converted into ammonia and thus has been phased out of most airports around the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "All anti-ice fluids offer _________ protection.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limited",
            "b) Complete",
            "c) Permanent",
            "d) Artificial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A de-icing fluid fails when it can no longer absorb the contaminant. In such a case, the fluid essentially becomes a contaminant itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "What is the full form of LOUT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower operational use tank",
            "b) Limited operational use temperature",
            "c) Lower operational use temperature",
            "d) Limited operational use tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All anti-ice fluids offer limited protection. The protection is dependent upon frozen contaminant type and the prevailing weather conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not caused due to ice on aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Critical control surfaces become rough and uneven",
            "b) Disruption of smooth air flow",
            "c) Increased drag",
            "d) De pressurization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, propylene glycol is less toxic than ethylene glycol. Although PG is classified as non-toxic, it pollutes waterways as it consumes large amounts of oxygen while decomposing."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Slats are located on the leading edge of the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wings",
            "b) Engines",
            "c) Rudder",
            "d) Tail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slats are located on the leading edge of the wings. They are one of the several high lift devices used on aircrafts."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about slats?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases stall speed",
            "b) Decreases coefficient of lift",
            "c) Helps an aircraft to take off and land in shorter distances",
            "d) Helps an aircraft to fly at slower speeds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Slats produce a higher coefficient of lift, due to a suitable angle of attack and speed. However, they decrease stall speed and help the aircraft to fly at slower speeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Slats allow the aircraft to operate at a higher angle of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incidence",
            "b) Attack",
            "c) Pitch",
            "d) Descent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slats allow the aircraft to operate at a higher angle of attack. They are usually retracted in normal flight phases to minimize drag."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an approach that could rival slats?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Folding wingtips",
            "b) Carbon fiber fuselage",
            "c) Flexible wings",
            "d) Lower takeoff weight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flexible wings is a prominent approach that could rival slats. One such project is the X-53 Active Aero elastic Wing, which is a NASA effort."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Flap systems run along the _________ of the wing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trailing edge",
            "b) Leading edge",
            "c) Corners",
            "d) Bottom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, springs extend the automatic slats. As an aircraft slows down, the aerodynamic force is reduced and springs are used to extend the slats. Such slats are not usually found on modern aircrafts."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "When were slats developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1918",
            "b) 1988",
            "c) 2008",
            "d) 1948"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flap systems run along the trailing edge of the wing of an aircraft. Flaps are one of the many devices used on aircraft to control its lift."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which of the following slats are most commonly used on airliners?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical",
            "b) Fixed",
            "c) Powered",
            "d) Automatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slats were first developed in 1918, by Gustav Lachmann. Lachmann presented a patent for leading edge slats in Germany, in the year 1918."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Handley-Page slats refer to _________ slats.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Automatic",
            "b) Powered",
            "c) Fixed",
            "d) Manual"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Powered slats are most commonly used on airliners. These slat extensions can be controlled by the pilot and thus are most favorable to be used on airliners."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to reduce the nose down pitching moment at higher speeds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Counter Flap setting",
            "b) Positive Flap setting",
            "c) Negative Flap setting",
            "d) Zero Flap setting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In order to reduce the nose down pitching moment, the aircraft uses the negative flap setting. The setting is used at higher speeds and helps reduce the trim drag on the aircraft. "
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Flaps are used to ________ the lift.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Maintain",
            "c) Nullify",
            "d) Decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flaps are used to increase the lift. Flaps are a kind of high-lift device that increases the lift of an aircraft at a given airspeed and help the aircraft adjust the flow of wind over its wings."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about flaps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases stall speed",
            "b) Decrease drag in mid flight",
            "c) Helps an aircraft to take off and land in shorter distances",
            "d) Helps an aircraft to fly at slower speeds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, flaps reduce the minimum speed at which the aircraft will safely maintain flight. His is because they raise the maximum lift coefficient or the upper limit to the lift a wing can generate."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Flaps are located on the leading edge of the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wings",
            "b) Engines",
            "c) Rudder",
            "d) Tail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flaps do not decrease drag in id flight, however they increase the drag if not retracted during mid-flight. Thus while flaps are only deployed during takeoff or landing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Crosswinds are __________ the line of flight.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adjacent",
            "b) Along",
            "c) Perpendicular to",
            "d) Across"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flaps are located on the leading edge of the wings. They are one of the several high lift devices used on aircrafts to increase the lift."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft has an inboard aileron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 747",
            "b) Airbus A380",
            "c) Airbus A340",
            "d) Airbus A330"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crosswinds are winds across the line of flight. These winds cause the windward side of the aircraft to generate more lift and drag."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "FlexFoil refers to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible Slats",
            "b) Flexible Flaperons",
            "c) Flexible Flaps",
            "d) Flexible Wings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Boeing 747 has an inboard aileron. However, the Airbus A380, A340 and A330 aircrafts have no inboard aileron. "
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Flaperons are a combination of which of the following pairs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flaps and slats",
            "b) Flaps and ailerons",
            "c) Slats an ailerons",
            "d) Slats and wingtips"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term FlexFoil in aviation terminology refers to flexible flaps. It is a modern technique that functions by bending a lattice that in turn changes the airfoil shape of the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CTEF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circular Trailing-Edge Flap",
            "b) Constant Trailing-Edge Flap",
            "c) Combined Trailing-Edge Flap",
            "d) Continuous Trailing-Edge Flap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flaperons are a combination of flaps and ailerons. They act as an aircraft control surface improving the flight dynamics and making flight control easier."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "What are flaps with one or more slots called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slotted flap",
            "b) Fowler flap",
            "c) Split flap",
            "d) Gouge flap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, flap deployment decreases aircraft pitch angle. This in turn lowers the nose of the aircraft thereby improving the pilot’s view of the runway during landing."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Fowler flap is a type of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leading edge flap",
            "b) Plain flap",
            "c) Split flap",
            "d) Slotted flap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The term CTEF in aviation terminology refers to Continuous Trailing Edge Flap. The device uses various mechanical hinges that are deployed to improve system reliability and stability."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Which of the following provides lateral control to the aircraft, rather than changing its lift characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spoilers",
            "b) Ailerons",
            "c) Rudders",
            "d) Wingtips"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flaps with one or more slots are called slotted flaps. These slots are designed to increase their effectiveness. They provide increased lift as compared to a split flap."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Aileron is a ________ word.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spanish",
            "b) French",
            "c) Persian",
            "d) British"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aileron is a French word. It refers to little wing or fin in the French language. It is a hinged flight control surface that improves the aerodynamic stability of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Ailerons are used to control the aircraft in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roll",
            "b) Pitch",
            "c) Yaw",
            "d) Thunderstorms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ailerons are used to control the aircraft in roll. Roll refers to the movement of the aircraft around its longitudinal axis. This is a vital and crucial aspect of flight control."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "What is the movement around the longitudinal axis called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yawing",
            "b) Curving",
            "c) Tilting",
            "d) Banking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, the modern aileron was invented 1868 and patented in the same year. It was invented by the British scientist Matthew Piers Watt Boulton based on his 1864 paper on Aerial Locomotion."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Aileron is located on the trailing edge of the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wings",
            "b) Engines",
            "c) Rudder",
            "d) Tail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The aircrafts movement around its longitudinal axis is called banking. It may also be referred to as rolling and it results in a change in flight path due to the tilting of the lift vector."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "What did the Wright brothers use instead of ailerons for roll control on their glider in 1902?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flaperons",
            "b) Flaps",
            "c) Wing wrapping",
            "d) Wing warping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aileron is located on the trailing edge of the wings. It is their on each wing of a fixed wing aircraft and is used in pairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to effectively compensate adverse yaw?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudder",
            "b) Empennage",
            "c) Flaps",
            "d) Slats"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Wright brothers used wing warping instead of ailerons for roll control on their glider in 1902. The Wright Brothers were successful in having better roll control in comparison to the early airplanes that made use of movable surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "When one aileron is moved downward, the other is moved _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Outward",
            "b) Inward",
            "c) Upward",
            "d) Downward"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The adverse yaw is effectively compensated by the use of the rudder. It results in a side force on the vertical tail which in turn opposes the adverse yaw by creating a favorable yawing moment."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Trim tabs are located at or near the trailing edge of the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engine",
            "b) Aileron",
            "c) Wings",
            "d) Rudder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When one aileron is moved downward, the other is moved upward. The ailerons work in pairs and are typically inter connected."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "As an aileron is deflected upward, the spade produces a _________ aerodynamic force.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Upward",
            "b) Inward",
            "c) Outward",
            "d) Downward"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The trim tabs in an aircraft are commonly located at or near the trailing edge of the aileron. These tabs are basically small and movable sections that resemble and work similar to scaled down ailerons."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following trim tab can be controlled from within the cockpit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adjustable trim tab",
            "b) Automatic trim tab",
            "c) Fixed trim tab",
            "d) Hydraulic trim tab"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, the trim tabs come in two forms: adjustable and fixed. These tabs are provided to adjust or trim out the pressure needed against any unwanted movement."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "The down going aileron __________ the lift on its wing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maintains",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Increases",
            "d) Nullifies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As an aileron is deflected upward, the spade produces a downward aerodynamic force. This tends to rotate the entire assembly so as to further deflect the aileron upward."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an unwanted side effect of aileron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adverse roll",
            "b) Adverse yaw",
            "c) Adverse pitch",
            "d) Adverse incline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The adjustable trim tab can be controlled from within the cockpit. It is locate such that different power settings or flight attitudes can be compensated for."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Spoilers may also be differentially operated for roll control in place of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Empennage",
            "b) Rudder",
            "c) Ailerons",
            "d) Flaps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The spoilers may also be differentially operated for roll control in place of ailerons. Such spoilers were first developed in 1948 by Martin Aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "A spoiler may also be called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lift dumper",
            "b) Lift enhancer",
            "c) Thrust dumper",
            "d) Thrust enhancer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A spoiler may also be called a lift duper, or lift spoiler. It is a device placed to intentionally manipulate the lift component of an airfoil in a controlled way."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about spoilers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Create a controlled stall",
            "b) Decrease descent rate",
            "c) Placed on wings",
            "d) Reduce lift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, spoilers on an aircraft work differently as compared to airbrakes. Spoilers are responsible for reducing lift, on the contrary airbrakes have no effect on the lift of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Where are the spoilers placed on an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) On the top surface of a wing",
            "b) On the bottom surface of a wing",
            "c) On the top surface of an engine",
            "d) On the bottom surface of an engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spoilers help in increasing descent rate without increasing speed. These devices create a controlled stall over the portion of the wing behind it."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "How is the airspeed affected in a descent without spoilers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set to zero",
            "b) No affect",
            "c) Decreased",
            "d) Increased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In an aircraft, the spoilers are placed on the top surface of a wing. They are plates that can be extended upward into the airflow to spoil it."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the following spoilers are used for descent control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inboard spoilers",
            "b) Outboard spoilers",
            "c) Mid span spoilers",
            "d) Fixed spoilers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The airspeed is increased when an aircraft descends without spoilers. Further, the engine will be at low power thus producing less heat than normal."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which of the following position is selected for lift dumpers on the landing approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Off",
            "b) Manual",
            "c) Automatic",
            "d) Deployed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For descent control in an aircraft, inboard spoilers are used. Further, when roll control is required, the aircraft makes use of outboard spoilers, which may also be referred to as mid span spoilers."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "What is the combination of spoilers and ailerons called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ailpoilers",
            "b) Spoilerons",
            "c) Spelerons",
            "d) Spoails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Automatic position is selected for lift dumpers on the landing approach. These devices are deployed in a fraction of a second at the moment of touchdown."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "What is the full form of PIO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch induced oscillation",
            "b) Pilot inclined oscillation",
            "c) Pilot induced oscillation",
            "d) Pitch inclined oscillation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PIO refers to pilot induced oscillation. These are oscillations that occur due to the pilot’s effort to control the aircraft. Such oscillations are necessary for providing stability to the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "In an FBW system, how are the electronic signals transmitted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manually",
            "b) Using radars",
            "c) Using sensors",
            "d) Using wires"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In an FBW system, the electronic signals are transmitted using wires. The movements of flight controls are first converted to electronic signals and then transmitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "FBW system replaces the manual flight controls of an aircraft with an _________ interface.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Automatic",
            "b) Electronic",
            "c) Mechanical",
            "d) Thermal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The FBW system replaces the manual flight controls of an aircraft with an electronic interface. The manual flight controls may also be referred to as conventional controls."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "FBW is a ________ electrically signaled system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudo",
            "b) Physically",
            "c) Partially",
            "d) Purely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, fly by wire systems do not require pilot’s involvement. These systems protect the pilot operating outside of the aircraft’s safe performance envelope."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first Airbus aircraft to feature FBW controls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A320",
            "b) A380",
            "c) 777",
            "d) A340"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: FBW systems are purely electrically signaled systems. These are modern systems equipped on both military and commercial aircrafts. Such systems are also helpful in reducing the gross weight of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "What is the full form of BITE?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Built in training equipment",
            "b) Built in task equipment",
            "c) Built in transfer equipment",
            "d) Built in test equipment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Airbus A320 series of aircrafts were the first Airbus airliners that used full-authority FBW controls. Boeing followed with its 777 aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first production fly-by-wire airliner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 737",
            "b) A320",
            "c) Concorde",
            "d) MD80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: BITE in aviation terminology refers to built in test equipment. Such equipment’s are used primarily on aircraft’s featuring FBW systems in order to conduct their preflight safety checks."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Which was the first pure electronic fly-by-wire aircraft with no mechanical or hydraulic backup?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A380",
            "b) Airbus A320",
            "c) Apollo 11",
            "d) Apollo Lunar Landing Training Vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Concorde was the first production fly-by-wire airliner. The aircraft first flew on 2 March 1969 and retired on 24 October 2003."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about FBW systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improved safety",
            "b) High maintenance costs",
            "c) Physically lighter",
            "d) Reliable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, FBW aircraft can be lighter as compared to a similar design with conventional controls. This is partly because of the lower overall weight of the system components, and partly because the natural stability of the aircraft can be relaxed."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "The Airbus A340 has a purely _________ back-up rudder control system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical",
            "b) Electronic",
            "c) Manual",
            "d) Hydraulic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: FBW systems are credited for reducing the maintenance costs as compared to the conventional controls. These systems are much more reliable and also provide enhanced flight economy."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first business jet with fly-by-wire controls?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Learjet 45",
            "b) Learjet 60",
            "c) Dassault Falcon 7X",
            "d) Gulfstream G550"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Airbus A340 has a purely electrical back-up rudder control system. However, beginning with the A380, all flight control systems on airbus aircrafts have back-up systems that are purely electrical."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "What is the full form of FADEC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flight Authority Direct Engine Control",
            "b) Flight Authority Digital Engine Control",
            "c) Full Authority Digital Engine Control",
            "d) Full Authority Direct Engine Control"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Dassault Falcon 7X was the first business jet with fly-by-wire controls. The aircraft offers a range of 5,950 nautical miles."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first production aircraft to feature fly by optics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Learjet 23",
            "b) Hawker 4000",
            "c) Learjet 40",
            "d) Kawasaki P-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: FADEC refers to Full Authority Digital Engine Control. It is a system that permits operation of the flight control systems and auto throttles for the engines to be fully integrated."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "In power by wire systems, the hydraulic circuit is replaced by an ________ circuit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrical power",
            "b) Thermal power",
            "c) Electronic power",
            "d) Mechanical power"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, Fly by optics is also referred to as fly by light. This is due to the use of fiber optics. The system might be used instead of fly by wire because it offers a higher data transfer rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "ESD in common terminology refers to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrostatic discharge",
            "b) Electric discharge",
            "c) Electronic discharge",
            "d) Elastic discharge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term ESD in common terminology refers to Electrostatic discharge. These are a certain type of charge particles that are commonly found on humans, electronic tools and various other objects. They may be hazardous under certain conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Electrostatic sensitive device is a component which can be damaged by common _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic charges",
            "b) Static charges",
            "c) Electric charges",
            "d) Electronic charges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electrostatic sensitive device is a component that can be damaged by common static charges. Densely packed electronic parts become more and more vulnerable to ESD."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "What is the electrical resistance of conductive ESD protective materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between 1mΩ and 1MΩ",
            "b) Between 1kΩ and 1MΩ",
            "c) Between 10kΩ and 10MΩ",
            "d) Between 10mΩ and 10MΩ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The electrical resistance of conductive ESD protective materials is between 1kΩ and 1MΩ. There are several kinds of ESD protective materials available."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a material that attenuates current and electrical fields?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anti-static",
            "b) Conductive",
            "c) Shielding",
            "d) Dissipative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shielding material is a material that attenuates current and electrical fields. Different ESD materials possess different characteristics and behave differently in the same environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Anti-static materials are also known as _________ materials.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low charging",
            "b) High charging",
            "c) Null charging",
            "d) Dash charging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, dissipative materials have an electrical resistance between 1MΩ and 1TΩ. Electrical resistance of such materials is greater as compared to conductive materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an alternate to photoemission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shielding",
            "b) Proton emission",
            "c) Corona discharge",
            "d) Electrical grounding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The anti-static materials are also known as low charging materials. These materials limit the buildup of charges by prevention of triboelectric effects, through physical separation."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a device that reduces or inhibits electrostatic discharge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic device",
            "b) Static device",
            "c) Anti-static device",
            "d) Anti-dynamic device"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Corona discharge is an alternate to photoemission. It is an electron emission effect used by antistatic systems. It is mostly used in a larger area, such as a factory floor or workshop."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for the neutralization of static charges in a larger area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photoemission",
            "b) Antistatic agents",
            "c) Electrical grounding",
            "d) Static agents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Devices that decrease the magnitude of electrostatic discharge may be referred to as anti-static devices. Such devices if not used properly may also damage electrical components."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "An ionizing bar is sometimes referred to as a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anti dynamic bar",
            "b) Antistatic bar",
            "c) Dynamic bar",
            "d) Static bar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of neutralization of static charges present in a significantly larger area, may be called as photoemission. The process is based on the emission of electrons into an area, which in turn neutralize the targeted object."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Dissipative bags are usually _________ in color.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow",
            "b) Pink",
            "c) Purple",
            "d) Blue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, humans beings have natural electrical sources running through the body, thus touching an ESD unequipped can result in serious material damage or injuries."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Which of the following antistatic bags are manufactured with a layer of conductive metal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shielding antistatic bags",
            "b) Dissipative antistatic bags",
            "c) Conductive antistatic bags",
            "d) Grounding antistatic bags"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conductive antistatic bags are manufactured with a layer of conductive metal. The conductive metal is often aluminum along with a dielectric layer of plastic covered in a static dissipative coating."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "What is the color of conductive foam used for storing electronic components, prone to ESD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow",
            "b) Red",
            "c) Pink",
            "d) Black"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, in order to store components that are prone to damage caused ESD, manufacturers make use of antistatic bags. These bags prevent any damage to the components that may be caused due to ESD."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "For the ESD garments to work appropriately, they must also be connected to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electricity",
            "b) Ground",
            "c) Semiconductors",
            "d) Insulators"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The conductive foam used for storing electronic components, prone to ESD is black in color. Foam also exists in pink, but it is dissipative in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Which of the following will provide no ground reference?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal mat",
            "b) Conducting mat",
            "c) Insulating mat",
            "d) Static mat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In order for ESD garments to function appropriately, it is mandatory for the garment to have connection with the ground, i.e. ground reference. These garments may not be sufficient to prevent a person from ESD, and thus additional devices for ESD prevention may also be required."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "What is the typical resistance of an antistatic mat, between points on the mat and to ground?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 105  ohms to 108 ohms",
            "b) 105  kilo ohms to 108 kilo ohms",
            "c) 108  ohms to 1010 ohms",
            "d) 108 kilo ohms to 1010 kilo ohms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, non-metalized bags are much more durable in comparison to their metal counterparts. Non-metal bags also offer longer shelf life in comparison to the metal bags, which have a much shorter shelf life."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "The safety wrist strap is connected to the ground port by means of a ________ mega ohm resistor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Out of the given options, an insulating mat will offer no ground reference. In other terms, the mat will not have grounding and may not be safe for repairing and overhaul of ESD components."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "The role of an antistatic agent is to make the surface or material slightly _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shielded",
            "b) Dissipative",
            "c) Conductive",
            "d) Static"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The typical resistance of an antistatic mat, between points on the mat and to ground is between 105  ohms to 108 ohms. The antistatic mat is one of a number of antistatic devices designed to help eliminate static electricity."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is generally referred to as a material which possess triboelectric charging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dissipative",
            "b) Anti-static",
            "c) Insulative",
            "d) Conducting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The safety wrist strap is connected to the ground port by means of a 1 mega ohm resistor. This connection is made using a retractable cable that is coiled along its entire length."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an ESD material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dissipative",
            "b) Anti-static",
            "c) Insulative",
            "d) Conducting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The role of an antistatic agent is to make the surface or material slightly conductive. The antistatic agent is a compound used for the treatment of materials, in order to eliminate the buildup of static electricity."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "When did the Concorde enter service?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21 January 2000",
            "b) 21 January 1999",
            "c) 21 January 1959",
            "d) 21 January 1976"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Concorde aircraft entered into service on 21 January 1976. The aircraft flew for 27 years and was withdrawn from commercial service due to various reasons. The aircraft was capable of flying at supersonic speeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "The Concorde was jointly developed and manufactured under an _________ treaty.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arab-French",
            "b) Anglo-British",
            "c) Anglo-French",
            "d) Arab-British"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Concorde was jointly developed and manufactured under an Anglo-French treaty, by Sud Aviation and the British Aircraft Corporation."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "How much did the Concorde program cost?",
        "Options": [
            "a) £1.3 billion",
            "b) £1.3 million",
            "c) £70 billion",
            "d) £70 million"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Concorde program costed £1.3 billion. However, the original program cost estimate was of £70 million. Huge overruns and delays resulted in such extreme costs."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "What does the word Concorde mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flight",
            "b) War",
            "c) Harmony",
            "d) Supersonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concorde is a French word, which has an English equivalent, concord. The aircraft has been named after this word. Both words mean harmony or unity."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operator of the Concorde?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air France",
            "b) Air India",
            "c) British Airways",
            "d) Singapore Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Air India is not an operator of the Concorde. However, Air France, British Airways and Singapore Airlines were operators of the Concorde. Singapore Airlines had one aircraft on short term lease."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Which of the following was not a launch customer of the Concorde?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air France",
            "b) BOAC",
            "c) Emirates",
            "d) Pan-Am"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Concorde is an ogee delta winged aircraft. The aircraft is equipped with four Olympus engines, based on those employed in RAF’s Avro Vulcan strategic bomber."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Apart from the Concorde, which of the following is one of only two supersonic transports that has been operated commercially?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A380",
            "b) Tupolev Tu-144",
            "c) MD 80",
            "d) Boeing 777"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the aircraft flew its first test flight on 2 March 1969. The aircraft flew from Toulouse in France and numerous checks were performed during the test flight.  Further, the first supersonic flight by the Concorde was on 1 October 1969."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "The Concorde had seating for up to ________ passengers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 428",
            "b) 28",
            "c) 228",
            "d) 128"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Emirates was not a launch customer of the Concorde. However, Pan Am, BOAC, and Air France were the launch customers, with six Concorde’s each."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "What was the maximum speed of the Concorde?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 2.04",
            "b) Mach 0.24",
            "c) Mach 1.5",
            "d) Mach 24"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Tupolev Tu-144 and Concorde are the only two supersonic transports that have been operated commercially. The Tupolev Tu-144 operated in the late 1970s."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Which of the following developed Concorde’s thrust-by-wire engine control system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BAE Systems",
            "b) Ultra Electronics",
            "c) General Electronics",
            "d) Rolls-Royce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Concorde did not have auxiliary power unit. This is because the aircraft would only visit large airports where ground air start carts are available."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "What was the maximum temperature that aluminum could sustain over the life of the aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 ℃",
            "b) 1270 ℃",
            "c) 100 ℃",
            "d) 127 ℃"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Concorde had seating for 92 to 128 passengers. The aircraft was primarily used by wealthy passengers who could pay a high price in return for the aircraft’s speed and luxury service."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "The Concorde airframe was designed for life off ________ flying hours.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45,000",
            "b) 4,500",
            "c) 450",
            "d) 4,50,000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aircraft’s airframe was designed for life off 45,000 flying hours. The aircraft went through two cycles of heating and cooling during a flight, firstly cooling down as it gained altitude, then heating up after going supersonic."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "When any aircraft passes the critical Mach of that particular airframe, the centre of pressure shifts ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rightwards",
            "b) Leftwards",
            "c) Rearwards",
            "d) Frontwards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The centre of pressure shifts rearwards when any aircraft passes the critical Mach of that particular airframe. This phenomenon causes a pitch down moment on the aircraft, if the centre of gravity still remains where it was."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "When the radiation levels became a bit too high, the aircraft had to descend below __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4,700 feet",
            "b) 47,000 feet",
            "c) 3,700 feet",
            "d) 37,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the radiation levels became a bit too high, the aircraft had to descend below 47,000 feet. This was done in order to silence certain speculations on the aircraft, which said supersonic travel may increase the chances of skin cancer."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "What was Concorde’s maximum cruising altitude?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50,000 feet",
            "b) 40,000 feet",
            "c) 30,000 feet",
            "d) 60,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the aircraft had certain livery restrictions. A major portion of the aircraft was supposed to be painted white, so as to avoid over heating of the airframe due to effects of supersonic flight."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "What was Concorde’s normal landing speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 170 miles per hour",
            "b) 1,700 miles per hour",
            "c) 100 miles per hour",
            "d) 1,000 miles per hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Concorde offered a significantly high maximum cruising altitude of 60,000 feet, which is approximately 18,000 m. It may also be noted that most subsonic aircrafts have cruise altitudes under 44,000 feet."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "The aircraft’s tires are rated to a maximum speed of ________ on the runway.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 mph",
            "b) 25 mph",
            "c) 250 mph",
            "d) 500 mph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Concorde’s normal landing speed was 170 miles per hour, which is approximately 274 km/h. The aircraft adopted a higher angle of attack at low speeds than conventional aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Concorde required a minimum of ________ runway length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4,000 feet",
            "b) 6,000 feet",
            "c) 7,000 feet",
            "d) 5,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The aircraft’s tires are rated to a maximum speed of 250 mph, approximately 400 km/h on the runway. The undercarriage had to be unusually strong because of the way Concorde’s delta wing generated lift."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Which of the following developed the brakes for Concorde?",
        "Options": [
            "a) General Electric",
            "b) BAE Systems",
            "c) Boeing",
            "d) Dunlop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the final flight of a Concorde, worldwide took place on 26 November 2003. The aircraft landed at Filton, Bristol in the United Kingdom."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "When did Air France’s final Concorde flight take place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 27 June 2000",
            "b) 27 June 2003",
            "c) 27 June 2009",
            "d) 27 June 1998"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Concorde required a minimum of 6,000 feet runway length. Although, this was considerably less than the shortest runway Concorde ever actually landed on."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Concorde offered a range of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5,900 nautical miles",
            "b) 300 nautical miles",
            "c) 3,900 nautical miles",
            "d) 500 nautical miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Brakes for the Concorde were developed by Dunlop, a tire manufacturer having its headquarters in the United States. Further, the Concorde was the first aircraft to feature carbon based brakes."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "How long was the wing span of Concorde?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 84 feet",
            "b) 80 feet",
            "c) 70 feet",
            "d) 100 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Air France’s final Concorde flight took place on 27 June 2003, when F-BVFC retired to Toulouse. The airline made its final commercial Concorde landing in New York City from Paris on 30 May 2003."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "What is the full form of MRO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maintenance, repair and overhaul",
            "b) Maintenance, repair and organization",
            "c) Maintain, repair and overhaul",
            "d) Maintain, repair and organization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aircraft maintenance, repair and overhaul (MRO) is an essential requirement to ensure that aircrafts are maintained in pre-determined conditions of airworthiness in order to safely fly around the globe."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most extensive check to be performed on an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Category A-Check",
            "b) Category B-Check",
            "c) Category D-Check",
            "d) Category C-Check"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Category-D check is the most extensive check to be performed on an aircraft, it may also be referred to as Heavy Maintenance Visit. Such checks are performed every 5 to 6 years and require a tremendous amount of manpower."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Flight Data Recorder is also known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orange Box",
            "b) Black Box",
            "c) Red Box",
            "d) Green Box"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Flight data recorder or commercial aircraft cockpit data recorders are also commonly referred as a black box. These recorders store ﬂight information and audio from the aircraft cockpit."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Aircraft equipment’s operate at _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 350Hz",
            "b) 450Hz",
            "c) 400Hz",
            "d) 40Hz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aircraft equipment’s operate at 400Hz. The equipment operates at high frequency in order to reduce their core size, thus being lighter and more efficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most frequently conducted check on an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Category C-Check",
            "b) Category A-Check",
            "c) Category B-Check",
            "d) Category D-Check"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Category A-check is performed approximately every 500 – 800 ﬂight hours. The check needs about 20 man hours and is usually performed overnight at an airport gate. All other category checks are more extensive."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which of the following indicates an aircraft’s rotation about its longitudinal axis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turn Indicator",
            "b) Pitch Indicator",
            "c) Yaw Indicator",
            "d) Bank indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The turn indicator indicates an aircraft’s rotation about its longitudinal axis. The instrument includes Turn-and-Slip Indicator and the Turn Coordinator."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "What is the frequency range of VHF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 MHz to 300 MHz",
            "b) 30 Hz to 300 Hz",
            "c) 30 KHz to 300 KHz",
            "d) 30 mHz to 300 mHz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Very high frequency (VHF) is the radio frequency range from 30 MHz to 300 MHz.  Frequencies immediately below VHF are denoted high frequency and the next higher frequencies are known as ultra-high frequency."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Which of the following bodies regulates civil aviation in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DGCA",
            "b) EASA",
            "c) FAA",
            "d) CASA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DGCA is the flight regulation authority in India. FAA, EASA and CASA are the flight regulation authorities in the USA, Europe and Australia respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "Radio altimeters are used only up to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2500 feet",
            "b) 3000 feet",
            "c) 250 feet",
            "d) 300 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radio altimeters are capable of determining the flight altitude only up to 2,500 feet above ground level. These devices send data to the auto throttle, which in turn processes by means of flight computers."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of the “big five” instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altimeter",
            "b) Airspeed indicator",
            "c) Head up display",
            "d) Artificial Horizon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, the Airbus A380 is equipped with four engines. It is a wide body, double decker aircraft that is mainly operated on long haul routes."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a part of the tail assembly of an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spoilers",
            "b) Edge flaps",
            "c) Slats",
            "d) Stabilizer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The head up display is not a part of the “big five” instruments. The five instruments in the “big five” are Altimeter, Airspeed indicator, vertical speed indicator, artificial horizon and heading indicator."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Radar systems use which of the following waves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultrasonic",
            "b) Radio",
            "c) Nuclear",
            "d) Electronic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stabilizer are a part of the tail assembly of an aircraft. Spoilers, edge flaps and slats are located on the wing of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "How are the electronic signals transmitted in a FBW system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manually",
            "b) Using radars",
            "c) Using sensors",
            "d) Using wires"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electronic signals are transmitted using wires, in a FBW system. In order to transmit these flight controls, they need to be first converted into electronic signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the world’s largest airliner?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A350",
            "b) Airbus A320",
            "c) Airbus A380",
            "d) Airbus A340"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the conventional flight control systems require pilot’s involvement. However, modern fly by wire systems do not require the pilot’s involvement, and hence reduce workload."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the largest aircraft by weight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 777",
            "b) Antonov An-225 Mriya",
            "c) Airbus A380",
            "d) MD 80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Airbus A380 is the world’s largest airliner. The first A380 prototype was unveiled in Toulouse, France on 18 January 2005, with its first flight on 27 April 2005."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft holds the record for the fastest recorded powered aircraft flight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lockheed SR-71 Blackbird",
            "b) Sukhoi 30",
            "c) Concorde",
            "d) NASA X-43A Pegasus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Antonov An-225 Mriya is the largest aircraft by weight. It is also the largest regular fixed-wing aircraft ever built. The aircraft is equipped with six engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "Engine fuel is usually stored in the wings but some aircraft have additional fuel tanks in the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undercarriage",
            "b) Tail",
            "c) Fuselage",
            "d) Nose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The NASA X-43A Pegasus aircraft holds the record for the fastest recorded powered aircraft flight. The aircraft broke its own world record of Mach 6.3 set in March 2004."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Yaw is a rotation about the ________ axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical",
            "b) Longitudinal",
            "c) Horizontal",
            "d) Diagonal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Engine fuel is usually stored in the wings but some aircraft have additional fuel tanks in the fuselage. Generally, larger aircrafts, like the A380 have these additional fuel tanks."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about fly by wire systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improved safety",
            "b) High maintenance costs",
            "c) Lighter in weight",
            "d) Reliable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yaw is a rotation about the vertical axis. It gives a side-to-side movement of the nose known as sideslip. The yaw axis is one of the three principle axes of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "A rotary wing is typically unstable in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yaw",
            "b) Roll",
            "c) Pitch",
            "d) Bank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the pitch of an aircraft is based on its angle of attack. It gives an up down movement of the aircraft nose measured by the angle of attack."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Control systems are sometimes also used to increase or decrease ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Altitude",
            "b) Airspeed",
            "c) Drag",
            "d) Thrust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fly by wire systems offer low maintenance costs as compared to conventional controls and also improve efficiency by being lighter in weight."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "The tail section is also referred to as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undercarriage",
            "b) Cockpit",
            "c) Rudder",
            "d) Empennage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A rotary wing is typically unstable in yaw. Such wings usually require a vertical stabilizer in order to balance the unstable yaw. In case the yaw is unbalanced, the aircraft may go out of control and crash."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "What is the NATO reporting name for Antonov An-225 Mriya?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cossack",
            "b) Dream lifter",
            "c) Dreamliner",
            "d) Beluga"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The NATO reporting name for Antonov An-225 Mriya is Cossack. NATO reporting names are code names assigned to military equipment from a certain set of nations."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the registration for the single example built of the Antonov An-225?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UA-82060",
            "b) UK-82060",
            "c) UR-82060",
            "d) UU-82060"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: UR-82060 is the registration for the single example built of the Antonov An-225. Only one such aircraft has been produced till date."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Which of the following engine type is used to power the Antonov An-225 Mriya?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turboprop",
            "b) Turbojet",
            "c) Turbofan",
            "d) Turboshaft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Turbofan engines are used to power the Antonov An-225 Mriya. The aircraft uses six engines and is the heaviest aircraft ever built."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "When was the first Antonov An-225 completed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1998",
            "b) 1988",
            "c) 2005",
            "d) 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first Antonov An-225 aircraft was completed in the year 1988 and was produced keeping in mind freight transport. This was the only An-225 aircraft ever produced and was based on the Antonov An-124."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "The An-225 is used for commercial operations by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qatar Airways",
            "b) FedEx",
            "c) UPS",
            "d) Antonov Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Antonov An-225 aircraft is used for commercial operations by Antonov Airlines. The airline is based out of Gostomel Airport in Ukraine. The aircraft is mostly used for chartered freight services."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "The An-225 first flew on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21 December 2008",
            "b) 21 December 1998",
            "c) 21 December 1988",
            "d) 21 December 2018"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, cargo on the upper fuselage of the An-225 can be 70m, approximately 230 feet long. The aircraft can carry ultra-heavy and oversize freight."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "The An-225 landing gear system consists of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 wheels",
            "b) 32 wheels",
            "c) 42 wheels",
            "d) 28 wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. The An-225 comes with a swept-back horizontal stabilizer.  The aircraft also features a twin tail, which was essential to enable the plane to carry large and heavy external loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The An-225’s pressurized cargo hold is ________ in terms of volume.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,300 m3",
            "b) 1,900 m3",
            "c) 1,000 m3",
            "d) 2,000 m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The An-225 first flew on 21 December 1988. It was a 74-minute flight from Kiev. The aircraft also flew during the public days at the Farnborough air show in 1990."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "What is the maximum takeoff weight of the Antonov An-225 Mriya?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 640 tons",
            "b) 740 tons",
            "c) 700 tons",
            "d) 400 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The An-225 landing gear system consists of 32 wheels. The system has a number of steerable wheels which enable the aircraft to turn within a 60-metre-wide runway."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "What is the maximum speed of the An-225?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,000 km/h",
            "b) 800 km/h",
            "c) 700 km/h",
            "d) 850 km/h"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the UR-82060 aircraft is registered in Ukraine. The aircraft is owned by Antonov Airlines, a division of the Antonov aviation company."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "The An-225 has a service ceiling of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10,000 m",
            "b) 15,000 m",
            "c) 11,000 m",
            "d) 9,000 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The An-225’s pressurized cargo hold is 1,300 m3 in terms of volume. The aircraft is heavier in comparison to the double-decker Airbus A380."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "What is the wingspan of the An-225?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 88.4m",
            "b) 80.4m",
            "c) 90.0m",
            "d) 86.9m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Antonov An-225 Mriya has a maximum take-off weight of 640 tons. The take-off weight may also be specified as 710 short tons or 630 long tons."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "What is the maximum landing weight of the An-124?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 330,000 kg",
            "b) 430,000 kg",
            "c) 530,000 kg",
            "d) 130,000 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The An-124 has a maximum landing weight of 330,000 kg, which is approximately 727,525lb. The aircraft has a gross weight of 214,000 kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "The An-124 has a maximum certified altitude of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10,000 m",
            "b) 14,000 m",
            "c) 12,000 m",
            "d) 9,000 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The An-124 has a maximum certified altitude of 12,000 m, which is approximately 39,000 feet. The aircraft has a ferry range of 14,000 km with maximum fuel and minimum payload."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft is based on the An-124?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A380",
            "b) Boeing 747",
            "c) Antonov An-225 Mriya",
            "d) Airbus Beluga"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Antonov An-225 Mriya is based on the An-124. The An-125 is a greatly enlarged design of the An-124 and is the heaviest operating cargo aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "When did the An-124 receive civil certification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 December 1982",
            "b) 30 December 1992",
            "c) 30 December 1979",
            "d) 30 December 1995"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The An-124 received civil certification on 30 December 1992. It was developed as a heavy transport aircraft and features four engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The Antonov An-124 aircraft first took to the skies on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 December 2000",
            "b) 24 December 1909",
            "c) 24 December 1959",
            "d) 24 December 1982"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Antonov An-124 aircraft first took to the skies on 24 December 1982. The aircraft was developed with the motive of transporting heavy materials around the globe."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "The military variant of the Antonov An-124 can accommodate up to _______ of cargo.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200 tons",
            "b) 100 tons",
            "c) 150 tons",
            "d) 300 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the An-124’s rear cargo door can open in flight. The aircraft features a double fuselage and opening of the rear cargo door in flight does not affect its structural integrity."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "The An-124 features __________ wheels.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 24",
            "c) 36",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the An-124 is similar to the American Lockheed C-5 Galaxy. This is because both aircrafts share a similar fuselage and door design."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a proposed variant of the An-124?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An-124-130",
            "b) An-124 Ruslan",
            "c) An-124-100",
            "d) An-124-102"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The military variant of the Antonov An-124 aircraft can accommodate up to 150 tons of cargo. The cargo limit may also be specified as 150 long tons and 170 short tons."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "What is the range of the An-124 with maximum payload?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3,700 km",
            "b) 5,700 km",
            "c) 2,000 km",
            "d) 2,500 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Antonov An-124 aircraft features a total of 24 wheels. The aircraft can easily land on rough terrains as it is equipped with the oleo strut suspension system."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "What is the maximum speed of the An-124?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 650 km/h",
            "b) 600 km/h",
            "c) 1,100 km/h",
            "d) 865 km/h"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Antonov An-124 is equipped with an overhead crane. This onboard crane can lift and winch cargo items weighing up to 30 tons and 120 tons respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "How many passengers can the An-124 carry in a palletized seating arrangement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 800",
            "b) 550",
            "c) 350",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The An-124-130 is a proposed variant of the An-124. An-124 Ruslan is a strategic heavy lift transport aircraft, while the An-124-100 and An-124-102 are both commercial variants."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "What is the wingspan of the An-124?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 73.3m",
            "b) 60.0m",
            "c) 80.50m",
            "d) 86.9m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The An-124 can fly 3,700 km with maximum payload. Further, it can fly 8,400 km with 80,000 kg payload or 11,500 km with 40,000 kg payload."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "What is the seating layout in a one class An-148-100 aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-3",
            "b) 3-3",
            "c) 1-1",
            "d) 2-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The typical seating layout in a one class configuration is 2-3. They can also be configured in a multiple class layout which can carry fewer passengers, typically with four abreast business class."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "The An-148 uses ________ engines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turboprop",
            "b) Turbojet",
            "c) Turbofan",
            "d) Turboprop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The An-148 uses turbofan engines. The aircraft is equipped with two Motor Sich D-436-148 engines, mounted in pods under the wing."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a stretched version of the An-148?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A320",
            "b) Antonov An-225",
            "c) Antonov An-158",
            "d) Airbus A319"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Antonov An-158 aircraft is a stretched version of the An-148, the newer An-158 features a stretched fuselage and can seat a maximum of 100 pax in a single class layout."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "The An-148 can carry up to _________ passengers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120",
            "b) 85",
            "c) 360",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The An-148 can carry up to 85 passengers. The seating capacity ranges between 68 to 85 passengers, depending on the aircraft configuration."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "The An-148 first flew on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17 December 1995",
            "b) 17 December 2000",
            "c) 17 December 2014",
            "d) 17 December 2004"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The An-148 first flew on 17 December 2004. Development of the aircraft started in the 1990s and it was certified on 26 February 2007."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "The An-148-100-E has a maximum takeoff weight of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75.7 tons",
            "b) 10.7 tons",
            "c) 90.7 tons",
            "d) 43.7 tons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the An-148-300 is a business variant. It was previously called An-168 and can seat up to 40 passengers, offering a range of up to 7,000 km."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a cargo variant of the An-148?",
        "Options": [
            "a) An-148-100E",
            "b) An-158",
            "c) An-178",
            "d) An-148-100Bc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The An-148-100-E has a maximum takeoff weight of 43.7 tons. It is an extended range version of the An-148 and offers a range of up to 4,400 km."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "The An-148 has a service ceiling of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35,000 feet",
            "b) 40,000 feet",
            "c) 30,000 feet",
            "d) 37,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The An-178 is a cargo variant of the An-148. The aircraft has a payload capacity of 15 tons and there is an extra pair of main-wheels on each side."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Autopilot system is used to control the __________ of an aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trajectory",
            "b) Thrust",
            "c) Landing gear",
            "d) Air conditioning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Autopilot system is used to control the trajectory of an aircraft. The system eliminates the need of constant hands-on control by a human operator."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "The autopilot is often used in conjunction with the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Empennage",
            "b) Rudder",
            "c) Auto throttle",
            "d) Flaps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The autopilot is often used in conjunction with the auto throttle. Auto throttle is the analogous system that controls the power delivered by the engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "When was the first autopilot developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1950",
            "b) 1912",
            "c) 1900",
            "d) 1945"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first autopilot was developed in 1912, by Sperry Corporation. The system allowed the aircraft to fly straight and level on a compass course without the pilot’s attention."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Autopilots in modern complex aircraft are __________ axis.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Four",
            "d) Three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, smaller and older general aviation aircraft are still hand flown. Further, small airliner may also be flown without an autopilot as they are operated on short-haul flights with two pilots."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CWS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control Wheel Steering",
            "b) Control Wheel Stoppage",
            "c) Crank Wheel Steering",
            "d) Cross Wheel Steering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Autopilots in modern complex aircraft are three axis. Three axis control is essential to control the roll, pitch and yaw of an aircraft. The system maybe further divided into different phases."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Autopilot on airplanes maybe colloquially referred to as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delta",
            "b) North",
            "c) George",
            "d) Vortex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CWS refers to Control Wheel Steering. It is an option that lies midway between fully automated flight and manual flying. It is still used as a function on many aircraft today."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "A single axis autopilot controls an aircraft in the __________ axis only.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch",
            "b) Roll",
            "c) Yaw",
            "d) Bank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Autopilot on airplanes maybe colloquially referred to as George. The system allows us to focus on broader aspects of operations, thereby reducing their workload."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "An autopilot controlled landing on a runway is known as a __________ landing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CATII",
            "b) CATI",
            "c) CATIA",
            "d) CATIIIB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, a two axis autopilot control system is able to control the aircraft in the pitch and the roll axis. The system receives inputs from radio navigation systems present onboard the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used on the Boeing 777?",
        "Options": [
            "a) General Electric AFDS-770 Autopilot Flight Director System",
            "b) Rockwell Collins AFDS-770 Autopilot Flight Director System",
            "c) Rolls Royce AFDS-770 Autopilot Flight Director System",
            "d) BAE Systems AFDS-770 Autopilot Flight Director System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Rockwell Collins AFDS-770 Autopilot Flight Director System is used on the Boeing 777 aircraft. The flight directing system is highly advanced equipment which features high end microprocessors."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Autopilot is mostly an integral component of a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel Quantity Indication Computer",
            "b) Traffic Collision Avoidance System",
            "c) Flight Management System",
            "d) Spoiler and Elevator Computer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Autopilot is mostly an integral component of a Flight Management System. Autopilot systems exist which automate all of the flight phases, except taxi and take-off."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "In CWS mode, pilot controls the autopilot through inputs on the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yoke",
            "b) HUD",
            "c) HMD",
            "d) PFD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When an aircraft is operating in CWS mode, the pilot handles the autopilot by feeding inputs using the yoke. Further, these inputs are then processed and in turn converted to corresponding heading and attitude values."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "What is the full form of SAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stall alignment system",
            "b) Stability alignment system",
            "c) Stall augmentation system",
            "d) Stability augmentation system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the MD-11 which uses a constant CWS in roll. It is an aircraft that employs a form of CWS even in manual mode. Further, a modern Airbus aircraft using FBW under Normal Law is always in CWS mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most common type of SAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roll damper",
            "b) Yaw damper",
            "c) Pitch damper",
            "d) Banking damper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The term SAS in aviation terminology refers to the stability augmentation system. Such systems work to dampen aircraft buffeting without being affected by the aircrafts current attitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Which of the following category permits pilots to land with a decision height of 200 feet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CAT IIIa",
            "b) CAT II",
            "c) CAT I",
            "d) CAT IIIc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The yaw damper is the most common type of SAS. The system is used to eliminate the Dutch roll tendency of swept wing aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Which of the following category may also be referred to as “zero-zero”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CAT IIIa",
            "b) CAT II",
            "c) CAT IIIb",
            "d) CAT IIIc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The CAT I category permits pilots to land with a decision height of 200 feet.  In this category, autopilots are not required."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "The fail-operational autopilot is a __________ channel system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triple",
            "b) Four",
            "c) Double",
            "d) Single"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CAT IIIb category may also be referred to as “zero-zero”. It is not yet available on commercial airliners, however may be available in the near future."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "The cabin pressure is regulated by the ___________ valve.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Outflow",
            "b) Inflow",
            "c) Downward",
            "d) Upward"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cabin pressure is regulated by the outflow valve. It is a process in which conditioned air is pumped into the cabin of an aircraft to create a safe environment for people on board."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "The air used for pressurization is usually bled off from the engines, at the __________ stage.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cryogenic",
            "b) Compressor",
            "c) Thermal",
            "d) Hydraulic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The air used for pressurization is usually bled off from the engines, at the compressor stage. The air is cooled, humidified, and processed with recirculated air if required, before being distributed to the cabin."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "What is the ambient air pressure at 40,000 feet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 bar",
            "b) 0.2 bar",
            "c) 20 bar",
            "d) 0.02 bar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ambient air pressure at 40,000 feet usually falls to 0.2 bar. At this level, oxygen masks are required to maintain a minimum partial pressure of oxygen of 0.2 bar."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "The pressure inside the cabin is technically referred to as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cabin bar",
            "b) Cabin pressure",
            "c) Cabin altitude",
            "d) Cabin level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pressure inside the cabin is technically referred to as cabin altitude, it may also be referred to as equivalent effective cabin altitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "For private aircraft operating in the US, the crew is required to use oxygen masks if the cabin altitude stays above __________ for more than 30 minutes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12,000 feet",
            "b) 50,000 feet",
            "c) 25,000 feet",
            "d) 20,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the cabin altitude of zero would indicate the pressure found at mean sea level. This pressure is taken to be 101.325 kilopascals or 14.696 psi."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the body’s most common response to hypoxia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hyperventilation",
            "b) Hypoxia",
            "c) Barotrauma",
            "d) Sinus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For private aircraft operating in the US, the crew is required to use oxygen masks if the cabin altitude stays above 12,000 feet for more than 30 minutes."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "In aircrafts, the cabin altitude during flight is kept above sea level so as to reduce stress on the pressurized part of the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engines",
            "b) Wings",
            "c) Fuselage",
            "d) Tail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hyperventilation is the body’s most common response to hypoxia. It helps in partially restoring the partial pressure of oxygen in the blood. However, it also causes CO2 to out gas."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "What is the typical cabin altitude of the Boeing 767 when cruising at 37,000 feet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7,000 feet",
            "b) 10,000 feet",
            "c) 15,000 feet",
            "d) 18,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In aircrafts, the cabin altitude during flight is kept above sea level so as to reduce stress on the pressurized part of the fuselage. The stress is directly proportional to the difference in pressure inside and outside the aircraft cabin."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "The cabin altitude rises gradually from the altitude of the airport of origin to a regulatory maximum of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15,000 feet",
            "b) 20,000 feet",
            "c) 40,000 feet",
            "d) 8,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The typical cabin altitude of the Boeing 767 when cruising at 37,000 feet is 7,000 feet, which is approximately 2,100m. This altitude is typical for older jet airliners."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Which of the following can provide a sea-level cabin altitude when cruising at 41,000 feet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bombardier Global Express",
            "b) Emivest SJ30",
            "c) Boeing 767",
            "d) Airbus A340"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the compulsory maximum cabin altitude does not eliminate all physiological problems. Passengers suffering from cold or other infections may still experience pain in the ears and sinuses."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "The new FAA amendment impose an operational ceiling of ___________ on the majority of newly designed commercial aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40,000 feet",
            "b) 50,000 feet",
            "c) 45,000 feet",
            "d) 35,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The new FAA amendment impose an operational ceiling of 40,000 feet on the majority of newly designed commercial aircraft. However, aircraft manufacturers can apply for a relaxation of this rule, if required."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ECS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Empennage control system",
            "b) Environmental cooling system",
            "c) Environmental control system",
            "d) Empennage cooling system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ECS refers to Environmental control system. It controls the pressurization of compressed air into the aircraft cabin."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "At 39,000 feet altitude, the cabin pressure of an aircraft would be automatically maintained at _________ feet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15,000",
            "b) 10,300",
            "c) 2,000",
            "d) 6,900"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, at least two engines provide compressed bleed air for the aircrafts pneumatic systems. This is required in order to provide full redundancy."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "In case of failure of cabin pressurization at altitudes above 10,000 feet, the aircraft requires an emergency descent to ________ feet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8,000",
            "b) 1,000",
            "c) 2,000",
            "d) 6,000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cabin pressure is automatically maintained near about 6,900 feet when the aircraft is flying at 39,000 feet. The pressure may also be specified as 79 kPa of atmosphere pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "What is the full form of MSA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum Safe Attitude",
            "b) Minimum Stable Altitude",
            "c) Minimum Safe Altitude",
            "d) Minimum Stable Attitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In case of failure of cabin pressurization at altitudes above 10,000 feet, the aircraft makes an emergency descent to 8,000 feet. If the aircraft does not descent to the required altitude in minimal time, it can cause a fatal situation for all passengers onboard."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first pressurized airliner in wide service?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MD-80",
            "b) Lockheed Constellation",
            "c) AN-124",
            "d) Avro Tudor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MSA refers to Minimum Safe Altitude. The aircraft is required to descend to the MSA, in case an unplanned decompression takes place."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "The Concorde maintained a cabin altitude of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6,000 feet",
            "b) 60,000 feet",
            "c) 2,000 feet",
            "d) 20,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Lockheed Constellation was the first pressurized airliner in wide service. It was a four engine airliner built between 1943 and 1958."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "The spacecraft Mercury used a cabin altitude of _________ feet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35,800",
            "b) 4,800",
            "c) 24,800",
            "d) 10,800"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Concorde maintained a cabin altitude of 6,000 feet. The aircraft had to deal with particularly high pressure differentials as it flew at unusually high altitude of 60,000 feet."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "The selection and control of high or low bleed sources are governed by the needs of different _________ systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical",
            "b) Hydraulic",
            "c) Thermal",
            "d) Pneumatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the Boeing 307 Stratoliner was the first airliner with a pressurized cabin. The aircraft was built in 1938 and only 10 units were produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "What is the full form of LNG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquefied Natural gas",
            "b) Light Natural Gas",
            "c) Low Natural Gas",
            "d) Lightning Natural Gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LPG refers to liquefied natural gas. It is one of the fuel feedstocks that aircraft could switch to, other than conventional fossil oil. For example, turbofans can be operated on a number of different fuels."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most important criterion in selecting an appropriate fuel to power an aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost",
            "b) Density",
            "c) Specific energy",
            "d) Efficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In order to select the appropriate fuel that could be used to power an aircraft, specific energy levels are studied extensively and are the most important criterion for selection. Other selection criteria’s include cost, density and efficiency of the fuel."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Aviation fuel is also called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engine fuel",
            "b) Jet fuel",
            "c) Gasoline",
            "d) Air fuel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term jet fuel may be used to refer aviation fuel. Such fuels are used for more critical applications and offer better quality and performance as compared to fuels used for road transport."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Which of the following tanks are used by combat aircraft, which need to discard them after use for performance reasons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tip tank",
            "b) Internal tank",
            "c) Drop tank",
            "d) Attack tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Drop tanks are used by combat aircraft, which need to discard them after use for performance reasons. These tanks are used to extend the range of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "In larger aircraft, fuel tanks are also present in the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tail",
            "b) Fuselage",
            "c) Nose",
            "d) Rudder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In larger aircraft, fuel tanks are also present in the fuselage. The fuel load affects the center of gravity of the aircraft and thus restricts the amount of fuel carried."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Few single-engine aircraft use __________ probes in the fuel tanks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Capacitive",
            "b) Inductive",
            "c) Resistive",
            "d) Radiative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Few single-engine aircraft use capacitive probes in the fuel tanks. As the fuel is burned, more air enters the fuel tank, in turn capacitance increases, and the remaining fuel is calculated and displayed to the pilots."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Aviation gasoline is also referred to as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Petrol",
            "b) Diesel",
            "c) Avgas",
            "d) Kerosene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the Tupolev Tu-155 was designed to run on LNG. However, low specific energy of natural gas even in liquid form as compared to conventional fuels acts as a big disadvantage for flight applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Jet-A fuel ignites at temperatures at or above _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 49 °C",
            "b) 100 °C",
            "c) 31 °C",
            "d) 75 °C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aviation gasoline is also referred to as avgas. It is used in spark ignited internal combustion engines in aircraft. It has a higher octane rating than motor gasoline."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Which of the following is referred to as the fuel selector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel control valve",
            "b) Fuel pump",
            "c) Fuel hose",
            "d) Fuel tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Jet-A fuel is a mixture of pure kerosene and ignites at temperatures at or above 49 °C. This category of fuel is generally used in modern commercial airliners."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "What is the density of BP Avgas 80 at 15 °C?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6,900 kg/m3",
            "b) 69 kg/m3",
            "c) 690 kg/m3",
            "d) 60,900 kg/m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, kerosene based fuel has a higher flash point as compared to gasoline-based fuel. Thus, it requires significantly higher temperatures to ignite and it fails the purity and quality tests for use on jet aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "For performance calculations, airliner manufacturers use a density of jet fuel around _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 kg/l",
            "b) 0.2 kg/l",
            "c) 8 kg/l",
            "d) 0.8 kg/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fuel control valve is referred to as the fuel selector. The valve serves several functions. One such function is to act as a fuel shut-off valve."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "In case of pressure refueling, fuel is pumped in at _________ kilopascals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 275",
            "b) 1,000",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The density of BP Avgas 80 at 15 °C is 690 kg/m3. The fuel has a net energy content of 44.65 MJ/kg. The net energy content for different aviation fuels depends on their composition."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Jet fuel is dispensed from a nozzle having a rectangular opening larger than __________ mm diagonally.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 89",
            "b) 100",
            "c) 60",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Jet fuel is dispensed from a nozzle having a rectangular opening larger 60 mm diagonally. This is done so that it does not fit into avgas ports. The nozzle called a J spout or duckbill."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "What is the flash point of Jet-A?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18 °C",
            "b) 10 °C",
            "c) 58 °C",
            "d) 38 °C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Jet-A has a flash point of 38 °C. The fuel has been used in the United States since the 1950s but is usually not available outside the United States."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Which of the following is military jet fuel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jet B",
            "b) Jet A",
            "c) JP-1",
            "d) Jet A-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: JP-1 is military jet fuel. Military organizations all around the world use a different classification system of JP numbers. Some of these military fuels are almost identical to their civilian counterparts."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Jet A-1 is similar to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) JP-1",
            "b) JP-5",
            "c) JP-8",
            "d) JP-4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Jet A-1 is similar to JP-8. The JP-8 is a kerosene based fuel that is projected to remain in use at least until 2025. Similarly, Jet B is similar to JP-4."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Jet fuel contains sulfur up to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,000 ppm",
            "b) 10,000 ppm",
            "c) 200 ppm",
            "d) 20,000 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the JP-7 fuel was developed for the SR-71 Blackbird. The fuel features a high flash point to better cope with the heat and stress of high speed supersonic flight."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first airline to operate a commercial flight on a 50:50 blend of synthetic Gas to Liquid jet fuel and conventional jet fuel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air New Zealand",
            "b) Delta Air Lines",
            "c) Air India",
            "d) Qatar Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jet fuel contains sulfur up to 1,000 ppm. This makes the fuel more lubricative and thus it does not currently require a lubricity additive as all pipeline diesel fuels require."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Jet B fuel is roughly _________ kerosene by volume.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30%",
            "b) 90%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 45%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Qatar Airways was the first airline to operate a commercial flight on a 50:50 blend of synthetic Gas to Liquid jet fuel and conventional jet fuel. It was a six hour flight from London to Doha."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "What is the NATO code for JP-5?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F-50",
            "b) F-44",
            "c) J-44",
            "d) J-50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Jet B fuel is roughly 30% kerosene by volume. The remaining 70% is gasoline. The fuel offers an extremely low freezing point of −60 °C and also exhibits a low flash point."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an internal tank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bladder tank",
            "b) Integral tank",
            "c) Conformal fuel tank",
            "d) Tip tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, around 30% of the worldwide consumption of jet fuel is in the United States. The worldwide consumption of jet fuel more than tripled in 30 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an internal tank?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bladder tank",
            "b) Integral tank",
            "c) Conformal fuel tank",
            "d) Tip tank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: F-44 is the NATO code for JP-5. The JP-5 is also known as NCI-C54784. It is a yellow colored, kerosene based jet fuel developed for use in aircrafts stationed aboard aircraft carriers."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "External tanks are common on modern __________ aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relief",
            "b) Business",
            "c) Commercial",
            "d) Military"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conformal fuel tanks are not an internal tank. However, bladder tank, integral tank and tip tank are all internal tanks. The conformal fuel tanks extend either the range or endurance of the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "Integral fuel tanks are also called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wet wings",
            "b) Essential fuel tanks",
            "c) Dynamic wings",
            "d) Stationary wings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Conformal fuel tanks are not an internal tank. However, bladder tank, integral tank and tip tank are all internal tanks. The conformal fuel tanks extend either the range or endurance of the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "What is the full form of WSR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wright surveillance radar",
            "b) Wing surveillance radar",
            "c) Weight surveillance radar",
            "d) Weather surveillance radar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: WSR refers to weather surveillance radar. It is also called a weather radar and is a radar that is used to locate precipitation and calculate its motion."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "Which of the following waves are used by radar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultrasonic",
            "b) Radio",
            "c) Nuclear",
            "d) Electronic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Radar systems make use of radio waves. These are systems used to determine parameters such as the range, angle or velocity of different objects."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "Modern weather radars being used in aircrafts are usually __________ Doppler radars.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Pulse",
            "d) Sound"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Modern weather radars being used in aircrafts are usually pulse based Doppler radars. These radars provide enhanced features such as detection of rain droplets in addition to the existing features."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Weather radars used in aircrafts emit directional pulses of ___________ radiation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultrasonic",
            "b) Microwave",
            "c) Supersonic",
            "d) Nuclear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The weather radars used in aircrafts emit directional pulses of microwave radiation. The aircraft uses an onboard cavity magnetron in order to send these waves to the intended target."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "In Canada, the 5 cm weather radar systems use angles ranging from 0.3 to _________ degrees.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 2.25",
            "d) 250"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, radar pulses are the order of a microsecond long. Further, the wavelengths of 1 to 10 cm are approximately about ten times the diameter of the droplets or ice particles of interest."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Which of the following radar system is used only for short-range units?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X-band",
            "b) C-band",
            "c) Ka-band",
            "d) S-band"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Canada, the 5 cm weather radar systems use angles ranging from 0.3 to 25 degrees. The scanning process is usually completed within 5 to 10 minutes to have data within a range of 15 km above the ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "The duration of the listen cycle is on the order of a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Second",
            "b) Nanosecond",
            "c) Millisecond",
            "d) Microsecond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 3cm X-band radar system is used only for short-range units. Typical applications include radar, satellite communication, and wireless computer networks."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "The cavity magnetron was developed in _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Australia",
            "b) Germany",
            "c) United Kingdom",
            "d) The United States"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The duration of the listen cycle is on the order of a millisecond. This duration is about thousand times longer than the pulse duration."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "On a radar display, magenta indicates _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Light precipitation",
            "b) Moderate precipitation",
            "c) Heavy precipitation",
            "d) Extremely heavy precipitation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cavity magnetron used in radar systems was developed in United Kingdom. The magnetron allowed the creation of comparatively smaller systems with sub-meter resolution."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Which of the following refers to a green radar return?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Level 1",
            "b) Level 2",
            "c) Level 3",
            "d) Level 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In aviation world, Level 1 indication refers to a green radar return. This level indicates chances of reduced visibility caused due to small amount of precipitation along with some minor turbulence."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "Which of the following levels may cause structural damage to the aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Level 1",
            "b) Level 3",
            "c) Level 2",
            "d) Level 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Level 3 may cause structural damage to the aircraft. This level indicates heavy precipitation which in turn may lead to the possibility of thunderstorms and severe turbulence."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "The NEXRAD is a __________ cm radar.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 100",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The NEXRAD is a 10 radar. For a wavelength of 5 cm, an unambiguous velocity range of 12.5 to 18.75 meter/second is produced, whereas in NEXRAD the unambiguous velocity range would get doubled."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "What is the full form of PRF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse repetition frequency",
            "b) Pitch repetition frequency",
            "c) Pulse roll frequency",
            "d) Pitch roll frequency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, in a uniform rainstorm moving eastwards, a radar beam that is pointing west will see the raindrops moving towards itself. However, a beam pointing east will see the raindrops moving away."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the only layout of radar return on a two dimensional image?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulse Position Indicator",
            "b) Pitch Position Indicator",
            "c) Plan Position Indicator",
            "d) Pitch Position Indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PRF refers to Pulse repetition frequency. In some systems, two alternating pulse repetition frequencies are used which allow a greater Doppler range."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "The constant altitude plan position indicator (CAPPI) has been developed by __________ researchers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) American",
            "b) British",
            "c) Indian",
            "d) Canadian"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Plan Position Indicator is the only layout of radar return on a two dimensional image. Also, the data coming from different distances to the radar are at different heights above the ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "The reflectivity of a radar beam depends on the diameter of the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Target",
            "b) Source",
            "c) Sun",
            "d) Earth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The constant altitude plan position indicator (CAPPI) has been developed by Canadian researchers. It is a radar display that provides a horizontal cross section of data at a constant altitude."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the primary specification for weather radar systems, using an airborne pulse Doppler radar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARINC 661",
            "b) ARINC 502",
            "c) ARINC 905",
            "d) ARINC 708"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the VAD Wind Profile system is to display the estimates of speed and direction of the horizontal winds. These estimates are displayed on a screen and the system may also be referred to as VWP."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ETA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Estimated Time of Arrival",
            "b) Eastern Time of Arrival",
            "c) Earliest Time of Arrival",
            "d) End Time of Arrival"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reflectivity of a radar beam depends on the diameter of the target. For example, snowflakes are large but weakly reflective, while on the other hand rain drops are small but highly reflective."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "In typical aircraft configuration, separate vertical and horizontal stabilizers combine to form an ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudder",
            "b) Elevator",
            "c) Empennage",
            "d) Trim"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In typical aircraft assembly and configuration methods, the empennage is formed by combining separate vertical and horizontal stabilizers. The combined system is installed at the rear end of an aircraft on its tail assembly."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "The aircraft stabilizer is an _________ surface.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aerodynamic",
            "b) Thermal",
            "c) Hydraulic",
            "d) Mechanical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most stabilizers used in aircrafts typically involve a number of control surfaces, which can be moved by the pilot. These are aerodynamic surfaces that are an essential component of flight."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "The stabilator is a useful device for changing the aircraft balance within ___________ limits.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrow",
            "b) Wide",
            "c) Diagonal",
            "d) Longitudinal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, stabilators with roll control function are called tailerons, or rolling tails. Roll control is usually a function of ailerons that are placed on the wings of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "A stabilator is a fully ___________ aircraft stabilizer.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Movable",
            "b) Hinged",
            "c) Fixed",
            "d) Stationary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The stabilator is a useful device for changing the aircraft balance within the wide limits. It is also useful for mastering the stick forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "Which of the following wind is across the line of flight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ground wind",
            "b) Headwind",
            "c) Tailwind",
            "d) Crosswind"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A stabilator is a fully movable aircraft stabilizer. The stabilator serves the usual functions of longitudinal stability, control and other stick force requirements."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "The stabilators were developed to achieve adequate __________ control on a supersonic flight.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch",
            "b) Yaw",
            "c) Roll",
            "d) Bank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crosswinds are the winds across the line of flight. Such winds cause the windward side of an aircraft to generate a greater amount of lift and drag."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "A stabilator may also be referred to as an all moving ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flaps",
            "b) Wing",
            "c) Tail",
            "d) Rudder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Supersonic flights required certain necessary upgrades in the aircraft structure so as to counter balance the effects of supersonic travel. Thus, stabilators were introduced on such aircrafts in order to obtain sufficient pitch control."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to maintain the aircraft in a longitudinal balance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical stabilizer",
            "b) Horizontal stabilizer",
            "c) Longitudinal stabilizer",
            "d) Diagonal stabilizer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A stabilator may also be referred to as an all moving. Alternatively, it may also be called an all flying tail. It is fitted in the tail section of an aircraft at its rear end."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft lack a separate horizontal stabilizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three surface aircraft",
            "b) Conventional aircraft",
            "c) Canard aircraft",
            "d) Tailless aircraft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tailless aircraft lack a separate horizontal stabilizer. In such aircrafts, the horizontal stabilizing surface is part of the main wing."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "Which of the following may be used to relieve pilot input forces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trim tabs",
            "b) Horizontal stabilizer",
            "c) Stabilator",
            "d) Rudder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The trim tabs may be used to relieve pilot input forces. Further, in some small aircraft having all-moving stabilizers, anti-servo tabs maybe used to increase these forces."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Stability of an aircraft can be defined only when it is in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pitch",
            "b) Yaw",
            "c) Trim",
            "d) Roll"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stability of an aircraft can be defined only when it is in trim position. Trim position can be controlled by the pilot and is an important flight control parameter."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Longitudinal stability in a tailless aircraft is achieved by designing the aircraft such that its aerodynamic center is behind the center of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass",
            "b) Gravity",
            "c) Weight",
            "d) Earth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The longitudinal stability in a tailless aircraft is achieved by designing the aircraft such that its aerodynamic center is behind the center of gravity. It is generally done by modifying the wing design of an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "Which of the following provides directional stability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical stabilizer",
            "b) Horizontal stabilizer",
            "c) APU",
            "d) Rudder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, the stabilator is controlled by the control yoke, or stick. On the contrary, an adjustable stabilizer is controlled by the trim system."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "In a V-tail configuration, the two stabilizers are positioned at ___________ to each other.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 – 120°",
            "b) 90 – 150°",
            "c) 60 – 120°",
            "d) 90 – 120°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Directional stability to an aircraft is provided by the vertical stabilizers fitted on the airframe on aircraft. These stabilizers are essential to keep an aircraft on its intended flight path."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft has a tailless configuration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Concorde",
            "b) Airbus 380",
            "c) Boeing 747",
            "d) Airbus A320"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a V-tail aircraft tail configuration, two stabilizers are positioned at 90 – 120° to each other. Different arrangements can be used on aircrafts depending upon the intended use of the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Landing gear systems are the _________ of an aircraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Left carriage",
            "b) Over carriage",
            "c) Undercarriage",
            "d) Right carriage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Landing gear systems are retractable systems which form the undercarriage of an aircraft. These systems are primarily used while landing, takeoff and taxi and its failure during these phases may prove fatal."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Landing gear was previously referred to as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alighting gear",
            "b) Resting gear",
            "c) Moving gear",
            "d) Rolling gear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Landing gear was previously referred to as alighting gear. This was during the early years of powered flight and post the Second World War these gears have been called landing gears. "
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "What is the full form of VTOL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Virtual take-off and landing",
            "b) Vertical take-off and landing",
            "c) Viscous take-off and landing",
            "d) Vernier take-off and landing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: False, the landing gear supports the aircraft when it is not flying. It allows the aircraft to take off, land, and taxi without any damage."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Landing gears fold away during the flight to reduce ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drag",
            "b) Thrust",
            "c) Airspeed",
            "d) Altitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: VTOL in typical aircraft terminology refers to vertical take-off and landing. This technique is currently being developed and can be seen as a modern approach to flying. It does not require long runways to take off and land."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "The landing gears have a ___________ hours’ time between overhaul.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50,000",
            "b) 5,000",
            "c) 2,000",
            "d) 20,000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Landing gears fold away during flight to reduce drag. Faster aircrafts usually have such retractable undercarriages that can be easily retracted via FBW systems. "
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Which of the following had a retractable tail bumper wheel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Concorde",
            "b) Airbus A340",
            "c) MD 80",
            "d) Boeing 767"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The landing gears have a 20,000 hours’ time between overhaul. Further, they have a lifetime of 60,000 hours or 20 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the compartment where the wheels are stowed in a retractable landing gear system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wheel dumper",
            "b) Wheel store",
            "c) Wheel wells",
            "d) Wheel safe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Concorde had a retractable tail bumper wheel. This is because delta winged aircraft such as the Concorde needed a high angle when taking off."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "Most retraction systems are _________ operated.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermally",
            "b) Hydraulically",
            "c) Mechanically",
            "d) Electronically"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wheels of an aircraft are stowed in a compartment known as the wheel well. The wheels are stowed up using the retractable landing gear system that is fitted onboard an aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "The Boeing 747 aircraft has ___________ different sets of wheels.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Boeing 747 aircraft, also known as the “queen of the skies” has 5 different sets of wheels. The landing gear features four sets each having four wheel bogies along with one nose wheel set."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "The Airbus A380 two sets of six-wheel bogies under the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engine",
            "b) Tail",
            "c) Wings",
            "d) Fuselage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Airbus A380 two sets of six-wheel bogies under the fuselage. Further the aircraft has a four wheel bogie under each wing. The aircraft has 2 flight decks."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Modern gliders are generally equipped with a single wheel in order to minimize ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drag",
            "b) Thrust",
            "c) Crosswind",
            "d) Airspeed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Modern gliders are generally equipped with a single wheel in order to minimize the drag on the glider surface. The wheel used on such gliders could be either fixed or retractable."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Which of the following controls the steering of an aircraft while it is on the ground?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rudder",
            "b) Trim Tab",
            "c) Tiller",
            "d) Empennage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tiller controls the steering of an aircraft while it is on the ground. It may be designed so as to work in combination with other controls such as the rudder or yoke."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a basis for the selection of main wheel tires?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static landing case",
            "b) Short landing case",
            "c) Short loading case",
            "d) Static loading case"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: True, for steering an aircraft on the ground by exclusively using the rudder, requires a substantial amount of airflow to be moving past the rudder. This can either be generated by the forward motion of an aircraft or by the thrust provided by engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Which of the following decreases the nose gear load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Forward thrust",
            "b) Reverse thrust",
            "c) Headwinds",
            "d) Tailwinds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In order to select wheels to be used on the main wheel tires, the static loading case is a primary criterion. The said criteria evaluates the amount of load applied on the main gear while the aircraft is taxing at low speeds."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to fill tires of commercial aircraft, in order to prevent internal combustion of the tire?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen",
            "b) Carbon-di-oxide",
            "c) Carbon monoxide",
            "d) Helium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reverse thrust decreases the nose gear load. The choice of nose wheel tires is based upon the nose wheel load braking at maximum effort."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a distinguishing feature for cargo aircrafts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wide Fuselage",
            "b) Number of engines",
            "c) High wings",
            "d) Large number of wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, a cargo aircraft does not carry passengers. On the contrary, it is designed or converted for the carriage of cargo only."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "What is the range of Boeing 777F?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3,000 nautical miles",
            "b) 5,500 nautical miles",
            "c) 4,900 nautical miles",
            "d) 7,000 nautical miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of engines is not a distinguishing feature for cargo aircrafts. An aircraft can have engines depending on its load and range, and it is irrespective of its operational use purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first purpose built cargo aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arado Ar 232",
            "b) MD 80",
            "c) Handley Page HP.42",
            "d) Boeing 747-8F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boeing 777F aircraft has a range of 4,900 nautical miles, which is approximately 9,070 km. It is a commercial aircraft with cruise speed of 896 km/h."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Which of the following aircraft can be ordered in a freighter version with a large nose door?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 747",
            "b) Airbus A320",
            "c) Boeing 737",
            "d) Airbus A340"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Arado Ar 232 was the first purpose built cargo aircraft. The aircraft was intended to supplement the earlier Junkers Ju 52 freighter conversions, however only a few were built."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Which of the following will be the launch customer of the Cessna 408 SkyCourier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qatar Airways",
            "b) Emirates",
            "c) UPS",
            "d) FedEx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Boeing 747 can be ordered in a freighter version with a large nose door. This door can be raised above the cockpit for loading and allows access to an unobstructed main deck."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a military cargo aircraft?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Airbus A330 MRTT",
            "b) Boeing 747 Freighter",
            "c) Boeing 767",
            "d) Douglas DC-3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: FedEx will be the launch customer of the Cessna 408 SkyCourier. The aircraft is scheduled to enter service in 2020 and is being developed to carry up to three LD3 cargo containers."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "What is the volume of an Airbus A400M?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 270 m3",
            "b) 2,700 m3",
            "c) 85 m3",
            "d) 850 m3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, airbus originally accepted orders for the freighter version A380F. However, the freighter versions were not produced and the aircraft is only being used for passenger transport."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "The modern FMS was introduced on the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing 787",
            "b) Boeing 767",
            "c) Boeing 737",
            "d) Boeing 747"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The modern FMS was introduced on the Boeing 767 aircraft. However, earlier navigation computers did exist. There are certain characteristics are common to all FMS."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "The FMS is a vital component of an aircraft’s __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronics",
            "b) Electricals",
            "c) Hydraulics",
            "d) Avionics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The flight management system, also referred to as FMS is a vital component of an aircraft’s avionics. It is used on most modern aircrafts to automate a large number of tasks, thereby reducing the crew workload."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CDU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control Display Unit",
            "b) Combined Display Unit",
            "c) Checkered Display Unit",
            "d) Cost Display Unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CDU refers to the Control Display Unit. The unit incorporates a small screen and keyboard or touchscreen and is used to control the FMS."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "Which of the following standard defines the navigation database?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARINC 900",
            "b) ARINC 800",
            "c) ARINC 724",
            "d) ARINC 424"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ARINC 424 standard is used to define the navigation database. All flight management system contain a navigation database."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "The aircraft navigation database is generally updated every _________ weeks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aircraft navigation database is generally updated every 4 weeks. Updating this database at regular intervals is important so as to ensure that its contents are current."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "What is the full form of IAP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incident approach procedure",
            "b) Inclined approach procedure",
            "c) Instrument approach procedure",
            "d) Inert approach procedure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, simple FMS uses a single sensor, mostly GPS to determine position. However, modern FMS uses a number of sensors, such as VORs, in order to determine the exact position."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "The flight plan generally appears as a __________ line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magenta",
            "b) Green",
            "c) Yellow",
            "d) White"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term IAP in common aviation terminology refers to Instrument approach procedure. This procedure is based on instrument flight conditions and makes use of a number of predetermined manoeuvres."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as the primary sensor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DME",
            "b) GPS Receiver",
            "c) VOR",
            "d) IRS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flight plan generally appears as a magenta line. It displays other airports, radio aids and waypoints as well. The FMS also sends the flight plan information for display on the ND of EFIS."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "VNAV provides __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roll",
            "b) Pitch",
            "c) Yaw",
            "d) Bank"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The GPS Receivers act as the primary sensor. This is because they possess the highest accuracy and integrity. Radio aids such as DME and VOR act as the second highest quality sensors."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "In pre-flight phases, the FMS builds the ________ profile.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical",
            "b) Horizontal",
            "c) Diagonal",
            "d) Lateral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the LNAV is used to provide roll steering command to the autopilot. The FMS mode is normally called as LNAV for the lateral flight plan. It may also be referred to as Lateral navigation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "A cost index of _________ gives maximum efficiency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 999",
            "b) 0",
            "c) 99",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: VNAV provides pitch, along with speed and altitude targets. VNAV or vertical navigation is the FMS mode for the vertical flight plan."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Boeing KC-46 Pegasus is scheduled to replace the older _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boeing KC-135 Stratotankers",
            "b) Boeing 747",
            "c) Airbus A400M",
            "d) Boeing C-7000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Boeing KC-46 Pegasus is scheduled to replace the older Boeing KC-135 Stratotankers. The USAF intends to procure 179 Pegasus aircraft by 2027."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "When is the Boeing KC-46 Pegasus scheduled to enter service?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2025",
            "b) 2030",
            "c) 2019",
            "d) 2022"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boeing KC-46 Pegasus is scheduled to enter service in 2019.  The aircraft is manufactured by Boeing Defense, Space and Security."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "The Pegasus has a __________ flight control system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical",
            "b) Electrical",
            "c) Electronic",
            "d) Hydraulic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Pegasus has a hydraulic flight control system. It is a wide body, low wing cantilever monoplane that features a conventional tail unit. The aircraft has a retractable tricycle landing gear."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines are used to power the Pegasus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolls Royce Trent 700",
            "b) Pratt & Whitney PW4062",
            "c) Rolls Royce Trent 800",
            "d) Pratt & Whitney F135"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Boeing KC-46 Pegasus is powered by two Pratt & Whitney PW4062 engines. One engine is mounted under each wing. It is a high bypass turbofan aircraft engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "The rear compartment of the Pegasus can be used in an aero-medical configuration for __________ patients.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 125",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 54"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rear compartment of the Pegasus can be used in an aero-medical configuration for 54 patients. Further, the aircraft flight deck has room for four crew members."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "When did the 767-2C first fly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28 December 2008",
            "b) 28 December 2018",
            "c) 28 December 2014",
            "d) 28 December 2016"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the aircraft has a Centerline Drogue System under the rear fuselage. Further, a fly-by-wire refueling boom is also present at the rear of the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "The Boeing KC-46 Pegasus was developed from the Boeing __________ jet airliner.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 787",
            "b) 767",
            "c) 737",
            "d) 707"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the NewGen Tanker is based on the 767-200 and features an improved version of the KC-10 refueling boom. It also features cockpit displays from the 787."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "When did the USAF take delivery of the first KC-46?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 January 2019",
            "b) 10 January 2017",
            "c) 10 January 2013",
            "d) 10 January 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The USAF took delivery of the first KC-46 on 10 January 2019. The aircraft was originally scheduled to be delivered in 2016, however got delayed due to various reasons."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "What is the maximum speed of the KC-46?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.86",
            "b) Mach 0.086",
            "c) Mach 8.6",
            "d) Mach 86"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum speed of the KC-46 was Mach 0.86, which is approximately 914 km/h. Cruise speed for the aircraft is Mach 0.80, which is approximately 851 km/h."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "The KC-46 has a service ceiling of ________ feet.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 37,000",
            "b) 32,500",
            "c) 45,000",
            "d) 40,100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The KC-46 has a service ceiling of 40,100 feet, which is approximately 12,200m. The aircraft requires 2 pilots and 1 boom operator."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operator of the KC-46?",
        "Options": [
            "a) United States",
            "b) Israel",
            "c) Australia",
            "d) Japan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Australia is not an operator of the KC-46. However, United States, Israel and Japan are all operators of the KC-46 aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "What is the wingspan of the KC-46?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 157 feet 8 inches",
            "b) 107 feet 3 inches",
            "c) 190 feet 2 inches",
            "d) 122 feet 0 inches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The KC-46 has a wingspan of 157 feet 8 inches (48.1m). Further, the aircraft measures 165 feet 6 inches (50.5m) in length."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "What is the payload of the Boeing KC-46 Pegasus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 49,500 kg",
            "b) 29,500 kg",
            "c) 20,000 kg",
            "d) 60,000 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Boeing KC-46 Pegasus aircraft has seating for up to 114 people. Alternatively, the aircraft can carry up to 18 463L pallets or 58 patients."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "The PW4000 engine is certified for __________ minute ETOPS if used in twinjets.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 60",
            "c) 180",
            "d) 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Boeing KC-46 Pegasus has a payload of 29,500 kg, which is approximately 65,000lb. The aircraft also has 15 permanent seats for additional air crew members."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first fifth-generation jet fighter that the KC-46 connected with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F-22",
            "b) Su-57",
            "c) J-20",
            "d) F-35A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The PW4000 engine is certified for 180 minute ETOPS if used in twinjets. The KC-46 uses a 94 inch diameter fan with a certified thrust up to 62,000lbf."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "The Boeing 747 Dreamlifter aircraft is also known as the Boeing 747-400 __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Large Cargo Glider",
            "b) Low Cargo Freighter",
            "c) Large Cargo Freighter",
            "d) Low Cargo Glider"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boeing 747 Dreamlifter aircraft is also known as the Boeing 747-400 Large Cargo Freighter. It is a wide-body cargo aircraft manufactured by Boeing."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "When was the maiden flight of the 747 Dreamlifter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9 September 2006",
            "b) 9 September 2016",
            "c) 9 September 1990",
            "d) 9 September 1984"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 747 Dreamlifter first flew on 9 September 2006. The world’s longest cargo loader is used to load cargo into the aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "The initial Boeing 747 Dreamlifter program intended to produce only _________ aircrafts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 13",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The initial Boeing 747 Dreamlifter program intended to produce only three aircrafts. However, another aircraft was subsequently added to the program and in total Four Boeing 747 Dreamlifter aircrafts have been built."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "The 747 Dreamlifter has a cruise speed of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mach 0.90",
            "b) Mach 0.82",
            "c) Mach 0.72",
            "d) Mach 0.85"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 747 Dreamlifter has a cruise speed of Mach 0.82, which is approximately 878 km/h. In comparison, the 747-400 offers a cruise speed of Mach 0.85, which is approximately 910 km/h."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an airline from which Boeing acquired the four second hand 747-400s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emirates",
            "b) China Airlines",
            "c) Air China",
            "d) Malaysia Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Emirates is not an airline from which Boeing acquired the four second hand 747-400s. However, it acquired these aircrafts from China Airlines, Air China and Malaysia Airlines."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "When was the first 747 LCF rolled out of the hangar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 17 August 2000",
            "b) 17 August 2006",
            "c) 17 August 2016",
            "d) 17 August 2002"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the 747 Dreamlifter is exclusively used for transporting Boeing 787 aircraft components. The Dreamlifter carries the fuselage and wing sections of the 787 aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "Which of the following airlines operated the LCF fleet until August 2010?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atlas Air",
            "b) Evergreen International Airlines",
            "c) Cargo Logic Air",
            "d) FedEx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the 787 aircraft parts were deemed too large for standard marine shipping. Thus, it was decided that air transport will be the favourable method for transporting parts of the Boeing 787 Dreamliner."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "The Dreamlifter can hold __________ times the volume of a 747-400F freighter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Five",
            "b) Eight",
            "c) Ten",
            "d) Three"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the cargo portion of the Dreamlifter aircraft is unpressurized. LCF conversion of the aircraft was designed partially by Boeing’s Moscow bureau and Boeing Rocket dyne."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "What is the volume of the 747 LCF main cargo compartment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 85,000 cubic feet",
            "b) 50,000 cubic feet",
            "c) 65,000 cubic feet",
            "d) 49,000 cubic feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dreamlifter can hold three times the volume of a 747-400F freighter. The aircraft is used to transport aircraft components to Boeing’s assembly plants from suppliers around the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines are used on the 747 LCF?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trent 800",
            "b) Trent 700",
            "c) PW 4062",
            "d) PW 4098"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The 747 LCF main cargo compartment can hold a volume of 65,000 cubic feet, which is approximately 1,840 cubic meters. The aircraft requires two crew members."
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "The 747 Dreamlifter offers a range of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4,200 nautical miles",
            "b) 5,300 nautical miles",
            "c) 6,700 nautical miles",
            "d) 8,000 nautical miles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boeing 747 LCF uses PW 4062 engines. The aircraft is equipped with four engines, two being mounted on each wing."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "What is the maximum takeoff weight of the 747 Dreamlifter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 664,235 kg",
            "b) 90,235 kg",
            "c) 464,235 kg",
            "d) 364,235 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 747 Dreamlifter offers a range of 4,200 nautical miles (which is approximately 7,800 km), when fully loaded. In comparison, the 747-400 offers a range of 7,260 nautical miles, when fully loaded."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "The 747 Dreamlifter measures __________ in length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 312 feet 3 inches",
            "b) 185 feet 5 inches",
            "c) 200 feet 1 inch",
            "d) 235 feet 2 inches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 747 Dreamlifter has a maximum take-off weight of 364,235 kg. The aircraft has a bulging fuselage designed to carry over sized loads."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "The Boeing CH-47 Chinook is a __________ engined rotorcraft.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mono",
            "b) Quad",
            "c) Tri",
            "d) Twin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Boeing CH-47 Chinook is a twin engined rotorcraft. It was developed by the American rotorcraft company Vertol as a transport helicopter."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "When did the Boeing CH-47 Chinook first fly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21 September 1990",
            "b) 21 September 1985",
            "c) 21 September 1961",
            "d) 21 September 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boeing CH-47 Chinook first flew on 21 September 1961. It is one of the heaviest lifting Western helicopters."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "The preproduction CH-47 was designated as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) YCH-1B",
            "b) HC-1B",
            "c) AC-1B",
            "d) CCH-1B"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The preproduction CH-47 was designated as YCH-1B. The preproduction craft performed its maiden flight on 21 September 1961."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "The CH-47D entered service in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1965",
            "b) 1982",
            "c) 2005",
            "d) 1996"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The CH-47D entered service in 1982. It was one of the most substantial variants to be produced, featuring a large number of upgradations."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the civilian version of the Chinook?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HH-47",
            "b) Boeing Vertol 234",
            "c) CH-47A",
            "d) CH-47CC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The Boeing Vertol 234 is the civilian version of the Chinook. The variant has often been used for passenger and cargo transport by a range of different civil operators."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "The CH-47 Chinook has been licensed to be built by __________ in Japan.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agusta",
            "b) Phillips",
            "c) Kawasaki",
            "d) Fujifilm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the CH-47 is powered by turboshaft engines. The craft uses two Lycoming T55 engines. The engines were designed as a scaled-up version of the smaller Lycoming T53."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "The CH-47F is powered by two __________ horsepower engines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6,733",
            "b) 4,733",
            "c) 2,365",
            "d) 50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the Boeing CH-47 was named Chinook after the Chinook people of the Pacific Northwest. Over 1,200 CH-47 have been built, as of 2012."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "The Boeing CH-47A had a maximum gross weight of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40,000lb",
            "b) 25,000lb",
            "c) 35,000lb",
            "d) 33,000lb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The CH-47 Chinook has been licensed to be built by Kawasaki in Japan. Similarly, it is licensed to be built by AgustaWestland in Italy."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "How many CH-47A were built?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 349",
            "b) 39",
            "c) 400",
            "d) 68"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The CH-47F is powered by two 4,733 horsepower engines. The engines are manufactured by Honeywell. The CH-47F is the latest mainstream generation variant of the CH-47."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "Which of the following was unofficially referred to as Guns A Go Go?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CHH-47B",
            "b) ACH-47A",
            "c) CH-47C",
            "d) MH-47D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the earlier Chinook design was limited by its rotor system. This is because the system did not permit full usage of the installed power."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "The Super C version of the CH-47C delivered __________ shp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 575",
            "b) 1,750",
            "c) 8,750",
            "d) 3,750"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Boeing CH-47A had a maximum gross weight of 33,000lb. Further, the craft allowed for a maximum payload of around 10,000lb."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "How much payload can the CH-47D carry externally?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 26,000 pounds",
            "b) 35,000 pounds",
            "c) 10,000 pounds",
            "d) 18,000 pounds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The CH-47D can carry a payload of 26,000 pounds (approximately 12 tons), externally. It can also carry heavy payloads internally. The CH-47D was first introduced into service in 1979."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Which of the following has inflight refueling capability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CH-47B",
            "b) CH-47A",
            "c) MH-47D",
            "d) CH-47J"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the CH-47D has advanced avionics. It features the Global Positioning System, which provides improved navigation and tracking capabilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "The CH-47F is an upgraded version of the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CH-47J",
            "b) CH-47D",
            "c) MH-47D",
            "d) CH-47C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The MH-47D craft featured inflight refuelling capabilities and was thus different from its other variants. This variant was equipped with major upgrades and a special rope rappelling system."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "What is the full form of DAFCS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Digital Advanced Flight Control System",
            "b) Direct Advanced Flight Control System",
            "c) Digital Automatic Flight Control System",
            "d) Direct Automatic Flight Control System"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The CH-47F is an upgraded version of the CH-47D. The craft first flew on 23 October 2006 and was equipped with an upgraded engine."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "A Boeing CH-47F Block 2 is planned to be introduced after __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2030",
            "b) 2015",
            "c) 2020",
            "d) 2025"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, the CH-47F can fly at speeds of over 175 mph (282 km/h), while carrying a payload of more than 21,000lb (9.5 tons)."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "The Boeing CH-47 is planned to be in service beyond __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2025",
            "b) 2030",
            "c) 2010",
            "d) 2060"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: DAFCS refers to Digital Advanced Flight Control System. The CH-47F features such systems. The system is manufactured BAE Systems and is part of the avionics."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Which of the following is similar to the MH-47E?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CH-47G",
            "b) MH-47G",
            "c) CH-47F",
            "d) HH-47"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A Boeing CH-47F Block 2 is planned to be introduced after 2020. It aims for a payload of 22,000lb along with high and hot hover performance, and an increased MTOW."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an operator of the Boeing CH-47 Chinook?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bolivia",
            "b) Japan",
            "c) Italy",
            "d) India"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Boeing CH-47 is planned to be in service beyond 2060. Thus it will be in service over 100 years after first entering service."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "What is the service ceiling of the CH-47?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35,000 feet",
            "b) 40,000 feet",
            "c) 25,000 feet",
            "d) 20,000 feet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The MH-47G is similar to the MH-47E. However, it features more sophisticated avionics including a Digital Common Avionics Architecture System (CAAS)."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Which of the following provides the Common Avionics Architecture System for the Boeing CH-47?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolls Royce",
            "b) BAE Systems",
            "c) Rockwell Collins",
            "d) BMW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, the CH-47C Plus was the export version of the CH-47C Chinook for the Italian Army. Export models were designated differently."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Which of the following is equipped with CFM LEAP-1B engines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BBJ1",
            "b) BBJ C",
            "c) BBJ3",
            "d) BBJ MAX 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The BBJ MAX 9 is equipped with CFM LEAP-1B engines. The aircraft is based on the Boeing 737 MAX 9 and features advanced winglets."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "When did the BBJ first fly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 September 1990",
            "b) 4 September 2008",
            "c) 4 September 1998",
            "d) 4 September 2018"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The BBJ first flew on 4 September 1998. Production for the BBJ series started in 1998 and the aircrafts are still in use all around the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "Which of the following is based on the 737-800?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BBJ MAX 8",
            "b) BBJ3",
            "c) BBJ C",
            "d) BBJ2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The BBJ2 is based on the 737-800. The aircraft, introduced in 2002, offers a 25% larger cabin providing a similar range with five fuel tanks."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "The BBJ MAX 7 has a __________ nautical mile range.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5,000",
            "b) 7,000",
            "c) 8,500",
            "d) 3,500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The BBJ MAX 7 has a 7,000 nautical mile (approximately 12,960 km) range. The aircraft offers 10% lower operating costs as compared to the original BBJ while having a longer cabin."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "The first BBJ is based on the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 737 MAX",
            "b) 737-800",
            "c) 737-200",
            "d) 737-700"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The first BBJ is based on the 737-700. The aircraft offered a stronger wing and landing gear as compared to the 737-800."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "The Boeing Business Jet division offers __________ products derived from different Boeing airliners.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 11",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the BBJ MAX 8 has a 6,325 nautical mile range, which is approximately 11,710km. The BBJ MAX 8 is based on the Boeing 737 MAX 8 aircraft."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "The Boeing Business Jet series is based on the _________ airliner.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 757",
            "b) 737",
            "c) 787",
            "d) 777"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False, the Boeing Business Jets are equipped with two engines. The engine may vary depending on the aircraft. For example, the BBJ MAX 9 uses engines manufactured by CFM International."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a wide body model of the BBJ?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B777",
            "b) BBJ3",
            "c) BBJ2",
            "d) BBJ MAX 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Boeing Business Jet division offers 11 products derived from different Boeing airliners. The aircraft series offers corporate jet configurations based on airliners such as the 777 and 737."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "What is the maximum payload of the BBJ MAX 9?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 38,600lb",
            "b) 32,600lb",
            "c) 45,600lb",
            "d) 52,600lb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Boeing Business Jet series is based on the 737 airliner. The aircrafts are variants of Boeing jet airliners manufactured for the corporate jet market."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines is used on the BBJ 777-8?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trent 800",
            "b) Trent 700",
            "c) GEnx-2B67",
            "d) General Electric GE9X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, the BBJ MAX 8 offers a range up to 6,640 nautical miles, which is approximately 12,297 km. The BBJ MAX 7 offers a better range as compared to the BBJ MAX 8."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "The BBJ 787-8 measures __________ in length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 158 inch 1 inch",
            "b) 200 feet 10 inch",
            "c) 186 feet 1 inch",
            "d) 213 feet 3 inch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The B777 is a wide body model of the BBJ. In December 2018, the BBJ 777X succeeded the BBJ 777. The -200LR variant offers a range of 10,030 nautical miles."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a BBJ operator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Japan",
            "b) India",
            "c) Australia",
            "d) Malaysia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The BBJ MAX 9 offers a maximum payload of 38,600lb, which is approximately 17,509kg. In comparison, the BBJ MAX 8 offers a maximum payload of 35,510lb, which is approximately 16,107kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "When did the Boeing 757 first fly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 19 February 2005",
            "b) 19 February 1952",
            "c) 19 February 1997",
            "d) 19 February 1982"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Boeing 757 first flew on 19 February 1982. It is a mid-sized, narrow body short to medium range aircraft that is equipped with two engines."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "Which of the following engines are used on the Boeing 757?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turboprop",
            "b) Turboshaft",
            "c) Turbofan",
            "d) Turbojet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Turbofan engines are used on the Boeing 757. These engines provide sufficient power and allow takeoffs from relatively short runways and higher altitudes."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "The 757 was intended to replace the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 727",
            "b) 767",
            "c) 777",
            "d) 787"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 757 was intended to replace the 727. The aircraft featured a conventional tail and a supercritical wing design in order to reduced aerodynamic drag."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "When did the production of the 757 end?",
        "Options": [
            "a) November 2016",
            "b) November 2010",
            "c) October 2004",
            "d) October 2008"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Production of the 757 ended in October 2004. The most popular model was the 757-200, of which 913 units were built. A total of 1,050 757s had been built for 54 customers."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "The last 757 was delivered to which of the following airlines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thai Airways",
            "b) Air India",
            "c) Shanghai Airlines",
            "d) Malaysia Airlines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The last 757 was delivered to shanghai airlines, in November 2005. Declining sales amidst an airline industry trend towards smaller jetliners led the manufacturer to end production."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "The wings of a 757 are swept at __________ degrees.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, Eastern Air Lines was the launch customer of the 757. British Airways was another launch customer. The two became the first carriers to publicly commit to the 7N7."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "Which of the following supplies CRT screens for the 757?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BAE Systems",
            "b) Rockwell Collins",
            "c) General Electric",
            "d) Mercedes Benz"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True, pilots rated on the 757 could be qualified to fly the 767. This is because both aircrafts had a common type rating thus allowing a pilot to fly both aircrafts."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a stretched variant of the Boeing 757?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 757-200PF",
            "b) 757-200",
            "c) 757-200M",
            "d) 757-300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wings of a 757 are swept at 25 degrees. Further, the wings are largely identical across all 757 variants and each wing features a supercritical cross-section."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "What is the maximum takeoff weight of the 757-200?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 255,000 pounds",
            "b) 355,000 pounds",
            "c) 455,000 pounds",
            "d) 155,000 pounds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rockwell Collins supplies CRT screens for the 757. The aircraft flight deck is equipped with six CRT screens to display flight instrumentation."
    }
]